<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels :)</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Introduction to Shovels</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/introduction-to-shovels/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2022-11-08:/blog/introduction-to-shovels/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels launched in November 2022 to bring more transparency into construction and building data.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Ryan Buckley sent this newsletter about the launch of Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hello friends, advisors, and (a few) relatives! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of a hiatus, I'm really excited to launch a new company along with an incredible team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process has been a journey. Thanks again to those of you who suffered through my many explanations of half-baked ideas and more than a few false starts. This time is different! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to introduce Shovels, a new way to discover and evaluate building contractors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an agency problem in the trades. In my economics classes we called it "information asymmetry," a term popularized by Nobel Prize winner Joseph Stiglitz who proved that this asymmetry leads to inefficient markets. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, you don't need an economics degree to know that hiring a home contractor is fraught with risk. Just talk to anyone who's done it. More often than not, and far more frequently than any other hiring decision I can think of, it's a bad experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is contractors have far more knowledge of their skill level and fit for the job than the people who hire and finance them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels does a few things to address the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We scrape all permits and associate them with contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We include all permit inspections and their results &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do this across multiple jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we crunch the numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a very compelling new way to look at contractor skill level and job fit. We're calculating new metrics like inspection pass rate and construction speed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These metrics are predictive of project outcomes: we know what good and bad contractors look like. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear over and over again how the entire construction industry is slow to adopt new technology. The field is littered with startups who failed to get contractors to adopt a new app. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we're not trying to be in the field. Instead, we're in the offices of the people who decide who to hire and fund and we gather data from the municipalities that issue and inspect building permits. This part of the construction industry is moving online and we're able to take advantage of it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we built&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototype is live! It only has Contra Costa County data (about five years worth) but it's enough to see who the major builders are and it shows their key metrics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out: https://app.shovels.ai/register/. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we're building next&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to pull in seven of the nine Bay Area counties this month. That effort will really showcase the power of Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most contractors work in multiple counties and this data isn't centralized anywhere. It takes some heavy technical lifting to grab it all, but we have the expertise to do it. Once this historical data is pulled, we'll continue to update the open permits and grab new permits daily. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The climate angle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been telling everyone that my next thing will be climate-related. That's still true. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, our first paying customer is a climate tech company :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very likely our first several paying customers will be green building contractors, financiers, consultants, and data aggregators. We'll be able to track the proliferation of green buildings and see who's doing the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on all that is here: https://www.shovels.ai/climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Who we are&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but certainly not least, I want to share a couple of things about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am co-founder and CEO. I just stepped away as CEO of MightySignal after Airnow acquired us last year. We did a ton of data scraping and analysis there and my own (great, fortunately) experience with a major home remodel inspired Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luka Kacil is my co-founder and CTO. He is supremely talented and someone I look forward to being in the trenches with. We met through MightySignal when we acquired his company, AppMonsta, back in 2019. He built and managed the tech stack to scrape all of the Google Play and Apple App stores daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have a small team of part-time folks doing hands-on work in data analysis and marketing support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="launch"></category></entry><entry><title>December 2022 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/december-2022-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2022-12-13:/blog/december-2022-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have a better problem statement and understanding of our customers!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Dec 2022 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few things I've been thinking about recently with this business, but I'll start with an ask:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to talk to more real estate developers, especially if they're active in Contra Costa County or in the broader SF Bay Area. If you have a friendly one you can intro to me, I'd appreciate it! I want to understand how they vet and hire contractors.
That aside, here's a quick summary and then I'll get into more detail on each item. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've improved the way I describe the problem we're solving and our solution for fixing it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We encountered some new challenges that are slowing us down -- but also increasing our resolve because hey, the harder it is, the more value we're creating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had great conversations with people who match our three ideal customer profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I made a bunch of progress on boring back office operational stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some fundraising progress was had&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Our problem and how we solve it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is information asymmetry in the labor market for the trades, and this mismatch leads to transactions that make both sides worse off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There, that's the problem! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one that homeowners, construction lenders, and real estate developers each have to deal with. The way we solve it is to aggregate building permit and related data and objectively assess the work that these guys do. We use source data to provide the transparency lacking in this market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach is unique, and I'll describe why in the next section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;New data challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew aggregating this data would be hard. We didn't know it would be this hard. The challenge is several-fold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no clean public datasets for the detail we want to collect, so we have to find "interesting" ways to grab it.
Once we have it, the data is inconsistent and incomplete. It needs a good amount of TLC. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is distributed among counties and cities, and isn't always online. Sometimes have to make public records requests to get it.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But that's what makes this work valuable and worth doing. It's also why no one else has already done it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will get easier, too -- I'm hearing directly from city clerks that they're in the process of bringing building permits online. That's encouraging, both for my co-founder Luka, who has to deal with most of this, and for us generally because it means our timing is good. It feels like we're catching the wave for clean, accessible government data, and we can be among the players that bring this critical trend* fully ashore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conversations with potential customers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to several "bulls-eye" potential customers. They're exactly the profiles who would want to work with us. Here are a few takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The contractor marketplaces (Thumbtack, BuildZoom, etc) seem to refer contractors with whom they have referral agreements. It leads to bad matches and creates distrust on the buy side. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real estate developers already use public permit databases to see which contractors are active in a region. It's a tedious process that takes several hours to identify a single contractor. The time sink multiplies for every new jurisdiction they have to research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no database available today to look up a property address and get its permit history. 
What does this mean to me? We have work to do! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These potential customers will remain "potential" until we can get more data coverage, which leads me to...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back office and fundraising&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels, Inc. is now officially a Delaware C-corp. We have a bank account, a Stripe account, and real paying customers. I have a CRM flush with conversations to stay on top of. This is a real milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get us even further, we will need to raise a small seed round. I'm talking every day to friends who are making introductions, advisors who critique our pitch deck, and people in the angel and venture investing community who are taking a hard look at Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm hearing so far is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to describe the market size better. Luka and I are working on this, but there's no specific market report for what we do. Our total available market calculation is a bit haphazard. I know it's huge, but I have yet to prove it :) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more customers we get, the easier it will be to fundraise. I'm working on those customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construction tech is a tricky area to fundraise. It's not your typical market and many investors shy away. They just don't get it. That's okay -- we're finding others who lean in right away. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently received our first offer. We were invited to join a venture studio that would handle a lot of the operations for us, effectively an "in-kind" investment of $500,000+. Ultimately we decided this one was not a great fit, so we're going to focus on raising a seed round instead. It was a good vote of confidence, though. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for now. Luka is busy grabbing all the data we can in the SF Bay Area. I'm keeping the revenue and fundraising operation together. It's a grind, but I wouldn't rather be doing anything else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy holidays! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Our first newsletter is &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/introduction-to-shovels/"&gt;on the blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
* Why is taking building permits online critical? Let me ascend my climate change soapbox for a moment. Homes need to electrify. It's inevitable that every building will disconnect its gas line in the next 50 years. Getting there requires streamlining the bureaucratic mess that is building permits. We all hate it, so let's make it better. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>February 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/february-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-02-16:/blog/february-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We raised money and increased prices!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Feb 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot to cover, so I'll summarize first and then get into some detail for those who wish to read on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We raised a seed round from legit investors and angels, and I plan to gather signatures and checks next week! We'll announce details soon thereafter. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've had dozens of great conversations with property technology and construction financing companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a roadmap and budget for the year. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We increased our price to $1,000/mo per metro area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also continue to work through data challenges -- to be expected in this corner of the Internet. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Heroes" src="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/february-2023-newsletter/heroes.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pic of Luka and me amid a hero's journey through the mystical and enchanted world of building permit databases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I took this screenshot, we had recently discovered that there were 45 more permitting jurisdictions than we expected in the SF Bay Area. We'd just committed to a customer that we could scrape all of them. My screen froze during our meeting, and I took this pic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around this time, a friend and fellow entrepreneur texted me to ask how things were going with Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We've hit the bogs," I wrote back. "We're plodding through the shit." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"That's my favorite part!" he replied. Usually, it's mine too, but I was stressed and worried at that moment. What else had I underestimated? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did mention this was a hero's journey, right? A hero sets out on a high-risk adventure, encounters adversity, and overcomes it. The arc of entrepreneurship is one long hero's journey, but within that long arc are countless smaller ones. This data challenge is an example of one of those smaller arcs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll cut to the chase: we set out to grab all permits in the SF Bay Area. We encountered much more work than expected, fretted for a couple of weeks, and then found a solution. Huzzah! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're now purchasing raw permit and inspection data from a data vendor. Remarkably, this simple development led to a string of wins over the last couple of months. It's why I skipped the January newsletter -- I wanted to include the next win before sending it, and the wins just kept coming, so I never clicked send. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here we are in mid-February, so I'm just going to send. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons from our fundraise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's never easy, but I have to say, it felt like we had something akin to "investor-market-fit." The firms that passed did so for a few common reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're too early. Not enough revenue or traction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're not focused enough on climate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They're not familiar enough with proptech / construction tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our best conversations were with firms who:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believe in B2B and are willing to invest in new markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appreciate my background in VC and PE-backed startups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like data-as-a-service business models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fund that I was excited about turned us down because they were too close to the contractor data market. He spent years working at one of the big contractor marketplaces. When he declined to invest, he gave me the best advice: "You need to find an investor who is as irrationally excited about this idea as you are." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This advice stuck with me, and I remained optimistic that I would find some irrationally excited funds and angel investors. And that's what happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll announce who they are once we're signed, sealed, and delivered 😁.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons from my many customer interviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's one piece of startup advice that I hear over and over again, it's this: interview customers from day 1... and never stop. I have taken this to heart. I have customer calls nearly every day. Usually multiple. I have learned A LOT. Here are some highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like investors, the best meetings come from referrals. I get a call nearly every time someone we both know introduces me. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold emailing is getting a lot harder. When it works, it works well, but it's a numbers game, and I have to get lucky. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proptech customers have many uses for clean and processed permit data. Their needs are unique, but our delivery is the same. They all want to store this data internally. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many would pay a premium for weekly or daily permit data refreshes rather than monthly updates. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construction banks can use our processed data for underwriting and loan draw decisions, but they need broad coverage to see the value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've given quotes ranging from $500/mo to $10,000/mo. I love that. Our geographic coverage is the only thing keeping me from closing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Asks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're hiring! We'd appreciate any candidate intros. Feel free to share these job descriptions: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://broadleaf-leech-f9b.notion.site/Growth-Marketer-4a35d1c91875485eaee25c72b77fedf1"&gt;Marketer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://broadleaf-leech-f9b.notion.site/Data-Engineer-8c88bef8282d4d0ebdf74178c5e737d4"&gt;Data Engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intros to construction loan people. I want more interviews. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intros to developers who do 10+ projects at a time in the Bay Area. I need to learn more from this segment. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next note will officially announce our funding round, and then probably we'll settle into a quarterly update to all of you friends and/or family and/or investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for your support! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>March 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/march-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-03-15:/blog/march-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We raised over $600,000 and have a robust roadmap&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Mar 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greetings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the special fundraising update email and other updates since last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have raised $610,000 so far, with more likely to come in the next few weeks! (Timing likely will be delayed by the Silicon Valley Bank failure and related malaise.) This money is in the bank, so it's official.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm still taking a few very strategic fundraising calls. We don't need more money, but I'm receptive to any investors who could help us find product-market fit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of product-market fit, that's top of mind now and will remain so for the foreseeable future. Expect this to be the central topic of these newsletters going forward!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And to that end, I completely rewrote &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago. It still needs some color, but I'm happy with the copy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We released a &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/e440a465-a280-44be-aa81-5388b8ac20ff"&gt;Green Contractor Directory&lt;/a&gt; prototype!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fundraise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to share that our lead investor is Zach Coelius from &lt;a href="https://coelius.vc/"&gt;Coelius Capital&lt;/a&gt;. He's an ideal lead for us. I've known of Zach for years. We've been in the same circles but didn't really connect until late last year after I attended one of his dinners in San Francisco. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zach knows the super early stages as well as anybody. He'll be a great sounding board as we come up against critical decisions and can help us raise funds to accelerate growth if needed. We're delighted to have his support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other angel investors, whom I won't name directly but can describe as old friends, new friends, former bosses, and fans of my personal blog, were the first to sign and send their checks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luka and I are humbled and grateful -- and ready to get back to work :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to learn. The permit and contractor data landscape is evolving rapidly, and we are a player in this space. The other companies are aware of us and reacting to our presence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I'm good at, perhaps because I enjoy doing it, is getting to know my neighbors. I like to be friendly with my business neighbors, too. I want to know everyone in the market. Not just know their names, but meet them, exchange messages, and (try to) be friends. It doesn't always work, but when it does, it leads to profit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Businesses that look like competitors can turn out to be partners, customers, or lead to friendly mergers. This has happened at every company I've run. It happened again recently with Shovels. I'm really happy about this development because it opens up a big opportunity for us in the contractor data market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contractor data is what I said we'd do in the early days of Shovels. Late last year, though, I became very excited about permit data. I saw a huge opportunity there. I still see it. I'd reach out or be introduced to potential customers under the pretense of contractor data and discover that what they really wanted was permits. It's a huge opportunity, but I don't think it's ours to get. We don't have enough value to add there; the incumbents will meet this need well and soon enough. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contractor data is a different story. It's underserved, and we have a tremendous opportunity right now to fill the void. I describe the four segments on &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt;: software, climate, finance, and builders. I'll write more detail about all four in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coming Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a very exciting product roadmap! We're going to expand our little &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/e440a465-a280-44be-aa81-5388b8ac20ff"&gt;green contractor prototype&lt;/a&gt;. We're going to make all of the San Francisco Bay Area available; this demo currently has only 500 records.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to release an API (application programming interface -- a way for computer programmers to easily access this data) and put contractor landing pages up on our website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next quarter, we're going to layer on additional datasets to make the contractor information even more insightful. I'll share more details on these data layers soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we're going deep on contractor data and we're starting in the SF Bay Area. I'll share more next month when more products are released! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>April 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/april-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-04-20:/blog/april-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We've now raised about $1M and we're super close to releasing v2 of our prototype&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels April 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few more updates since last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have now raised $960,000, up from $610,000 last month. We're very grateful for the investor support and ready to prove that customers are equally excited about what we're building. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have more detail on the ICPs (ideal customer profiles) we're targeting. The picture continues to get clearer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're also excited about AI/GPT/LLMs, etc. I'll share a couple of snippets about how we're using this latest (justifiably) hyped up technology. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new data is coming, and we have plans to go national. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fundraise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're very pleased to add &lt;a href="https://www.coolclimatecollective.com/"&gt;Cool Climate Collective&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://venture.angellist.com/zach-coelius/syndicate"&gt;Coelius Syndicate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.coolclimatecollective.com/"&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.manaventures.vc/"&gt;Mana Ventures&lt;/a&gt; to our list of investors. We also added another friendly angel. We'll close this seed round at just over $1M, punt any new interest to the next round, and focus 100% on execution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ideal Customer Profiles (ICPs)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still do customer interviews every day. It's incredibly helpful. Although I'm eager to actually close deals, since it's taken longer to process the data we've acquired than we originally anticipated, I'm able to have more wide-ranging conversations. I'm not held back by what we have in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm learning that there are all sorts of problems that can be addressed with permit data. We can go very deep into pre-construction timelines, serving information about approval steps, costs, and timing. My focus previously was on construction, what happens once the permit is approved. There's a whole other world of pre-construction data going back to when a permit is submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serving this market will require going deeper into planning departments, requesting data from public utilities, and even scanning planning commission minutes and agendas. We can't do all of this tomorrow, but it feels well within the scope of Shovels to tackle it eventually. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, our latest ICPs look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Construction loan portfolio manager at a bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: Limited information about contractor quality when asked to underwrite a new loan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Contractor metrics and permits summary delivered as a PDF&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Construction loan fund controller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No idea what else a contractor is working on when they're asked to approve a loan draw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solutions&lt;/em&gt;: Current and past contractor metrics and permits history delivered as JSON via API, and webhooks for permit processing time changes in a set of jurisdictions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Large condo developer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No visibility into pre-construction permit timelines in a given jurisdiction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Web app interface to look up detailed permit and planning approval timelines in different cities and counties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Proptech CEO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No programmatic way to see if a house has an active permit already&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Permits delivered on a given address via API&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you fall into these buckets. If you want to chat, please get in touch! You know I like a good brainstorm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As these ideas firm up further, I'll incorporate them "officially" into our website copy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the AI stuff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll admit it -- I registered shovels.ai because it was the only decent "shovels" domain available. But I'm sure glad we got it! I had no idea AI was going to blow up like this in the months following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual AI application here is pretty obvious. Permits come with a lot of data and not all of it is structured. The AI models do a fantastic job of quickly (meaning: without any contextual training) identifying what the permit is about (meaning: categorizing it). That's just out of the box. We can train AI models to get better over time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are front-end uses too. You could imagine asking a chat-like interface about permits on a property, permits performed by a contractor, or who should remodel your kitchen. A lot of people would be excited about this, and we have a role to play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going national&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're working out a way for us to expand nationally very quickly. It's a direct result of the ICP discussions I've had recently: geographically-constrained data isn't nearly as valuable as national scope. It's a tricky dance but we're making headway and working towards a deal. I hope to be able to announce it next month! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>May 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/may-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-05-24:/blog/may-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;More on our final fundraising number and how we plan to spend it&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels May 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few more updates since April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our final fundraising total is $1,071,939.39. I'm happy to connect with any additional interest but we'll ultimately push it to the next round. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hired a full-time data engineer and two summer interns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of our interns made a chat AI interface to the &lt;a href="https://api.shovels.ai/docs"&gt;Shovels API&lt;/a&gt;. We're going to incorporate it into a new website we're building this summer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're thinking a lot about building and zoning laws. Aren't you?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National data coverage is right around the corner. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fundraise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a wrap! We set out to to raise $1M, pared it back to $500K, then raised the target to $750K and then back again to $1M. Fundraising is hard. It was hard for us too, but I think we did a few things right and caught a bit of good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll share a few learnings here about the fundraising process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was told by a climate tech CEO who recently raised several million dollars that I should expect to pitch 100 VCs. She generously shared her VC list with me. I ended up pitching about 20 before finding a lead investor, and then about 20 more to fill out the round to $1M.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing beats customer interviews. I didn't know this at the time, but I refined my investor pitch each time I spoke to a prospect interested in building permit data. It helped me choose the right language, define the right need, and formulate a solution that makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes sense to customers also makes sense to investors. It makes sense that these pitches should be quite similar. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It helps to be unique. Investors don't hear a lot of pitches about building permit data, so Shovels doesn't sound like anything else. I can use that to capture their imaginations, and I've learned from customer interviews about the many uses that permit data can have in the pre- and post-construction phases. I can make Shovels sound big &lt;em&gt;because it's true&lt;/em&gt;. This can be a VERY big business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investors and customers love the Shovels brand. We lucked into that bit of inspiration (the first domain I bought for this project was ChooseAGC -- "choose a general contractor" -- not nearly as cool). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And we got lucky that our lead investor bought in right away and has stood by us the rest of the fundraising journey.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operating Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to share a bit of high-level strategy about how we operate Shovels, which also worked well when fundraising. For anyone who knows me and reads my stuff, this strategy below should not be surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two central operating principles in our 2023 budget:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to breakeven as quickly as possible. This means staying lean for as long as possible and offsetting expenses with related revenue wherever possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert investment into ARR. This ensures a good return for investors as well as founders. It’s &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; equity we’re selling, after all! If we raise $1M, we want to be at a $1M annual revenue run rate when we start fundraising the next round.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these principles in mind, our financial projections are modeled with the following results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total burn of about $500K. We want to spend no more than half of funds raised before reaching breakeven, so we’ll still have powder left for growth experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peak burn of about $70K/mo. High fixed costs are salaries and data acquisition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will be at breakeven by summer 2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the assumptions built into this model are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can limit churn to 1% per month and upsell at 0.5% per month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luka can get by with 1 data engineer to breakeven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ryan can get by with 2 junior sales or 1 senior sales person to breakeven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our ACV is at least $1,000/mo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our product works and excites our customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can reach profitability by selling just our API products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to leverage my background with Xenon Partners to execute on revenue while being sensitive to cash flow by utilizing SEO and high impact content on target social media networks for market development. I also expect that our product will be great and we’ll continue to get word-of-mouth referrals because my co-founder is a badass CTO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most investors liked, if not &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt;, this message. The ones that weren't impressed, I wouldn't want to work with anyway. It's an important filter for me so I was very open about it. Plus, it's true. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did hire two summer interns. Luka got his data engineer (Petra is fantastic!) and I'm still experimenting with some sales strategies before hiring anyone full-time. In sum these are not insignificant expenses, but I can justify them 100% knowing that everyone at Shovels is working towards one goal right now: &lt;strong&gt;get revenue as fast as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More thinking about AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing from last month's newsletter, I have a few updates to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This summer we're looking at all the large language model (LLM) options and figuring out the right tech stack to use to process millions of permit records through it for permit classification and entity extraction (appliances, rooms, quantities, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We found another niche in municipal building and planning codes. Someone (might as well be us!) needs to load them into a LLM and use the LLM to figure out what the building rules are: setbacks, height limits, density requirements. These rules can completely disrupt the economics of a large project and they're very difficult to find and update. AI to the rescue! I know we're not the only ones with our eyes on this problem. Solving it is a stretch goal for the summer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, I see good data as our competitive advantage in the coming AI wars. Try asking Bard or ChatGPT what permits have been issued in a given zip code. They can't do it, but we can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going national&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We signed a deal today to get national data starting on June 1. We're working overtime to prep the data pipelines for this influx of data and we'll start reaching out to those of you who have been asking for this for months. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>Go-to-market strategies for proptech companies</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-06-22:/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn how to create an effective go-to-market plan for proptech companies that will help them reach their target audiences and maximize success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you a proptech company looking to reach your target audience? It can be a challenge to penetrate the tech landscape and get your message out there. However, with the right strategies in place, you can create an effective go-to-market plan that will make sure your message is heard loud and clear. In this blog post, we'll outline the necessary steps to take for proptech companies to effectively reach their target audiences. We'll cover understanding the proptech landscape, developing target audience personas, creating a go-to-market plan using building permits, choosing the right technologies for your proptech company, and measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. Read on to learn more about how you can maximize your success with these strategies and tools! And don't forget to read our &lt;a href="https://api.shovels.ai/docs"&gt;API docs&lt;/a&gt; and view more pages on &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai"&gt;Shovels&lt;/a&gt; for even more tips!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Understanding the proptech landscape&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proptech, or property technology, is revolutionizing the real estate industry. By leveraging cutting-edge technologies such as big data, cloud computing, the Internet of Things (IoT), and artificial intelligence (AI), proptech companies are creating innovative products and services that are transforming how people live and work with an emphasis on property data. In this section, we will discuss what proptech is and its different categories, the impact of proptech on the real estate industry, highlight some of the most successful proptech companies and their strategies, and share examples of how proptech is transforming how people live and work with an emphasis on property data including building permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, proptech consists of software solutions developed to improve efficiency in real estate transactions. It can be divided into three categories; product/service innovation – aimed at improving customer experiences; process automation – aimed at streamlining internal processes; and data-driven analytics – focused on gaining insights from a large amount of data to improve operations. These categories are helping to drive efficiency in both residential and commercial markets across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of proptech has been far-reaching in the real estate industry. From streamlining processes for tenants to providing more detailed insights into market trends for buyers - these technological solutions have enabled businesses to make better decisions faster than ever before. Additionally, they have allowed them to provide their customers with a better experience by utilizing tools such as virtual reality tours or digital payment options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most successful proptech companies include &lt;a href="https://www.zillow.com/"&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.wework.com/"&gt;WeWork&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.compass.com/"&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.redfin.com/"&gt;Redfin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.opendoor.com/"&gt;OpenDoor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.divvyhomes.com/"&gt;Divvy&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.reonomy.com/"&gt;Reonomy&lt;/a&gt; to name a few. Each company has its own unique strategy for success but all have leveraged technology to create products that make it easier for consumers to access information about properties or facilitate transactions quickly and conveniently online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to providing convenience for consumers searching for properties or looking to close a transaction quickly, proptech solutions like building permits also benefit businesses by giving them access to up-to-date information about local regulations quickly so they can avoid compliance issues or costly delays during development projects. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.accela.com/"&gt;Accela's&lt;/a&gt; govtech permit module enables users to easily search for permits within their city or county in order to view detailed information about each permit including who applied for it when it was filed and when it was granted or denied. This not only saves time but also helps developers stay informed about local rules while planning new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, proptech offers tremendous potential both for consumers who are looking for more convenient ways of accessing information about properties or closing a transaction quickly, as well as businesses who need access up -to -date information quickly in order stay compliant with local regulations while planning projects. By leveraging these technologies, proptech companies can create effective go-to-market strategies that will help them reach their target audiences effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Developing target audience personas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing target audience personas is an important step for proptech companies to reach their customers. Personas define the characteristics of a customer segment, allowing businesses to create marketing strategies that are tailored to the specific needs and desires of that group. By understanding their target audience, proptech companies can craft effective messaging that resonates with them and helps them achieve their goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing target audience personas should be done during the planning phase of any go-to-market strategy as it will inform all subsequent decisions about how best to reach those customers. It’s also important for a proptech company to analyze customer behavior in order to determine what types of messaging they respond most positively towards. For example, understanding which channels they use most frequently and what types of content they consume can help inform which methods would be most effective for reaching them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permits are another key tool for understanding when a persona is in the market for a proptech purchase. Building permits offer insight into when people are ready or likely to invest in property technology products or services such as automated home energy monitors, smart security systems, or heat pump HVAC systems. By leveraging this data, businesses can customize their go-to-market plan accordingly and ensure that their message reaches potential customers at the right time with maximum impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, proptech companies can create effective marketing strategies tailored towards their desired audiences that will help them maximize success and reach their goals. Developing comprehensive target audience personas is key for any business looking to make an impact with its go-to-market strategy, and especially so for those operating within the ever-evolving proptech landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating a go-to-market plan using building permits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a go-to-market plan using building permits is an important step for just about every proptech company. Building permits are documents that allow businesses to carry out construction or renovation projects, and they provide valuable information on who the target market is for a particular proptech product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main types of building permits: residential and commercial. Residential building permits refer to those issued for homes, such as single-family residences or duplexes, while commercial building permits refer to those issued for large-scale projects, such as multi-family dwellings or retail stores. Understanding these permit types can help proptech companies determine which types of customers will benefit most from their products or services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if a proptech company is offering a smart home energy management system, they might look for recently approved residential building permits in order to identify potential buyers who would be interested in the product. On the other hand, if the proptech company offers a cloud-based property management system suitable for large buildings with multiple tenants, then they may look at recently approved commercial building permits in order to find potential customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there's a tool available that makes it easier to quickly find homeowners and contractors who have recently submitted or completed a building permit: Shovels. With Shovels, proptech companies can use advanced search tools and filters to narrow down potential customers based on criteria such as location and type of project (residential vs. commercial). This allows them to create targeted marketing strategies tailored specifically towards their target audiences more efficiently than traditional methods like cold calling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the right technologies like Shovels and understanding how building permits work as part of their go-to-market strategy, proptech companies can reach their target customers more effectively and maximize their success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing the right technologies for your proptech company&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right technologies for your proptech company is essential for reaching out to your target audiences and maximizing success. The technologies you choose should be tailored to the needs of your business, so it’s important to take the time to research what’s available and understand how they can work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most effective ways to reach out to potential customers is through direct mail. &lt;a href="https://www.lob.com/"&gt;Lob&lt;/a&gt; is a valuable tool for proptech companies, as it allows them to send out direct mail pieces with a home address on them. This helps build trust between potential customers and your brand, as it shows that you’re willing to put in the extra effort when communicating with them, especially when using building permits to reach out at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way of reaching out via phone or email is by using a homeowner phone and email database. These databases allow you to access contact information for potential customers, allowing you to connect directly with personalized messages that speak to their specific projects. You can also use these databases to track customer behavior over time, giving you a better understanding of who your target audience is and how best to reach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, hiring a software consultant or using your engineering team can help stitch APIs together and automate processes such as data collection and analysis. This means that all the data collected from different sources will be automatically compiled into one place, allowing you to make more informed decisions about which technologies are best suited for your business goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By selecting the right technologies for your proptech company, you can create an effective go-to-market strategy that will help you reach your target audiences and maximize success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success is essential for proptech companies that want to maximize their return on investment. Proptech companies can use a variety of strategies to measure and optimize their success, such as regularly analyzing data, conducting A/B tests, and taking customer feedback into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analyzing data regularly is one of the most important strategies for measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. By looking at data trends over time, proptech companies can better understand how their marketing efforts are performing in terms of website visits, conversions, customer satisfaction scores, etc., as well as identify any potential issues or anomalies. This allows them to make informed decisions about how to tweak campaigns or products in order to maximize performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A/B testing is another powerful tool that proptech companies can use to measure the effectiveness of changes they have made to their marketing efforts. A/B testing involves creating two versions of a piece of content (e.g., an email) and then testing both versions on different audiences in order to determine which one performs better. This technique enables proptech companies to experiment with different approaches without having to guess what will work best for their target customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, taking customer feedback into account is essential when it comes to measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. By asking customers questions about their experience with your product or service after they’ve used it, you can gain valuable insights into what works and what doesn’t work from a user’s perspective – information which you can then use to improve campaigns or products accordingly. In addition, using surveys or focus groups provides another way for proptech companies to gain insights into what would improve the customer experience and increase engagement rates with their offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the right technologies and following these strategies for measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success, proptech companies can ensure that they reach the right audiences with the right message at the right time - helping them maximize their return on investment in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="GTM"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category></entry><entry><title>June 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/june-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-06-28:/blog/june-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Enough with the fundraising blah blah blah. It's time to start talking about building permits!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels June 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough with the fundraising blah blah blah. It's time to start talking about building permits! Here's the quick newsletter summary: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are cranking through 100 million building permits and doing all the things: cleaning, normalizing, fixing, and scrubbing so you can &lt;em&gt;get great data.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Order of release will be California, Florida, Texas, and New York. I'll announce the next tranche in a month. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some really interesting go-to-market (GTM) uses for building permits. I'll name a few. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early-bird pricing will be available in the next newsletter. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processing update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are burning up the servers at AWS! Amazon has granted multiple requests to increase our &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/fargate/"&gt;Fargate&lt;/a&gt; limits. That's how cool we are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Processing all of this data is not without its challenges. While I hoped we'd have all of California launched already, we're doggone close, and I know you're going to love what we deliver. Here are a few of the things you can look forward to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permits in over 200 jurisdictions&lt;/strong&gt;. The Golden State LOVES local permitting. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building electrification tagging&lt;/strong&gt;. We've identified all the permits related to batteries, heat pumps, EV chargers, and solar panels. We 💚 the 🌎 too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor rollups&lt;/strong&gt;. All these permits and tags roll up to contractors so you can see who's doing how much of what type of work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Normalized addresses&lt;/strong&gt;. The lovely people who enter permits into databases do all sorts of funny things with addresses, making us 🥺. So we fixed them for you.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, we are so close to launch. Soo close! We'll send a quick newsletter out when it's done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things to do with permits: GTM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people come through our marketing funnel, I always ask them what they plan to do with Shovels data. The uses are varied, but there's been an increasingly common use case: go-to-market (GTM). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense! Building permits are a gold mine for both B2B and B2C buyer intent. For B2B, a submitted commercial building permit means that the builder is in purchasing mode. Construction tech companies should get on it! Building entry systems, HVAC components, project management software... the roof's the limit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For B2C, a recently completed residential permit is a prime target for property tech companies. That homeowner is now ready to fix the lawn that just got torn up, install a new driveway, or put up solar panels. We can filter for EV chargers and batteries so climate tech companies can reach out about cost-cutting software add-ons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote more detail about all of this in our latest blog post: &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/"&gt;Go-to-market strategies for proptech companies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pricing update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still figuring it out, but I'm certain that we will offer a low-volume plan and special unlimited volume pricing for CA, FL, TX and NY once it's loaded. In the future, we'll offer pricing tiers for historical data and enhanced permit details. For our earliest customers, though, we'll throw it all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll let you know when you can get in on this Shovels API pricing bonanza. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry></feed>