<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels | - Case Study</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/case-study.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2024-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Case Study: Revolutionizing Lead Generation for Beam</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-revolutionizing-lead-generation-for-beam/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-04-08:/blog/case-study-revolutionizing-lead-generation-for-beam/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We transformed Beam's lead generation strategy by providing high-quality, regularly updated construction leads enriched with information such as permit type and recent activity, resulting in a 20-30% higher response rate.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/Shovels_Beam.pdf"&gt;PDF download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beam is an easy-to-use financial platform whose mission is to empower builders with better financial tools and services. Beam helps contractors take control of their project finances,  improve cash flow, and ultimately earn more money.  One of the ways they grow their business is through cold outreach to contractors. This is an effective customer acquisition strategy provided there is a source of quality leads, and an opportunity to reach out at the right time with a personalized message. When expensive lead lists yielded poor results, Beam turned to Shovels. Shovels' ability to provide high-quality, regularly updated leads enriched with information such as permit type and recent activity proved to be a game changer for Beam’s outreach efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Beam’s Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of homes and infrastructure are built and maintained by small and midsized contractors. However, most financial software has underserved these businesses, and many great builders still rely on paper checks, spreadsheets, and accounting software from the 90s. As a result, the payment process is error-prone and inefficient, leading to long delays and cash flow challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beam’s easy-to-use financial platform is built to serve the needs of small and mid sized contractors to help them move their processes online, speed up payments, and better manage their cash flow. In order to acquire new customers, Beam relied on cold outreach as one of their strategies.This proved to be challenging - lead lists were expensive, often contained information about companies and contractors no longer in business, and had no information on specific projects the business was engaged in or its recency. These lists had better data about the types of companies found on LinkedIn and not the small and medium sized businesses who were Beam’s target customers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beam therefore resorted to looking up contractor information on the Contractors State License Board (CSLB) public database, and this yielded a massive list. Calling businesses one at a time was inefficient. Many licensees contacted were either not in business anymore or were not actively working on a project. As a result, the yield rate from cold outreach was poor and the return on investment of time and effort was very low. Beam sought a better solution to high quality lead generation, and found that Shovels had the perfect solution to their challenge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Beam chose Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels analyzes over 100M building permits to help customers with lead generation by offering a comprehensive and filterable database tailored to the construction sector, adding between 5 and 10 million new permits nationwide every month. Raw permit data is cleansed, parsed, granularly categorized, and enriched with other data such as contractor profile information through cross referencing multiple data sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels’ ability to deliver high quality data containing detailed information including the type of permit filed, the date of filing, the profile of the contractor who applied for the permit and the permit fees paid made the company’s offering stand out. Top notch customer service during the sales and onboarding process sealed the deal for Beam. 
Shovels enabled Beam to efficiently and cost effectively generate a lead list, personalize their messaging, and reach out at the right time to prospects, thus scaling their cold outreach and providing a significant edge to grow their business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Beam Used Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Shovels became an integral part of Beam's cold outreach strategy,  their outreach efforts underwent a significant transformation. For instance, when the latest weekly data from Shovels listed a contractor who had pulled an ADU permit in the past month, the Beam team would swing into action and promptly reach out to the prospect using the contact information provided in the data feed. They would then establish rapport with the potential customer by citing an example of another customer who also constructs ADUs, whom they had assisted in achieving cost savings and efficiency. This type of timely, personalized outreach helped Beam earn trust and sign up new customers, eventually proving to be a game changer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integration of Shovels data in Beam’s cold outreach strategy resulted in a remarkable 20 to 30% higher likelihood of contractor engagement. Not only was Beam able to save time and effort by only reaching out to those contractors who had recently applied for a permit, they were also able to win new customers at a higher rate through personalizing their outreach efforts and reaching prospects at the beginning stages of a new project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The periodic data updates from Shovels helped fill Beam’s sales pipeline with prospects and helped the Beam team nurture awareness which subsequently transformed to consideration and high purchase intent among their target customers. The data also provided the Beam team with information about the other projects the contractor was working on, as well as information about derivative metrics such as inspection pass rates enabling future business opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Call-to-Action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready to revolutionize your outreach strategy? Connect with our team today to explore how Shovels can empower your business. Whether it's contractor and permit data or solutions to uplevel your go to market strategy and software, Shovels is your partner in navigating the complexities of the construction industry. Explore &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/about"&gt;our features&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Case Study"></category><category term="case"></category><category term="customer"></category></entry><entry><title>Case Study: Empowering Carbon Free Homes</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-empowering-carbon-free-homes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-05-13:/blog/case-study-empowering-carbon-free-homes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discover how Carbon Free Homes, in partnership with Shovels, successfully met 100% of their installation targets for eco-friendly appliances like heat pumps and water heaters in Marin County, CA. Utilizing Shovels' extensive contractor database, Carbon Free Homes streamlined the matching process, greatly enhancing efficiency and customer satisfaction. Learn more about this innovative approach to sustainable home solutions and its impact on the climate tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/Case_Study_Carbon_Free_Homes.pdf"&gt;PDF download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shovels Empowers Carbon Free Homes: Achieving 100% Installation Targets with Our Contractor Matching Platform&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon Free Homes faced significant difficulties in connecting homeowners with qualified contractors for the installation of heat pumps, water heaters, and other climate-friendly appliances. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a growing awareness and demand among homeowners for such technologies, the availability of trustworthy contractors who are capable, willing, and ready to take on these projects was limited. The traditional methods of finding these contractors were inefficient and often led to unreliable data that hindered scalability and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address this challenge, Carbon Free Homes turned to Shovels, a comprehensive and filterable database drawn from over 100 million building permit applications nationwide, updated monthly. Shovels provides detailed, high-quality data that includes the type of permit filed, the date of filing, and the profile and contact information of the contractor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This solution enabled Carbon Free Homes to efficiently connect homeowners with reputable contractors, significantly reducing the time and effort required to sift through data manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collaboration with Shovels led to remarkable outcomes for Carbon Free Homes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Achieved 100% of the target numbers for pilot installations of heat pumps, water heaters, and induction stoves in San Anselmo and Fairfax, Marin County, CA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streamlined the process of contractor matching, which was previously a major bottleneck, enhancing customer satisfaction and trust in the marketplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitated a group buy program that provided homeowners within a service area access to more competitive bids and seamless installation processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This efficient system not only improved the rate of successful installations but also supported the expansion of Carbon Free Homes' service offerings, including the launch of their Collaboration Energy group buying platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels offers the most comprehensive, clean, and customer-friendly building permit and contractor data products for the climate tech industry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access it via our web and mobile apps, API, or private table sharing into Snowflake, Databricks, BigQuery, and S3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/about"&gt;our features&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Case Study"></category><category term="case"></category><category term="customer"></category></entry><entry><title>Shovels Spotlight: Deep Product Enrichment with Inspectify</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-spotlight-deep-product-enrichment-with-inspectify/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-11-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Alex Brown</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-11-13:/blog/shovels-spotlight-deep-product-enrichment-with-inspectify/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels highlights companies that use their product well. Inspectify integrates with the Shovels API to enrich their home inspection report. All parties involved appreciated the collaboration efforts to achieve the goal.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Inspectify is an industry-leader in home inspection insights, who’s mission is to make every angle of the home inspection process as easy as possible. Whether it’s the home inspectors using Inspectify to build their in-depth reports, or lender institutions doing their risk analysis diligence, data quality is central to their platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With our platform, we help enterprise clients underwrite properties at scale and have always seen permit data as a missing piece to the overall risk of a property. When we were evaluating providers in this space, we were impressed with Shovel’s ability to iterate quickly and continue to make improvements to their platform. We are excited to grow both of our businesses together through this partnership. - Josh Jensen, CEO &amp;amp; Co-founder of Inspectify&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where Shovels comes in — Inspectify integrated with our API to bring in property permit history and complete the home inspection picture. Shovel’s API is easy to use, making it easy for the Inspectify engineering team to enrich their inspection reports with the permit data that sets their inspection reports above the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inspectify and Permit Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Inspectify team always had their eye on permit data, but struggled to find the right source or integration fit. That is, until they met Shovels. The insights that can be gleaned from the Shovels dataset — things like permit or connected contractor history — is crucial for the wholesale assessment that’s central to the Inspectify report workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started Shovels because there wasn’t a clear and easy way to programmatically access building permit data. There wasn’t an easy to use, well-documented, nationwide building permit API. So we set out to build it, and we’re very happy to have partners like Inspectify use our API to put our permit data to work. - Ryan, CEO &amp;amp; Co-Founder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do these extra data points set them apart from other home inspection platforms, but it gives them a material leg up on leveraging their holistic insights across the board. They look great on the inspection reports themselves, but are also key for lending institutions and risk assessment brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to have the full picture, and Shovels’s seamless API integration allows Inspectify to do just that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Shovels Integration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels has a simple yet powerful &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/api"&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;, which gave the Inspectify Product and Engineering teams an easy way to design their product around our data offering. Between the API docs themselves, the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qiIxx37_-6vGfGp2i5pXv4w2FdsLsShjCqSVO5v6OMQ/edit?gid=1818227349#gid=1818227349"&gt;Data Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; for additional clarity, and live support sessions from the Shovels team, Inspectify was able to easily connect the Shovels data to their existing home inspection report generation pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A Screenshot of the Inspectify product, highlighting the section that directly integrates the Shovels permit data." src="/images/inspectify-spotlight-report-summary.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Inspectify report itself, Shovels provides the data for their handy “Summary” section, which aggregates and counts available permits for this address, some general classification of the types of projects being done, with the option to drill down into the direct permits themselves. This drill down shows a granular view into the individual permits themselves, including the contractor business name if available. All of these are pulled as individual colors within the wider picture being painted for an individual address. And if we say so ourselves, really tie it all together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank [the Shovels team] for the communication, flexibility, and back and forth. We have a lot of projects and the ability to get quick answers from you has really helped us develop this integration. - Alex Mathieu, VP of Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hallmark of the collaboration between Shovels and Inspectify on this product integration was the high quality of communication between the teams. Their Product team worked with us over multiple calls to ensure that their designs made sense with the Shovels data structures. Once the design was done, Engineering had some requests too: we added some functionality to our existing endpoints to better handle the bulk requests that made more sense for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spotlights-R-Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every project needs a shovel and a spotlight (well, at least a work lamp).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At our core, we’re data people. We love to see cool projects doing even cooler things with publicly available data, especially in the real-estate and construction space. It makes our sweat and tears thus far spent making this data “shovel-ready” completely worth it. When that happens, we want to shine a spotlight on the great work and collaboration between Shovels and Inspectify: something less than a full-blown case study, but more than a shout out on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These kinds of collaborations are happening with most of our customers, so expect more of this content monthly. Hopefully you’ll find either a &lt;a href="https://www.inspectify.com/"&gt;cool new proptech company&lt;/a&gt; to check out, or get inspiration for how your own product might &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/api"&gt;integrate&lt;/a&gt; with the Shovels dataset. If you’re the latter, then check out our API in a &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai"&gt;Free Trial&lt;/a&gt;, or contact &lt;a href="mailto:sales@shovels.ai"&gt;Sales&lt;/a&gt; to get a data sample and platform demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Digging!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Case Study"></category><category term="spotlight"></category><category term="integration"></category><category term="API"></category><category term="inspectify"></category></entry></feed>