<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels | - Company</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/company.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Introduction to Shovels</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/introduction-to-shovels/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2022-11-08:/blog/introduction-to-shovels/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm thrilled to announce the launch of Shovels, a revolutionary platform that aims to transform the way we discover and evaluate building contractors. With Shovels, we address the agency problem in the trades by providing comprehensive data on contractors' permits, inspections, and key metrics across multiple jurisdictions. By crunching the numbers, we offer a unique perspective on contractor skill level and job fit, enabling you to make informed decisions. Our prototype is already live, showcasing the power of Shovels with Contra Costa County data, and we're working towards expanding our coverage to seven Bay Area counties. I'm incredibly grateful for the talented team behind Shovels, including my co-founder and CTO, Luka Kacil.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Ryan Buckley sent this newsletter about the launch of Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hello friends, advisors, and (a few) relatives! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of a hiatus, I'm really excited to launch a new company along with an incredible team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process has been a journey. Thanks again to those of you who suffered through my many explanations of half-baked ideas and more than a few false starts. This time is different! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to introduce Shovels, a new way to discover and evaluate building contractors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an agency problem in the trades. In my economics classes we called it "information asymmetry," a term popularized by Nobel Prize winner Joseph Stiglitz who proved that this asymmetry leads to inefficient markets. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, you don't need an economics degree to know that hiring a home contractor is fraught with risk. Just talk to anyone who's done it. More often than not, and far more frequently than any other hiring decision I can think of, it's a bad experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is contractors have far more knowledge of their skill level and fit for the job than the people who hire and finance them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels does a few things to address the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We scrape all permits and associate them with contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We include all permit inspections and their results &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do this across multiple jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we crunch the numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a very compelling new way to look at contractor skill level and job fit. We're calculating new metrics like inspection pass rate and construction speed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These metrics are predictive of project outcomes: we know what good and bad contractors look like. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why now?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear over and over again how the entire construction industry is slow to adopt new technology. The field is littered with startups who failed to get contractors to adopt a new app. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we're not trying to be in the field. Instead, we're in the offices of the people who decide who to hire and fund and we gather data from the municipalities that issue and inspect building permits. This part of the construction industry is moving online and we're able to take advantage of it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we built&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototype is live! It only has Contra Costa County data (about five years worth) but it's enough to see who the major builders are and it shows their key metrics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out: https://beta.shovels.ai/register/. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What we're building next&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to pull in seven of the nine Bay Area counties this month. That effort will really showcase the power of Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most contractors work in multiple counties and this data isn't centralized anywhere. It takes some heavy technical lifting to grab it all, but we have the expertise to do it. Once this historical data is pulled, we'll continue to update the open permits and grab new permits daily. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The climate angle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been telling everyone that my next thing will be climate-related. That's still true. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, our first paying customer is a climate tech company :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very likely our first several paying customers will be green building contractors, financiers, consultants, and data aggregators. We'll be able to track the proliferation of green buildings and see who's doing the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on all that is here: https://www.shovels.ai/climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Who we are&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but certainly not least, I want to share a couple of things about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am co-founder and CEO. I just stepped away as CEO of MightySignal after Airnow acquired us last year. We did a ton of data scraping and analysis there and my own (great, fortunately) experience with a major home remodel inspired Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luka Kacil is my co-founder and CTO. He is supremely talented and someone I look forward to being in the trenches with. We met through MightySignal when we acquired his company, AppMonsta, back in 2019. He built and managed the tech stack to scrape all of the Google Play and Apple App stores daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have a small team of part-time folks doing hands-on work in data analysis and marketing support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="launch"></category></entry><entry><title>December 2022 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/december-2022-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2022-12-13:/blog/december-2022-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We've made significant improvements in how we describe the problem we're solving and our solution. Despite facing new challenges that have slowed us down, they have only fueled our determination to create more value. We've had great conversations with potential customers who align perfectly with our ideal profiles. Our back-office operational tasks are well underway, and we've also made strides in fundraising. While we received an offer from a venture studio, we decided to prioritize raising a seed round instead. With my co-founder Luka diligently collecting data and my focus on revenue and fundraising, I'm confident that we're on the right track. Exciting times ahead! Happy holidays!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Dec 2022 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to share a few things I've been thinking about recently with this business, but I'll start with an ask:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to talk to more real estate developers, especially if they're active in Contra Costa County or in the broader SF Bay Area. If you have a friendly one you can intro to me, I'd appreciate it! I want to understand how they vet and hire contractors.
That aside, here's a quick summary and then I'll get into more detail on each item. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've improved the way I describe the problem we're solving and our solution for fixing it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We encountered some new challenges that are slowing us down -- but also increasing our resolve because hey, the harder it is, the more value we're creating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had great conversations with people who match our three ideal customer profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I made a bunch of progress on boring back office operational stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some fundraising progress was had&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Our problem and how we solve it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is information asymmetry in the labor market for the trades, and this mismatch leads to transactions that make both sides worse off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There, that's the problem! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one that homeowners, construction lenders, and real estate developers each have to deal with. The way we solve it is to aggregate building permit and related data and objectively assess the work that these guys do. We use source data to provide the transparency lacking in this market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach is unique, and I'll describe why in the next section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;New data challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew aggregating this data would be hard. We didn't know it would be this hard. The challenge is several-fold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no clean public datasets for the detail we want to collect, so we have to find "interesting" ways to grab it.
Once we have it, the data is inconsistent and incomplete. It needs a good amount of TLC. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is distributed among counties and cities, and isn't always online. Sometimes have to make public records requests to get it.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But that's what makes this work valuable and worth doing. It's also why no one else has already done it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will get easier, too -- I'm hearing directly from city clerks that they're in the process of bringing building permits online. That's encouraging, both for my co-founder Luka, who has to deal with most of this, and for us generally because it means our timing is good. It feels like we're catching the wave for clean, accessible government data, and we can be among the players that bring this critical trend* fully ashore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conversations with potential customers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to several "bulls-eye" potential customers. They're exactly the profiles who would want to work with us. Here are a few takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The contractor marketplaces (Thumbtack, BuildZoom, etc) seem to refer contractors with whom they have referral agreements. It leads to bad matches and creates distrust on the buy side. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real estate developers already use public permit databases to see which contractors are active in a region. It's a tedious process that takes several hours to identify a single contractor. The time sink multiplies for every new jurisdiction they have to research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no database available today to look up a property address and get its permit history. 
What does this mean to me? We have work to do! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These potential customers will remain "potential" until we can get more data coverage, which leads me to...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back office and fundraising&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels, Inc. is now officially a Delaware C-corp. We have a bank account, a Stripe account, and real paying customers. I have a CRM flush with conversations to stay on top of. This is a real milestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get us even further, we will need to raise a small seed round. I'm talking every day to friends who are making introductions, advisors who critique our pitch deck, and people in the angel and venture investing community who are taking a hard look at Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm hearing so far is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to describe the market size better. Luka and I are working on this, but there's no specific market report for what we do. Our total available market calculation is a bit haphazard. I know it's huge, but I have yet to prove it :) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more customers we get, the easier it will be to fundraise. I'm working on those customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construction tech is a tricky area to fundraise. It's not your typical market and many investors shy away. They just don't get it. That's okay -- we're finding others who lean in right away. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently received our first offer. We were invited to join a venture studio that would handle a lot of the operations for us, effectively an "in-kind" investment of $500,000+. Ultimately we decided this one was not a great fit, so we're going to focus on raising a seed round instead. It was a good vote of confidence, though. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for now. Luka is busy grabbing all the data we can in the SF Bay Area. I'm keeping the revenue and fundraising operation together. It's a grind, but I wouldn't rather be doing anything else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy holidays! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Our first newsletter is &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/introduction-to-shovels/"&gt;on the blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
* Why is taking building permits online critical? Let me ascend my climate change soapbox for a moment. Homes need to electrify. It's inevitable that every building will disconnect its gas line in the next 50 years. Getting there requires streamlining the bureaucratic mess that is building permits. We all hate it, so let's make it better. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>February 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/february-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-02-16:/blog/february-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm excited to share the latest updates from Shovels and our journey in the world of building permit data. We've raised a seed round from reputable investors, allowing us to move forward with our plans. Our conversations with property technology and construction financing companies have been fruitful, and we're thrilled to have a roadmap and budget in place for the year ahead. We've also made progress in addressing data challenges, which are common in our field. I'm grateful for the support and advice we've received, and I'm looking forward to sharing more exciting news in our upcoming funding round announcement.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Feb 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot to cover, so I'll summarize first and then get into some detail for those who wish to read on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We raised a seed round from legit investors and angels, and I plan to gather signatures and checks next week! We'll announce details soon thereafter. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've had dozens of great conversations with property technology and construction financing companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a roadmap and budget for the year. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We increased our price to $1,000/mo per metro area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also continue to work through data challenges -- to be expected in this corner of the Internet. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Heroes" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/heroes.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pic of Luka and me amid a hero's journey through the mystical and enchanted world of building permit databases. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I took this screenshot, we had recently discovered that there were 45 more permitting jurisdictions than we expected in the SF Bay Area. We'd just committed to a customer that we could scrape all of them. My screen froze during our meeting, and I took this pic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around this time, a friend and fellow entrepreneur texted me to ask how things were going with Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We've hit the bogs," I wrote back. "We're plodding through the shit." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"That's my favorite part!" he replied. Usually, it's mine too, but I was stressed and worried at that moment. What else had I underestimated? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did mention this was a hero's journey, right? A hero sets out on a high-risk adventure, encounters adversity, and overcomes it. The arc of entrepreneurship is one long hero's journey, but within that long arc are countless smaller ones. This data challenge is an example of one of those smaller arcs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll cut to the chase: we set out to grab all permits in the SF Bay Area. We encountered much more work than expected, fretted for a couple of weeks, and then found a solution. Huzzah! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're now purchasing raw permit and inspection data from a data vendor. Remarkably, this simple development led to a string of wins over the last couple of months. It's why I skipped the January newsletter -- I wanted to include the next win before sending it, and the wins just kept coming, so I never clicked send. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here we are in mid-February, so I'm just going to send. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons from our fundraise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's never easy, but I have to say, it felt like we had something akin to "investor-market-fit." The firms that passed did so for a few common reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're too early. Not enough revenue or traction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're not focused enough on climate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They're not familiar enough with proptech / construction tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our best conversations were with firms who:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believe in B2B and are willing to invest in new markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appreciate my background in VC and PE-backed startups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like data-as-a-service business models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fund that I was excited about turned us down because they were too close to the contractor data market. He spent years working at one of the big contractor marketplaces. When he declined to invest, he gave me the best advice: "You need to find an investor who is as irrationally excited about this idea as you are." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This advice stuck with me, and I remained optimistic that I would find some irrationally excited funds and angel investors. And that's what happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll announce who they are once we're signed, sealed, and delivered 😁.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons from my many customer interviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's one piece of startup advice that I hear over and over again, it's this: interview customers from day 1... and never stop. I have taken this to heart. I have customer calls nearly every day. Usually multiple. I have learned A LOT. Here are some highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like investors, the best meetings come from referrals. I get a call nearly every time someone we both know introduces me. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold emailing is getting a lot harder. When it works, it works well, but it's a numbers game, and I have to get lucky. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proptech customers have many uses for clean and processed permit data. Their needs are unique, but our delivery is the same. They all want to store this data internally. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many would pay a premium for weekly or daily permit data refreshes rather than monthly updates. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construction banks can use our processed data for underwriting and loan draw decisions, but they need broad coverage to see the value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've given quotes ranging from $500/mo to $10,000/mo. I love that. Our geographic coverage is the only thing keeping me from closing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Asks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're hiring! We'd appreciate any candidate intros. Feel free to share these job descriptions: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://broadleaf-leech-f9b.notion.site/Growth-Marketer-4a35d1c91875485eaee25c72b77fedf1"&gt;Marketer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://broadleaf-leech-f9b.notion.site/Data-Engineer-8c88bef8282d4d0ebdf74178c5e737d4"&gt;Data Engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intros to construction loan people. I want more interviews. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intros to developers who do 10+ projects at a time in the Bay Area. I need to learn more from this segment. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next note will officially announce our funding round, and then probably we'll settle into a quarterly update to all of you friends and/or family and/or investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for your support! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>March 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/march-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-03-15:/blog/march-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have raised $610,000 so far, and I'm open to more strategic fundraising calls to help us find product-market fit. We completely revamped our website and released a prototype of the Green Contractor Directory. We continue to learn and adapt in the evolving permit and contractor data landscape, and we're building strong relationships with our competitors, who may turn out to be partners or potential customers. Our focus is now on contractor data, as we see a significant opportunity in this underserved market.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels Mar 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greetings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the special fundraising update email and other updates since last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have raised $610,000 so far, with more likely to come in the next few weeks! (Timing likely will be delayed by the Silicon Valley Bank failure and related malaise.) This money is in the bank, so it's official.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm still taking a few very strategic fundraising calls. We don't need more money, but I'm receptive to any investors who could help us find product-market fit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of product-market fit, that's top of mind now and will remain so for the foreseeable future. Expect this to be the central topic of these newsletters going forward!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And to that end, I completely rewrote &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago. It still needs some color, but I'm happy with the copy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We released a &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/e440a465-a280-44be-aa81-5388b8ac20ff"&gt;Green Contractor Directory&lt;/a&gt; prototype!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fundraise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to share that our lead investor is Zach Coelius from &lt;a href="https://coelius.vc/"&gt;Coelius Capital&lt;/a&gt;. He's an ideal lead for us. I've known of Zach for years. We've been in the same circles but didn't really connect until late last year after I attended one of his dinners in San Francisco. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zach knows the super early stages as well as anybody. He'll be a great sounding board as we come up against critical decisions and can help us raise funds to accelerate growth if needed. We're delighted to have his support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other angel investors, whom I won't name directly but can describe as old friends, new friends, former bosses, and fans of my personal blog, were the first to sign and send their checks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luka and I are humbled and grateful -- and ready to get back to work :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to learn. The permit and contractor data landscape is evolving rapidly, and we are a player in this space. The other companies are aware of us and reacting to our presence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I'm good at, perhaps because I enjoy doing it, is getting to know my neighbors. I like to be friendly with my business neighbors, too. I want to know everyone in the market. Not just know their names, but meet them, exchange messages, and (try to) be friends. It doesn't always work, but when it does, it leads to profit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Businesses that look like competitors can turn out to be partners, customers, or lead to friendly mergers. This has happened at every company I've run. It happened again recently with Shovels. I'm really happy about this development because it opens up a big opportunity for us in the contractor data market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contractor data is what I said we'd do in the early days of Shovels. Late last year, though, I became very excited about permit data. I saw a huge opportunity there. I still see it. I'd reach out or be introduced to potential customers under the pretense of contractor data and discover that what they really wanted was permits. It's a huge opportunity, but I don't think it's ours to get. We don't have enough value to add there; the incumbents will meet this need well and soon enough. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contractor data is a different story. It's underserved, and we have a tremendous opportunity right now to fill the void. I describe the four segments on &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/"&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt;: software, climate, finance, and builders. I'll write more detail about all four in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coming Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a very exciting product roadmap! We're going to expand our little &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/e440a465-a280-44be-aa81-5388b8ac20ff"&gt;green contractor prototype&lt;/a&gt;. We're going to make all of the San Francisco Bay Area available; this demo currently has only 500 records.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to release an API (application programming interface -- a way for computer programmers to easily access this data) and put contractor landing pages up on our website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next quarter, we're going to layer on additional datasets to make the contractor information even more insightful. I'll share more details on these data layers soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we're going deep on contractor data and we're starting in the SF Bay Area. I'll share more next month when more products are released! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>April 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/april-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-04-20:/blog/april-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We've raised over $960,000 in our successful fundraising journey, thanks to amazing investor support. Customers are equally thrilled about what we're building! Using permit data, we're tackling construction challenges like pre-construction timelines, approval steps, and costs. Our AI-powered system quickly analyzes permit data, allowing you to ask a chat-like interface about permits or kitchen remodeling. We're going national, leaving geographically-constrained data behind. Join us as we revolutionize the construction industry one permit at a time!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels April 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few more updates since last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have now raised $960,000, up from $610,000 last month. We're very grateful for the investor support and ready to prove that customers are equally excited about what we're building. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have more detail on the ICPs (ideal customer profiles) we're targeting. The picture continues to get clearer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're also excited about AI/GPT/LLMs, etc. I'll share a couple of snippets about how we're using this latest (justifiably) hyped up technology. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new data is coming, and we have plans to go national. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fundraise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're very pleased to add &lt;a href="https://www.coolclimatecollective.com/"&gt;Cool Climate Collective&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://venture.angellist.com/zach-coelius/syndicate"&gt;Coelius Syndicate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.coolclimatecollective.com/"&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.manaventures.vc/"&gt;Mana Ventures&lt;/a&gt; to our list of investors. We also added another friendly angel. We'll close this seed round at just over $1M, punt any new interest to the next round, and focus 100% on execution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ideal Customer Profiles (ICPs)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still do customer interviews every day. It's incredibly helpful. Although I'm eager to actually close deals, since it's taken longer to process the data we've acquired than we originally anticipated, I'm able to have more wide-ranging conversations. I'm not held back by what we have in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm learning that there are all sorts of problems that can be addressed with permit data. We can go very deep into pre-construction timelines, serving information about approval steps, costs, and timing. My focus previously was on construction, what happens once the permit is approved. There's a whole other world of pre-construction data going back to when a permit is submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serving this market will require going deeper into planning departments, requesting data from public utilities, and even scanning planning commission minutes and agendas. We can't do all of this tomorrow, but it feels well within the scope of Shovels to tackle it eventually. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, our latest ICPs look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Construction loan portfolio manager at a bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: Limited information about contractor quality when asked to underwrite a new loan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Contractor metrics and permits summary delivered as a PDF&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Construction loan fund controller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No idea what else a contractor is working on when they're asked to approve a loan draw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solutions&lt;/em&gt;: Current and past contractor metrics and permits history delivered as JSON via API, and webhooks for permit processing time changes in a set of jurisdictions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Large condo developer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No visibility into pre-construction permit timelines in a given jurisdiction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Web app interface to look up detailed permit and planning approval timelines in different cities and counties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Proptech CEO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem&lt;/em&gt;: No programmatic way to see if a house has an active permit already&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shovels Solution&lt;/em&gt;: Permits delivered on a given address via API&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you fall into these buckets. If you want to chat, please get in touch! You know I like a good brainstorm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As these ideas firm up further, I'll incorporate them "officially" into our website copy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the AI stuff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll admit it -- I registered shovels.ai because it was the only decent "shovels" domain available. But I'm sure glad we got it! I had no idea AI was going to blow up like this in the months following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual AI application here is pretty obvious. Permits come with a lot of data and not all of it is structured. The AI models do a fantastic job of quickly (meaning: without any contextual training) identifying what the permit is about (meaning: categorizing it). That's just out of the box. We can train AI models to get better over time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are front-end uses too. You could imagine asking a chat-like interface about permits on a property, permits performed by a contractor, or who should remodel your kitchen. A lot of people would be excited about this, and we have a role to play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going national&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're working out a way for us to expand nationally very quickly. It's a direct result of the ICP discussions I've had recently: geographically-constrained data isn't nearly as valuable as national scope. It's a tricky dance but we're making headway and working towards a deal. I hope to be able to announce it next month! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>May 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/may-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-05-24:/blog/may-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our final fundraising total reached an impressive $1,071,939.39. We are grateful for the interest and support we received during this process. We also expanded our team by hiring a full-time data engineer and two talented summer interns. One of our interns developed a chat AI interface for our Shovels API, which will be incorporated into our upcoming website. Additionally, we have been actively considering building and zoning laws and are excited about the potential opportunities they present. On another note, we are thrilled to announce that national data coverage is just around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels May 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few more updates since April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our final fundraising total is $1,071,939.39. I'm happy to connect with any additional interest but we'll ultimately push it to the next round. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hired a full-time data engineer and two summer interns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of our interns made a chat AI interface to the &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;Shovels API&lt;/a&gt;. We're going to incorporate it into a new website we're building this summer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're thinking a lot about building and zoning laws. Aren't you?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National data coverage is right around the corner. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fundraise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a wrap! We set out to to raise $1M, pared it back to $500K, then raised the target to $750K and then back again to $1M. Fundraising is hard. It was hard for us too, but I think we did a few things right and caught a bit of good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll share a few learnings here about the fundraising process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was told by a climate tech CEO who recently raised several million dollars that I should expect to pitch 100 VCs. She generously shared her VC list with me. I ended up pitching about 20 before finding a lead investor, and then about 20 more to fill out the round to $1M.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing beats customer interviews. I didn't know this at the time, but I refined my investor pitch each time I spoke to a prospect interested in building permit data. It helped me choose the right language, define the right need, and formulate a solution that makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes sense to customers also makes sense to investors. It makes sense that these pitches should be quite similar. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It helps to be unique. Investors don't hear a lot of pitches about building permit data, so Shovels doesn't sound like anything else. I can use that to capture their imaginations, and I've learned from customer interviews about the many uses that permit data can have in the pre- and post-construction phases. I can make Shovels sound big &lt;em&gt;because it's true&lt;/em&gt;. This can be a VERY big business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investors and customers love the Shovels brand. We lucked into that bit of inspiration (the first domain I bought for this project was ChooseAGC -- "choose a general contractor" -- not nearly as cool). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And we got lucky that our lead investor bought in right away and has stood by us the rest of the fundraising journey.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operating Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to share a bit of high-level strategy about how we operate Shovels, which also worked well when fundraising. For anyone who knows me and reads my stuff, this strategy below should not be surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two central operating principles in our 2023 budget:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to breakeven as quickly as possible. This means staying lean for as long as possible and offsetting expenses with related revenue wherever possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert investment into ARR. This ensures a good return for investors as well as founders. It’s &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; equity we’re selling, after all! If we raise $1M, we want to be at a $1M annual revenue run rate when we start fundraising the next round.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these principles in mind, our financial projections are modeled with the following results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total burn of about $500K. We want to spend no more than half of funds raised before reaching breakeven, so we’ll still have powder left for growth experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peak burn of about $70K/mo. High fixed costs are salaries and data acquisition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will be at breakeven by summer 2024.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the assumptions built into this model are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can limit churn to 1% per month and upsell at 0.5% per month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luka can get by with 1 data engineer to breakeven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ryan can get by with 2 junior sales or 1 senior sales person to breakeven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our ACV is at least $1,000/mo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our product works and excites our customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can reach profitability by selling just our API products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to leverage my background with Xenon Partners to execute on revenue while being sensitive to cash flow by utilizing SEO and high impact content on target social media networks for market development. I also expect that our product will be great and we’ll continue to get word-of-mouth referrals because my co-founder is a badass CTO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most investors liked, if not &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt;, this message. The ones that weren't impressed, I wouldn't want to work with anyway. It's an important filter for me so I was very open about it. Plus, it's true. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did hire two summer interns. Luka got his data engineer (Petra is fantastic!) and I'm still experimenting with some sales strategies before hiring anyone full-time. In sum these are not insignificant expenses, but I can justify them 100% knowing that everyone at Shovels is working towards one goal right now: &lt;strong&gt;get revenue as fast as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More thinking about AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing from last month's newsletter, I have a few updates to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This summer we're looking at all the large language model (LLM) options and figuring out the right tech stack to use to process millions of permit records through it for permit classification and entity extraction (appliances, rooms, quantities, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We found another niche in municipal building and planning codes. Someone (might as well be us!) needs to load them into a LLM and use the LLM to figure out what the building rules are: setbacks, height limits, density requirements. These rules can completely disrupt the economics of a large project and they're very difficult to find and update. AI to the rescue! I know we're not the only ones with our eyes on this problem. Solving it is a stretch goal for the summer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, I see good data as our competitive advantage in the coming AI wars. Try asking Bard or ChatGPT what permits have been issued in a given zip code. They can't do it, but we can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going national&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We signed a deal today to get national data starting on June 1. We're working overtime to prep the data pipelines for this influx of data and we'll start reaching out to those of you who have been asking for this for months. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>June 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/june-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-06-28:/blog/june-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Enough with the fundraising blah blah blah. It's time to start talking about building permits! We've been working hard on processing 100 million building permits to provide you with high-quality data. We'll release the permits for California, Florida, Texas, and New York soon, with more to come. In addition, we've identified some really interesting go-to-market (GTM) uses for building permits.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels June 2023 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough with the fundraising blah blah blah. It's time to start talking about building permits! Here's the quick newsletter summary: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are cranking through 100 million building permits and doing all the things: cleaning, normalizing, fixing, and scrubbing so you can &lt;em&gt;get great data.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Order of release will be California, Florida, Texas, and New York. I'll announce the next tranche in a month. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some really interesting go-to-market (GTM) uses for building permits. I'll name a few. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early-bird pricing will be available in the next newsletter. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processing update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are burning up the servers at AWS! Amazon has granted multiple requests to increase our &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/fargate/"&gt;Fargate&lt;/a&gt; limits. That's how cool we are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Processing all of this data is not without its challenges. While I hoped we'd have all of California launched already, we're doggone close, and I know you're going to love what we deliver. Here are a few of the things you can look forward to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permits in over 200 jurisdictions&lt;/strong&gt;. The Golden State LOVES local permitting. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building electrification tagging&lt;/strong&gt;. We've identified all the permits related to batteries, heat pumps, EV chargers, and solar panels. We 💚 the 🌎 too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor rollups&lt;/strong&gt;. All these permits and tags roll up to contractors so you can see who's doing how much of what type of work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Normalized addresses&lt;/strong&gt;. The lovely people who enter permits into databases do all sorts of funny things with addresses, making us 🥺. So we fixed them for you.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, we are so close to launch. Soo close! We'll send a quick newsletter out when it's done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things to do with permits: GTM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people come through our marketing funnel, I always ask them what they plan to do with Shovels data. The uses are varied, but there's been an increasingly common use case: go-to-market (GTM). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense! Building permits are a gold mine for both B2B and B2C buyer intent. For B2B, a submitted commercial building permit means that the builder is in purchasing mode. Construction tech companies should get on it! Building entry systems, HVAC components, project management software... the roof's the limit. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For B2C, a recently completed residential permit is a prime target for property tech companies. That homeowner is now ready to fix the lawn that just got torn up, install a new driveway, or put up solar panels. We can filter for EV chargers and batteries so climate tech companies can reach out about cost-cutting software add-ons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote more detail about all of this in our latest blog post: &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/"&gt;Go-to-market strategies for proptech companies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pricing update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still figuring it out, but I'm certain that we will offer a low-volume plan and special unlimited volume pricing for CA, FL, TX and NY once it's loaded. In the future, we'll offer pricing tiers for historical data and enhanced permit details. For our earliest customers, though, we'll throw it all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll let you know when you can get in on this Shovels API pricing bonanza. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>July 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/july-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-07-24:/blog/july-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We overcame data processing challenges and loaded all of California into our internal database, with an API update coming soon. Additionally, we are actively following up with Florida, Texas, and New York, and we remain on track to expand nationwide by the end of summer. We have also created a dashboard showcasing building electrification permits in Contra Costa County and made predictions for EV charging permits in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Greetings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm writing from Sunriver, OR, where my family's vacation ground to a halt due to air quality. There's a wildfire in Oregon. Several, actually, but the one that's bothering me right now is smoldering 75 miles to the west, and it smells like the inside of a chimney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In happier news: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We finally broke through a bunch of data processing hurdles to load up all of California into our internal database. The API update is imminent! We now show 21M building permits in California, where the air is perfect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're still following up with Florida, Texas, and New York. We'll know more about going nationwide after this, but I'm confident that we'll get there by the end of summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our really smart friend made a cool dashboard of building electrification permits in Contra Costa County. We also tried to predict the number of EV charging permits in 2024. Links to both are below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early-bird pricing is here. How does $1K/mo for unlimited access through 2023 sound?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Processing update&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full API data load is just days away. We want this next release to be pretty much perfect! With that in mind, we made these improvements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleared out all the "nan" and "null" values in the API results &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simplified our tag list and made sure that each one has permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further improved our address matching (this one was tricky!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sped up the overall processing time by using more efficient data structures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few cool statistics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Californians file about 100,000 building permits each month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LA and Orange Counties make up a third of all historical CA building permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LA, San Diego, Riverside, and Orange Counties have a third of all &lt;em&gt;solar&lt;/em&gt; permits 🌞&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LA and Sacramento Counties (finally, some NorCal representation) are the leaders in EV charging ⚡️&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2022, LA County filed the most ADU permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also in 2022, Riverside County led in new homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminder: you can get all of this detail (the individual addresses and contractors) using our API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: Charts and dashboards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should not be surprising that there's a lot of interest in building permits for home electrification. We're seeing this interest from climate tech companies, financial institutions, and even the public sector. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracking the progress of residential EV chargers is important for transportation authorities who need to plan for public EV charging stations. Communities that have more residential chargers will have less demand for public ones, so those resources can go elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sarahidaniels/"&gt;Sarah Daniels&lt;/a&gt; made &lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/sarah.daniels4671/viz/CCCTestdashv1/Dashboard1#1"&gt;this amazing dashboard&lt;/a&gt; of building electrification permits in Contra Costa County using Shovels data. If you see a need for something like this in your own community, please let us know! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also put on our data science hats and built a prediction model for EV charger permits in CA through 2024. Predictions are the dotted line. We even decided to write a &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;blog post about it&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EV Charger chart" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shovels_ev_prediction.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Early bird pricing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've been having a bunch of conversations about what all this Shovels data is going to cost. The short answer is this: we still don't know. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have a solution! Early-bird pricing that you can lock in now and keep for the rest of the year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🐣 Early bird extra special offer 🐣&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$1,000/mo&lt;br&gt;
- Unlimited API requests (subject only to a reasonable rate limit)&lt;br&gt;
- Nationwide coverage (meaning: everything we have loaded)&lt;br&gt;
- Access to every endpoint (no future feature gating)&lt;br&gt;
- Available through 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some hints here for future pricing. Plans will be limited by usage, geography, and/or endpoints. This plan locks you into an awesome price for &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll offer this to the first 10 customers who sign up. Just hit reply to get in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>August 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/august-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-08-17:/blog/august-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels, the leading provider of building permit and contractor API services, is expanding to Florida and Texas, with plans to cover all 47 remaining states by end of summer. We recently added date filters to our API, allowing users to easily access the most relevant data. Our team has also resolved any issues related to displaying dates in the API response. We are developing a new website that will offer registration and API key services, as well as a data explorer portal. Looking ahead, we are working on new market endpoints for building permits, providing valuable insights into current and historical trends by zip code.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like California. I've lived here my whole life, and so have both of my parents and most of my grandparents. That's why when we launched Shovels, we started in California. Why wouldn't we? California is the best 😎.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we keep hearing that the home of the Grateful Dead and Clint Eastwood is just not enough. You want more, so by golly, you'll get more. We are launching Florida and Texas in just a few days. And soon after that... the remaining 47 🇺🇸!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what else is going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We added date filters to the API and fixed some issues displaying dates in the API response 🎉&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're building out a brand new website on some brand new technology. It will allow us to quickly add registration and API key services, as well as a data explorer portal for you folks that prefer not to deal with API endpoints. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That $249/mo price is live. On this plan you get 1,000 lookups per month in any  one state (so long as it's California... for now :) A self-serve pricing page will go up soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;API update: Date filters!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dates are important! You might not care about the roofing permit from 10 years ago, but you definitely care about the one filed last week. Our new date filters allow you to hone in on precisely the data you care most about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also now default sort permits by date descending, so in all responses, when you see a list of permits, the most recent ones are first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is live already (as of about 12 hours ago!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate, we added two new demos: &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/9ab4b347-6227-4ee3-8648-b1e0dc632e1b"&gt;Permit Directory&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://shovels.retool.com/embedded/public/e440a465-a280-44be-aa81-5388b8ac20ff"&gt;Contractor Directory&lt;/a&gt;. You have to add a zip code and both the start and end dates for the demos to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you really want to test it out, you'll need an API key. Just reply and I'll get one for you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sneak preview: &lt;strong&gt;markets&lt;/strong&gt;. We're starting to plan for a new set of markets endpoints that will tell you all sorts of interesting current and historical trends for building permits by zip code. This data will be fantastic for those who are trying to prioritize sales territories by identifying where certain types of building activity is happening.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: Calculate approval times&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On most of our permits we are able to see the file date and the issue date, which bookend the jurisdiction's permit processing period. In other words, we can see which jurisdictions are slow and which ones are quick to approve permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For building developers, this is really important information. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we keep hearing from EV charger companies, we decided to continue on our investigation of this industry with a post on EV charger permit approval times in California. We looked at every EV charger permit over the last few years and tallied them up by jurisdiction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's one insight: &lt;strong&gt;We learned that Oakland approves EV charger permits 30X faster than LA&lt;/strong&gt;. Crazy, eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/"&gt;read more about it here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Bottom 5 jurisdictions" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/bottom5.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking with us. We're working hard to deliver the best building permit and contractor API in the country. And we're really close to covering the whole thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>September 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/september-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-09-17:/blog/september-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to share that we have processed all 100 million building permits nationwide. With the release of our markets endpoint, you can now see current and historical building permit counts for specific zip codes. We also revamped our API documentation to make it more user-friendly. We also updated our monthly API pricing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Greetings from Las Vegas. I'm on Day 5 and very happy to be heading home now. 😮‍💨&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel proud today. The Shovels team, all three of us, had a very productive two weeks working together in-person. I'm going to share some highlights below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🚀 We processed 100M building permits! We can run custom SQL queries and export CSV files for residential and commercial buildings nationwide. 🚀&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;States currently available in the API: California, Texas, Florida, and New York. Now that the rest are processed, we'll begin loading them into the API too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of API, we released our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Markets/operation/get_market_activity_by_zip_code_v1_markets_permits_zip_get"&gt;markets endpoint&lt;/a&gt;. We count current and historical building permit counts on all of our zip codes sliced by any of our tags. I'll describe an interesting application for this data below! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also released &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;new prettier API docs&lt;/a&gt;. Why does this matter? I'll tell you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our pricing matrix is good to go. You'll know what cost to expect when you're ready to get on this building permit data bandwagon. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;100 million building permits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know most people reading this newsletter aren't data nerds. I'm glad for that. I'm also glad that I'm surrounded by people who love thinking about and wrangling with data. Building permit data is particularly challenging because it uses data types that are prone to be inconsistent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, look at these addresses: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4203 Pearl Gate Drive, Las Vegas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4203 Pearl Gate, Las Vegas, NV 89133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4203 Pearl Gate DR, 89133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know these are all the same address. But you're human and you're an expert at deduction. How do you get machines, which aren't built for ambiguity, to know these addresses are the same? And then how do you get machines to fill in the missing address components? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one of many, many fascinating (dare I say fun?) problems we solved on the road to 100 million permits. I'm so proud of this team for getting through it so quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because now we can do stuff like this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SQL Screenshot" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/sql.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that's a screenshot of SQL. Yes, this is a marketing newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just want to make a point about what it means to "process" 100 million permits. It means we have them all in a standard taxonomy that allows us to look up the same info across states, counties, and cities and run complex filters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm showing here is a way to identify leads for solar installers. This query scans all 100 million building permits in about 3 seconds using inexpensive AWS technology. It's amazing what our team built. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now it can be yours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: Learn about neighborhoods&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretend you're in the market for a new home (or if you really are in this market, don't pretend, and I'm sorry). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are interested in two homes in the same city. They're comparable in size, age, amenities, school district, and price. You'd be happy with either one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there's a critical difference lurking below surface. They're in different neighborhoods, and different neighborhoods act... differently. We can measure this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say one home is in a neighborhood with very little permit activity. The neighbors aren't maintaining, improving, or expanding their homes. They're not invested. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other home is in a neighborhood bustling with solar installs, new ADUs, and kitchen remodels. The homeowners are doubling down on their purchases, in it for the long haul. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which house would you prefer now? I know my answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a new way of looking at neighborhoods. I don't believe this data exists anywhere else. We want to help you get it out there! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Neighborhood improvement index" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/neighborhood-index.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a heat map at the zip code level in my neck of the woods (we could also do this block-by-block) showing relative investment in ADUs, kitchens, and other additions. The SQL query that drives it is pretty cool too, but I'll just leave you with the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Beautiful API documentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first company I co-founded was &lt;a href="https://www.scripted.com/"&gt;Scripted&lt;/a&gt;. I'm a business guy, but I've always been fascinated by programming. I guess that's why I landed in tech. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on at Scripted, I found reasons to get my hands dirty in Ruby and Python. I committed code, reviewed pull requests, and sprinkled bits of "Ryansoft" like fairy dust throughout our repository. I also worked with a lot of APIs, and I got to see the impact first-hand of thoughtful design and helpful documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admire companies like Stripe and Clearbit who make it easy for developers to use their products. I want Shovels to be the same. Fortunately, the competition in our market is pretty weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why we are going to make Shovels the most developer-friendly construction data API in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;new API docs&lt;/a&gt; are searchable, have input and output samples, and a new page structure. Enjoy! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Money talk&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, yes, we are going to charge money for all this awesomeness. Here's how it looks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⛺️ $249/mo: 1,000 lookups, residential only, in one state&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏠 $749/mo: 5,000 lookups, residential only, nationwide&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏢 $2,499/mo: 50,000 lookups, residential and commercial, nationwide&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>October 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/october-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-17:/blog/october-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now sign up for your very own Shovels API key and start building awesome stuff with building permits. Our new web application is going to have more features to find contractors, look up permits, and get all the permits on any address in the country.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This will be a newsletter about using the Shovels building permit API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a new war began since our last newsletter, and I think first of the children. I don't know how to help other than to put this little mention in this little newsletter and try to stay positive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that... back to permits. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last month, I said we'd work on loading every state into the API. This month, I get to tell you it's done! Yay! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To celebrate this launch, we're making it easier to get API keys. You don't need to ask us first. Just register an account with &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;our sweet new app&lt;/a&gt; and get your API key 💪&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't know how to use an API? That's cool, for most of my life, I didn't either. I have a solution for you, too. Read below. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you do like APIs, don't forget about our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;pretty API docs&lt;/a&gt; 😍 and check out our &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;API starter guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;🇺🇸 The API is national 🇺🇸&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 100 million permits span:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;24,593,329 addresses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14,688 zip codes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;973 jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;656 counties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48 states&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And across all of these permits we applied 33 unique "tags" in order to make it easy to cluster and slice these 100 million permits to your liking... &lt;strong&gt;all by using the Shovels API&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API wuh? 🤔&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my attempt at writing the shortest-ever tutorial on how to use an API. We have a more detailed &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;tutorial on the blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An API is like a set of defined questions you can ask a database using your favorite programming language. Each of these questions is called an "endpoint." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can ask &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Permits/operation/get_permits_by_address_v1_permits_address_get"&gt;this endpoint&lt;/a&gt; the question, "What are all the permits on 15 Cherry Lane, Anytown, MD?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can ask &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Permits/operation/get_permits_by_zip_code_v1_permits_zip_get"&gt;this endpoint&lt;/a&gt; the question, "Which homes in the zip code 94123 pulled ADU permits in the last 6 months?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so on... each endpoint is purpose-built for you to ask a certain type of question. The questions our endpoints can answer are described in our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;lovely API documentation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything's unclear, please holler at me! I'll be happy to share my screen as we do some programming together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;API keys galore&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always thought that to be truly developer-friendly, a company should not stand in between developers and the API. The docs should be great, the API should be fast, and when inspiration strikes, software developers shouldn't have to wait for an API key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we've built an app to give you an API key whenever you want one. Just make an account at &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;https://beta.shovels.ai&lt;/a&gt;. You'll see your shiny new API key on the dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: We built this thing for the web using a new mobile app technology called Flutter. That means we're going to release native mobile apps, too!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;100 million building permits in your pocket, coming soon to an app store near you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="App screenshot" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/app-auth-screenshot.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Spreadsheets for the rest of us&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone knows what JSON is. Even those in tech might think I omitted a vowel from the name of a popular YouTuber / investor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I have a solution. We will run CSV files you as you need them, one-off or monthly, for roughly the same price as our API. We won't give you the entire database, but we'll accommodate you if you'll accommodate a monthly subscription. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSV files are super convenient and until we have a self-serve solution for you to query and download your own CSVs, we'll be happy to do it for you! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pricing page is live&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I always save this section for last? I dunno! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can't give this data away for free. If you start using your API key, we will start asking you to pay for it. Pricing is going to be reasonable, though. The shared goal here is for you to use Shovels data and be absolutely thrilled with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out our pricing (with some minor updates from last time) here: &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pricing"&gt;https://www.shovels.ai/pricing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pricing"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✌️ Peace&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>December 2023 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/december-2023-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-12-05:/blog/december-2023-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We added some new tools to the Shovels web app. We also now have a nationwide contractor directory, so anybody can look up contractors based on their service area, not just their work address. And we're doing a lot of data enrichment!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You can now look up permits by type and ZIP code or by postal address using &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;the Shovels app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal here is not to build the killer building permit SaaS app (that may come later). It's just to help you understand what's sitting in our database and give you some ideas about what to do with this data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since permits are tied to contractors, contractor profiles will start to appear here as well 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels permit directory" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/permits-screenshot.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: see where contractors work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you go to Yelp, or Thumbtack, or Porch, or Angi, or any of those guys to find an electrician "near me," you'll get a list of electricians whose business address is near you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that's not really how electricians and other trades work. They travel! They don't stick to the same ZIP code as their business address. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yelp et al, therefore, won't recommend the best electrician working in your neighborhood. Those guys have no clue who &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt; in your neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But we do!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Contractors/operation/get_contractors_by_activity_zipcode_v1_contractors_activity_zip_get"&gt;API endpoint&lt;/a&gt; to find the most active heat pump (etc, etc) contractor that works in your ZIP code. We'll add a basic interface to the Shovels app to show you this too. Or if you want a sample CSV report, just reply. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Heat pumps galore ☀️&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's undeniable that the world is getting hotter. We can debate how much humanity is at fault, but the increase in worldwide average temperature and all the trouble that causes is irrefutable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whodunnit, there's a new crop of well-funded "climate tech" startups trying to prevent the impacts from getting worse. Shovels is here to help. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winds are shifting towards electric home appliances, and with that comes a tremendous business opportunity. Our timing here is perfect: the Inflation Reduction Act that passed in 2022 is going to hit the markets in 2024. That means a TON of building electrification permits (heat pumps, EV chargers, batteries, and solar) and installations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it also means a lot of innovation and technology which will be visible in data that Shovels is uniquely capable of collecting. We intend to be the de facto leader in building electrification data going into next year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's why I'm excited. Here's a worthwhile &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/09/business/energy-environment/heat-pumps-biden-tax-credits-rebates.html?unlocked_article_code=1.90w.qsq1.QP6pmedG0WQU&amp;amp;smid=url-share"&gt;New York Times article&lt;/a&gt; all about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Now what?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many things! I'll mention a few highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better contact info&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're partnering with a B2B and B2C data company to fill in homeowner and contractor contact details where they're missing on permits. We're also appending homeowner data fields like job title and seniority level, marital status, and much more. On the contractor side, we're improving phone and email coverage, as well as business websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result: some crazy awesome filtering for lead generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online advertising&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you could run online ads to everyone with a solar panel installation? Or an ADU? Or any kind of remodel in the last 5 years? We're partnering with two platforms that can take our permit data online and build lookalike audiences to expand your reach. Let me know if you're interested!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tax assessor data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think it'd be pretty great to have all the tax assessor data (home value, lot size, number of stories, etc) alongside the building permit and building contractor data.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with the better contact info, I believe this will put Shovels second to none in the proptech lead gen category 💯&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very curious what you think of the above. What should we tackle first?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>January 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/january-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-01-04:/blog/january-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A custom GPT, millions of new permits and hundreds of thousands of new contractors. This is a major update to our database and the way you can access it!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nice, I get to be the 32nd person to wish you a happy new year in a marketing newsletter 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, let's get down to business!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the help of ChatGPT, we are officially putting the AI in Shovels.ai. Preview &lt;a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-zXFhOF8SP-shovels-ai"&gt;our custom GPT&lt;/a&gt; before it goes behind a paywall later this month. Tell it to look up some permits! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added a bunch of new contractors and then de-duplicated them so searching by name is less confusing. We also improved the way permits are queried by zip code!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And more things to do with permit data: calculate permit approval times (soon with even more granularity). &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;✨ Have you heard of ChatGPT? ✨&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be true that we are shovels.ai because the .com was taken, but we've always known artificial intelligence would play a major role here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI went and made doing that a whole lot easier by releasing custom GPTs late last year. These used to be called plugins, and they enable ChatGPT to interact with APIs like ours. So, we configured a custom GPT to use all of our API endpoints and &lt;a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-zXFhOF8SP-shovels-ai"&gt;released it to the public&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hear that OpenAI is going to release a GPT Store later this month. When that happens, we'll put the ShovelsAI GPT in there. But for now, anyone with a ChatGPT Plus account ($20/mo) can use our GPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, uhh... yea, it's pretty crazy. Here's what you can do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give it an address in plain text and ask for the permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask for a certain type of permit (heat pump? roof? foundation?) in a zip code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give it your address (or one nearby) and ask for a contractor recommendation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell it to make a CSV from any result and give you a link to download it 😎 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to release some more endpoints so you can filter by permit status, fees, and such. We'll also make it easier to filter by city (we only do zips and states right now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're super excited about this new way to use Shovels! &lt;a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-zXFhOF8SP-shovels-ai"&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🥳 A new product release worthy of 2024 🥳&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are also thrilled to announce our latest data update. Here are the highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Enhancements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expanded Coverage:&lt;/strong&gt; Our jurisdiction, ZIP code, and city counts have increased, offering wider and more comprehensive data coverage:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jurisdictions: from 1,041 to 1,106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ZIP+4 codes: from 113,255 to 121,926&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cities: from 41,582 to 46,813&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better Permit Geolocations:&lt;/strong&gt; Three million additional permits are now precisely geo-located, enhancing the accuracy of location data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More Contractors:&lt;/strong&gt; We increased the number of Shovels contractors by 17% to a total of 2.2M, covering 79K ZIP codes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer Contractor Duplicates:&lt;/strong&gt; we’ve grouped contractors that belong to the same entity within a state. Different branches should now be represented as one contractor company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API Improvements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More intuitive ZIP code queries:&lt;/strong&gt; Querying our API is now more straightforward and includes all +4 extension results even if you only provide 5-digit ZIP code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimized Queries:&lt;/strong&gt; The introduction of materialized views has significantly boosted the efficiency and speed of API queries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Pipeline Updates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metabase Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; Automation in QA and validation processes is enhanced through Metabase integration, offering immediate access to data insights.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City Cleaning:&lt;/strong&gt; We've tightened our city cleaning process to ensure data accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address Updating:&lt;/strong&gt; Our permit address verification is more robust than ever, thanks to the automation of external address source processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Extraction Advancements:&lt;/strong&gt; Progress in extracting more accurate data from raw fields continues, improving the overall data quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallelism in Flows:&lt;/strong&gt; Processing efficiency has been boosted with further optimization of our data flows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels permit directory" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/dashboard.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: track approval times&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to listen to &lt;a href="https://www.capstonegov.com/podcast"&gt;these podcast interviews&lt;/a&gt; of city council members, mayors, and economic development staff in Contra Costa County, where I live. Maybe not everyone's cup of tea, but I dig it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frequently, and I mean wayyy more than you'd think, these civic professionals talk about &lt;strong&gt;permit approval times&lt;/strong&gt;. The first mention was from the CEO of a local chamber of commerce. Then a very well connected commercial real estate broker said it. Then, once again, a local mayor mentioned how important this is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had coffee a few days ago with the CEO of a regional economic development agency out here and she too said permit approval times are critical data for city and county managers to track. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels sees the permit file date and the issue date and can calculate the approval time. We did a &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/"&gt;really thorough analysis&lt;/a&gt; of California EV charger permit processing times back in August. I plan to write another one on nationwide permit approval times next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's some data from the midwest. What's going on, Louisville??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels permit directory" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/midwest.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Looking ahead&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month I'll announce some major progress on a new and improved web app. It's already looking awesome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to 2024!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category><category term="newsletter"></category></entry><entry><title>February 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/february-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-02-12:/blog/february-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We now have a web-based app that people can use to explore our wondrous permit data!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been looking forward to writing this newsletter for more than a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🥳 Today we invite you to sign up for our first major software release! 🥳&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can register at &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;https://beta.shovels.ai&lt;/a&gt;! All you need is an email address. Here's &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-app/"&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; about it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's free for now. There still are a few bugs I know about, and you'll find a few more. It's free because I want your feedback. I figure we'll start charging for access before the next newsletter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-zXFhOF8SP-shovels-ai"&gt;custom GPT&lt;/a&gt; is getting LOTS of use too. Who knew making building permit and contractor data accessible would be such a useful thing? (We did 😇)&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The case for software&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels is a data company. That's our DNA. We're not very proficient (yet) at building software. We'll develop that skill as we go, but what will always set us apart is our devotion to clean, reliable, and useful data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We launched our nationwide &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Permits"&gt;building permit API&lt;/a&gt; in August 2023. We followed that release with a &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Contractors"&gt;nationwide contractor API&lt;/a&gt; in November 2023. We now have a bunch of paying customers and meaningful revenue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just getting this far is a big deal! And we'll continue to serve our current and new API customers. We ❤️ API deals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as you know, the building trades are in transition. Many companies that have a clear, burning need for our data have no means to access it through an API. ChatGPT is great for figuring out what we offer and getting some samples, but it's not great for most commercial uses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"This all sounds good, Ryan," they would say. "Reach out again when you have software."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now we have software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🥳 Introducing: Shovels app v1.0 🥳&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you too excited to continue reading? I get it. &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to see it for yourself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shovels app introduces our three data features: &lt;strong&gt;addresses&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;permits&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;contractors&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/permits-filter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this screenshot, we're looking up all active air source heat pump permits in California that mention the brand Mitsubishi. It's popular! I looked up Fujitsu (what we have) too and didn't see nearly as many. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other potential uses are endless:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for all new permits statewide last month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find all active commercial permits valued at over $1M&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for wave pool permits (yes, somebody asked for this once)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download to a CSV straight from the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anywhere in the good ol' US of A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, wouldn't it be interesting to see which contractors did these Mitsubishi heat pump installs? Click on a permit and you'll get to a permit profile page. On that profile page is (usually) going to be a contractor. Click and that, et voila.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have contractor profiles!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shane.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we see every permit that Shane Patrick O'Malley (don't know him, hope he's nice!) has worked on. Shane does a ton of work in San Francisco. If you're curious, you can click on each of his permits and learn everything you need to know about each job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find more Shanes, hit the Contractors filter where you can look up all the heat pump installers in any ZIP code in the country. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if you just want to look up the permits on an address, you can do that too. Click on Addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/addresses.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the address profile page we're eventually going to show a bunch of property attributes, all of the permits, and all of the contractors. Contractor profiles are going to show a summary of all of their permits by type, stage, and eventually all of their business branches too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeesh. There's always so much more to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: even more heat pump contractors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kr0G9miWRDY"&gt;did a demo of Shovels&lt;/a&gt; for the GreenHome Institute, a 501 c3 nonprofit with a mission to empower people to make healthier and more sustainable choices in the renovation and construction of the places we live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turned out to be a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kr0G9miWRDY"&gt;really long, interesting conversation&lt;/a&gt;. We got into the nuts and bolts of how permit data works, and since there were many trades professionals in the audience, we got to go deep on how we classify permits and rate contractors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/kr0G9miWRDY?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=1871"&gt;Scroll ahead to minute 31&lt;/a&gt; to see us dive into how the new Shovels app can help anyone find their perfect heat pump contractor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The future&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As implied, this is the start of a loooong development process. We've only just begun to build the killer building permits application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine being able to look up a jurisdiction like Palo Alto and see everything in the permitting queue and get estimates on how long the review process will take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine being able to dive into building inspection results, even see who the inspector is, or see each step in the permit review process and how long it usually takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine being able to filter for contractors by the number of heat pumps they've installed and how long it usually took.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep, it's all on the roadmap! Read even more detail in &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-app/"&gt;our launch post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. We're Silicon Valley famous: Here's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FfY92Zk0S4Q&amp;amp;t=3448s"&gt;our mention on TWIST&lt;/a&gt; with Elizabeth Yin, Zach Coelius, and Jason Calacanis 😎&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category><category term="newsletter"></category></entry><entry><title>March 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/march-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-03-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-03-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-03-11:/blog/march-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We launched our Android app in Google Play and made a bunch of data pipeline improvements. We can also now share tables to Snowflake, Big Query, and Databricks.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month we launched &lt;a href="https:/beta.shovels.ai"&gt;our web app&lt;/a&gt;. This month we're offering even more ways to get your hands on our building permit and contractor data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we want to meet you IRL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few days ago we launched an &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.shovels.shovels1"&gt;Android app&lt;/a&gt;. You can find it now on Google Play. Next month we'll launch on the Apple App Store, too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let's meet! The Shovels team will be in SF from March 18-19 and LA on March 21. We'll come to your office. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots more data and API enhancements. Details below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can now push permit and contractor tables into Big Query, Snowflake, Databricks, S3, GCS, and Azure! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;We're so mobile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built the Shovels app using a relatively new technology called Flutter. This software development kit gives our small team a ton of leverage to build cross-platform and make rapid improvements to the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's because of Flutter that we can build a web app and a mobile app at the same time, with the same code, and without a ton of cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could say it gives us mobility. We're moving fast! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a few screenshots of our Android app. Get it on &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.shovels.shovels1"&gt;Google Play now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(We could have launched iOS too, but I gotta save &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; for April.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mobile app screenshots" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/screenshots.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hang out with us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shovels team is international. I'm in California. Luka and Petra are in Europe. We only meet in person a couple of times a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky for you, the next convening is happening the week of March 18 and we want to meet. We'd love to come to your office and chat face-to-face about how you think about building permit and contractor data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about a small team is we can fit in a single Uber. We'll come to you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;San Francisco: March 18-19   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LA area: March 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just reply to me and we'll figure out a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shovels in your data lake&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that for many of you, API access doesn't fully scratch the itch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have bigger plans that will be realized only if you can merge our permits with your own data. We can send you our db files, but to pull them into Snowflake (or wherever) you'll need help from your engineering team and oh boy, that'll take forever. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a solution for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're now offering private shares of our production database tables into Big Query, Snowflake, Databricks, S3, GCS, and Azure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's super fast and easy and gives you unlimited access to query and join our permit and contractor tables with your data lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've already done the engineering -- so you don't have to! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Shovels March release&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a new month, and with that, a bunch of new fixes. Here's our March release notes. We pushed all this to production about a week ago. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better address validation&lt;/strong&gt;: We've improved our ability to validate and enhance cities and ZIP codes on permit addresses. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improvements in contractor grouping&lt;/strong&gt;: We're using more comprehensive details, including addresses and phone numbers, to cluster contractor branches into groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A new address dataset&lt;/strong&gt;: We added over three million exact geo locations to our permits table. We are closing down the gap of unlinked permits (permits without geo coordinates).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improvements in our internal docs&lt;/strong&gt;: We move fast but we also recognize that investing in good documentation now will save us headaches later. We created a new internal knowledge base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API enhancements&lt;/strong&gt;: We introduced a &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/Permits/operation/get_permits_by_id_v1_permits_get"&gt;new API call&lt;/a&gt; that allows for the specification of multiple permits in a single request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database optimization&lt;/strong&gt;: In response to API usage patterns, we've restructured our database architecture. No more timeouts!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;: We have integrated with an awesome tool to help us track API usage, errors, and patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: make permit predictions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever noticed that when one of your neighbors gets an ADU, or installs solar panels, or does the huge remodel and room addition, it seems to trigger everyone else in the neighborhood to do the same? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's FOMO in the home improvement market. I think we can measure this "Keeping up with the Jones's" phenomenon with building permit data and start to see where this wave of home improvements might be swelling in a particular neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not enough of a data scientist to give this justice (and apparently ChatGPT isn't either -- it wasn't very helpful this time) but with our table sharing (see above), perhaps &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can crack this riddle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a chart showing the distribution of the percentage of homes with permits since 2023 by ZIP code. What I mean by that is how much variance is there in "permits per capita" nationwide? Most ZIPs have low permit density, but a few are very active ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's causing the difference? We don't know yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Distribution of permit density by ZIP code" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/permits-distribution.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;This is long enough&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month I plan to announce our iOS app and give a teaser for our V2 API and describe how it will improve the Shovels web and mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category><category term="newsletter"></category></entry><entry><title>April 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/april-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-04-10:/blog/april-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are very excited about the launch of Shovels V2. We know you are too. This is the start of the killer building permit application. The one that should have existed all along. We also can push 100 million building permits and contractors straight into Snowflake, Big Query, and Databricks.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels April 2024 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month was a planning month for us. Luka and Petra joined me in California and we spent a lot of time together. We met a few of you in person, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this mingling and meeting helped us set the stage for the next phase of Shovels. We're growing up a bit. I'll explain what I mean. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shovels V2 is in the works! I'll share more about what exactly this means. In short: a whole bunch of stuff you've told us you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because the V2 is our focus, I've neglected our iOS app development. It's just so V1. We'll get it launched in prep for V2, but it'll take us another month. In the meantime, we've been updating &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.shovels.shovels1"&gt;the Android app&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSA: We can now share 130M permits and 2.5M contractors directly into your Snowflake, Big Query, or Databricks account. This makes some data scientists VERY happy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ever wanted a list of every building permit jurisdiction? &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/list-of-all-building-permit-jurisdictions/"&gt;We released one&lt;/a&gt;. We're working on a V2 of that, too. It will have at least 5,000 more jurisdictions!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out how &lt;a href="https://www.trybeam.com/"&gt;Beam&lt;/a&gt;, one of our happy customers, is using Shovels to &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-revolutionizing-lead-generation-for-beam/"&gt;reach out to contractors&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join us at our &lt;a href="https://lu.ma/z40116as"&gt;Zero Carbon Building Happy Hour&lt;/a&gt; in Lafayette, CA on Earth Day, Monday April 22!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2 is better than 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There comes a time when you just need to cut bait and start over. After watching you use and build on Shovels, and building our own web and mobile apps, it became clear that our API design needed an overhaul. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And not just a 1.1. We needed to sorta break everything. (But don't worry, V1 will be out for a while, and we'll help you through the transition!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what's so awesome about our V2. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filters galore&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're combining tax assessor data with permit data! The possibilities are endless. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filter building permits by lot and building area size, and number of units and stories. Want every solar permit on a $2 million house? Every ADU permit on a 20,000 sq ft lot? You'll have it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll also be able to filter permits by city, county, and jurisdiction. I know, long time coming on this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, there will be parity between permit and contractor filters. Want every solar &lt;em&gt;contractor&lt;/em&gt; who worked on a $2 million house? Every ADU &lt;em&gt;contractor&lt;/em&gt; who worked on a 20,000 sq ft lot? You get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn't possible in V1 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All new tagging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every Shovels user filters by permit tags. Now we're going to make them wayyyy better. Thanks to some AWS incubator credits, we can use AI to tag all 130M permits for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're adding new tags and making them two-level. Check out the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/15rq0VbzD1FKcBzWAhGaAwbqlqm-BZa6nhM8F_qyNcMQ/edit#gid=0"&gt;working draft here&lt;/a&gt; and reply with your feedback. Let us know what's missing! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early tagging results are as amazing as you'd expect. What a time to be a data company. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More contact info&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have A LOT more contact info on homeowners and contractors than we currently expose through the V1 API. This is going to change in V2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In V2, you'll get the homeowners of a given address, all the people who work at a contractor company, and all the contact info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one customer recently told me, the industry needs a ZoomInfo for the building trades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we know which contractors are actually active, Shovels is in the perfect position to deliver it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the profiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things we hear from customers is that Shovels is useful for investment and market selection decisions. However, we don't make it easy for them to count and roll up all of the permits by geo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's fixed in V2. I mentioned that cities, counties, and jurisdictions will be filters. Well, they'll also have profiles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to see every building permit in flight in Palo Alto? How long it's taking to get approval? We'll calculate permit approval times by tag or tag group. We'll also help you navigate between counties, cities, ZIP codes, and the elusive jurisdiction. Each one will have a profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Addresses will have profiles too! See all the permits, contractors, and roll up metrics on any address in our database. This is also coming in V2. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're a data company, but the software play is just so obvious. Somebody needed to build it. Why not us? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a little preview!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Explore our permit data using our web app" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/explore.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: get customers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the companies we spent time with in San Francisco is &lt;a href="https://www.trybeam.com/"&gt;Beam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beam helps contractors run invoices, collect payments, send estimates, and streamline other time-consuming parts of the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They're a smart, passionate team that loves to use data and technology to be more efficient, especially in their marketing. We're pleased to provide them with contractor and permit data that increases the conversion on their outreach and drives more revenue to their bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the full case study &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-revolutionizing-lead-generation-for-beam/"&gt;on our blog&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/Shovels_Beam.pdf"&gt;download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;So tell us what you want, what you really really want&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to influence what gets included in V2!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>May 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/may-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-05-13:/blog/may-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels has grown by adding Betty Wan to the team, aiming to enhance their revenue efforts and overall growth. They are currently seeking feedback on their clickable prototype for version 2, which integrates comprehensive building permit and contractor data into one app. Additionally, they are advancing their data capabilities with AI-enhanced tagging and climate tech initiatives, emphasizing the importance of building permit data in reducing fossil fuel consumption and promoting sustainable building practices.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels May 2024 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Since we last wrote, our team of 3 grew 33%. We're now a team of 4. We're stoked to welcome &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bettywan7/"&gt;Betty Wan&lt;/a&gt; to Shovels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luka and I have known Betty for years and we knew she'd be perfect to lead our revenue efforts. The timing worked, so here we are.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's top of mind as we move to make Shovels 33% better and grow 33% faster. Here's what's up!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a clickable prototype of V2. I need to schedule some &lt;a href="https://shovels.pipedrive.com/scheduler/GXeGebUW/shovels-v2-prototype-test"&gt;short 15 minute calls&lt;/a&gt; to watch &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; click through it. Trade 15 minutes for some permit data? &lt;a href="https://shovels.pipedrive.com/scheduler/GXeGebUW/shovels-v2-prototype-test"&gt;Let's chat!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our new tagging system is almost ready for launch. Our first AI-enhanced tags will be live before the next newsletter! More on this process below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More jurisdictions, more duration calculations, and more contractor de-duplication was in our latest batch release, which was processed using way more automation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because every day is Earth Day 🌱 we have a new &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-empowering-carbon-free-homes/"&gt;climate tech case study&lt;/a&gt;, a new &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/White_Paper_Climate.pdf"&gt;climate tech white paper&lt;/a&gt;, and identified over 14,000 contractors with green rebate program affiliations (more on this next month!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First, a primer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new subscriber told me that she loves this newsletter (I mean, who wouldn't?) but that it's hard to pick up the story mid-stream. Since we're adding &amp;gt; 100 new subscribers every month, I figured she's not alone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here's the plot so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shovels set out in Oct 2022 to make building permit data useful  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luka and Ryan raised some angel and pre-seed money in March 2023  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Petra joined us to boost our data engineering in May 2023  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We released our nationwide building permit API in August 2023  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We followed that with a nationwide building contractor API in Nov 2023  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Lost? Here's &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-api/"&gt;what an API is&lt;/a&gt;)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we launched &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-ai-gpt/"&gt;a custom GPT&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/how-to-use-the-shovels-app/"&gt;a web app&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.shovels.shovels1"&gt;a mobile app&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now we're making all ☝️ a lot better  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Betty just joined to help me sell this stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thus, we need V2 feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/april-2024-newsletter/"&gt;last month's newsletter&lt;/a&gt; I described what V2 is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, it's the killer building permit and building contractor app that doesn't exist in the market yet probably because it seems too obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to give you the ability to look at the permit queue in any jurisdiction, and the active permits on any contractor, and the permit history on any address. All in one killer app. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a clickable prototype and before we really start building it, we'd love to watch you to try to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I get &lt;a href="https://shovels.pipedrive.com/scheduler/GXeGebUW/shovels-v2-prototype-test"&gt;15 mins of your time&lt;/a&gt;? What you'll get in return is influence, our gratitude, and some free Shovels data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the same sneak peak I shared last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Explore our permit data using our web app" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/explore.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From the Engineering desk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Shovels, we're on a mission to make our data dazzle by harnessing the coolest tech out there! We're excited to introduce our latest initiative: using Large Language Models (LLMs) to improve the tagging accuracy of permit records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Testing and Validation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach included a comprehensive evaluation of various LLMs, selecting the best fit for understanding and categorizing permit data. We are establishing a rigorous validation process, incorporating expert feedback to refine the model's accuracy through continuous iterations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalable Architecture for Future Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on our findings, we've been designing a scalable architecture that integrates with our systems and is equipped to handle future expansions. This ensures our capacity to manage and tag data efficiently as our operations grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-tagging and Expanding Tags&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will soon re-tag all existing permit records with this new system, doubling our tag categories! This expansion will enrich our dataset, offering more detailed insights and enhancing the value we deliver to our clients. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have implemented stricter validation rules for permit dates to address previously observed inaccuracies, such as implausible dates like "1900-01-01".   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added construction_duration which captures the time span between the issue and final date. The previous duration field is now called approval_duration.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We fixed issues where some permits did not have a status field set despite having a final_date value.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We resolved a bug affecting the grouping of contractors. Now contractors sharing the same phone number are accurately grouped together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: save humanity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to the notion that "Save the Planet" doesn't make much sense. The planet was fine before it was dominated by homo sapiens and it would be fine without us, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don't need to Save the Planet. We need to save ourselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month was Earth Month, punctuated by Earth Day on April 22. Much of the discussion was about the ocean currents that impact air temperature and weather events everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What contributes to warmer oceans? Greenhouse gases. And what contributes to greenhouse gases? Fossil fuels. And what accounts for a third of all fossil fuel consumption? Buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, heating air and water inside of buildings. This is why building permit data is &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/White_Paper_Climate.pdf"&gt;useful for climate tech&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's why we're working with &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/?category=Case%20Study"&gt;so many climate and construction companies&lt;/a&gt; who want to identify home and building owners who can level up to hyper efficient heat pumps to do the heating currently done by gas, oil, and propane appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permit data isn't perfect, but it's the best tool we've got. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're here to help.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>June 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/june-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-06-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-06-18:/blog/june-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels has launched a rebuilt web application and updated API documentation, adding city search to both the permit and contractor search APIs, along with license classification filtering. They re-classified every building permit in Texas, added 2 million permits, 1.3 million geo-tagged addresses, and expanded to 19 new jurisdictions. The nationwide contractor license data project is integrating state license files and building electrification rebate program affiliations. A website rewrite is underway, enhancing user experience. The new software build includes enhanced CSV downloads and city-based search functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels June 2024 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This month we started rebuilding a few things. The results are exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We rebuilt and re-released our web application. You can check it out now at &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;https://beta.shovels.ai&lt;/a&gt;. It just kinda needed to happen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We rebuilt our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/"&gt;API docs&lt;/a&gt; too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of API, we added city to the &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/search_permits_description_v1_permits_search_get"&gt;permit search API&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/get_contractors_by_activity_city_v1_contractors_activity_city_get"&gt;contractor search API&lt;/a&gt; (and the &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;new app&lt;/a&gt; and our &lt;a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-zXFhOF8SP-shovels-ai"&gt;ShovelsGPT&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can now also search contractors by their license classification  ⚡️&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We re-classified every building permit in Texas and the results are amazing. More details and the math behind this is below. The rest of the country is next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 million more permits and 1.3 million new geo-tagged addresses. We also added 19 new jurisdictions. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our big nationwide contractor license data project has begun. We're integrating all of the state contractor license files we can get our hands on. &lt;strong&gt;We're also including building electrification rebate program affiliations!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've begun a big website rewrite project which you'll start to notice in the coming weeks and months. This just kinda needed to happen too. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Quick reminder&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are here to make building permit data useful. We're hearing from our customers that to be &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; we need to make permit data &lt;em&gt;insightful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where we're headed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We post all of our newsletters on our blog. If you want the full recap on what's been going on at Shovels, you can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/?category=Company"&gt;read them all here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Another new software build&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a good thing we like learning new software platforms. Cuz if we didn't... Man, I'd be in the wrong profession.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few newsletters back (&lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/february-2024-newsletter/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, to be exact) we launched the Shovels app. It was built in Flutter using FlutterFlow. That detail doesn't matter to 99% of you, but it mattered to me, because I picked it. The main benefit of Flutter is it's cross-platform; the same code lets us deploy to web, Android, and iOS. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't know it at the time, but this compatibility leads to a lot of limitations. It was hard getting the web app to do what we wanted it to do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, and this is where you come in, it became clear awfully fast that you don't care about mobile apps. And that meant my Flutter choice was the wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of benefits to this exercise, though. Building our app, "dogfooding" our API, led to the changes you'll see in V2 (more about that &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/april-2024-newsletter/"&gt;in this newsletter&lt;/a&gt;). It also made us very comfortable decoupling the web framework from our data backend. We're leaning into that even more with our &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai/"&gt;brand new beta&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're using a fancy new front-end platform to build it. You'll feel the difference right away. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still very much a beta, though. It's a step along the way to our V2 release with all of the new bells and whistles we've been talking about for months. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, check out all these heat pumps in New York!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Explore our permit data using our web app" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/heat-pumps-in-ny.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a quick summary of the cool new stuff this release does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor contact info is now included in the CSV download.&lt;/strong&gt; On a Permit search, toggle on the Has Contractor? option under Contractor Filters. On a Contractor search, it's always included. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All permit details are included in the CSV download.&lt;/strong&gt; This used to be limited to just a few fields. Now it's not, so you get everything!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search permits by city.&lt;/strong&gt; Now you don't need to remember every zip code in every city! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search contractors by city.&lt;/strong&gt; Ditto.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An overall cleaner, faster experience.&lt;/strong&gt; You'll see. It just feels a lot better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From the Engineering desk&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that software is only as good as the underlying data. That fact is not lost on us. Here's how we improved Shovels permit data last month.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit database growth&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our total number of permits increased by 2 million, and we expanded our coverage to include 18 additional jurisdictions, along with 30,000 more contractors. In June, more than 400,000 new permits were filed that we are now tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better classifications using large language models (LLMs)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could share exactly how we did this, but it's a bit of a trade secret at this point. In short, we tested a whole bunch of LLMs against an expert data annotation platform which served as ground truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By testing against human annotators, we could see how LLMs "think" about permit descriptions. We then optimized this process to bring down both the production time and its associated cost. We've landed in a really nice place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We classified every building permit Texas and have moved on to the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More geo-tagging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're using Esri (where we just joined &lt;a href="https://www.esri.com/en-us/about/partners/our-partners/startups"&gt;their startup program&lt;/a&gt;!) to add 1.3 million geo-coordinates to our addresses, which helps reduce the gap of 3 million un-geocoded addresses. The remainder should be geocoded before next month's release. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor state license files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also next month -- more contractor contact information and building electrification rebate program affiliations. The data collection has been underway for some time and we're finally ready to merge it into production. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: sell stuff to contractors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've been taking a LOT of calls recently from companies that sell to building contractors (they also call them "vendors" or "companies" -- basically, orgs that build things) and they all say the same thing: &lt;strong&gt;finding info about contractors is hard&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, there's ZoomInfo but their firmographic info is static. Employee and revenue numbers don't tell you who does C&amp;amp;I or multifamily or SFH builds. It doesn't tell you where they build or their trades specialization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where permits come in (with some help from state contractor license files!) Permits fill the void and make contractor databases come to life. We've been working on this for a year (from the start of Shovels, really) and are going to push HARD in the coming months to release a truly exceptional sales intelligence product. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the big idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A website for every contractor (or darn close).&lt;/strong&gt; A contractor website domain is the key to joining all sorts of other databases into Shovels. We're going to give them to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts at contractors.&lt;/strong&gt; The phone and email address on the permit might not be the person you want to reach. We get it. We're building out our own B2B contractor contact database so you can reach deeper into the org. This will be available in both the web app and the API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clay integration.&lt;/strong&gt; To know &lt;a href="https://www.clay.com/"&gt;Clay&lt;/a&gt; is to love Clay. We're working with them on a native Shovels integration. This will be 🔥&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classifications and certifications.&lt;/strong&gt; If you want to filter by general contractor, electrician, or other special license, you'll be able to do that too. And we're even adding electrification rebate program affiliations for those of you working to save us from global warming. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're thrilled to be working with all of you. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>July 2024 Newsletter</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/july-2024-newsletter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-07-10:/blog/july-2024-newsletter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This month's Shovels newsletter focuses on community engagement and significant updates. We announced new partnerships with Autodesk, Esri, and Deep Sync, and launched a public Discord server for better interaction. We introduced a new Shovels Coverage Dashboard for transparency and made pipeline improvements, including AI-driven permit classifications. Join us at the Esri User Conference, suggest ideas for our SXSW panel, and check out our comprehensive data insights and upcoming features.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Shovels July 2024 Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This month's update is all about community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have new partnerships. We have a public Discord server. On the data side, we're announcing a new coverage dashboard and a bunch of pipeline improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partnerships galore the last few weeks: We announced our &lt;a href="https://construction.autodesk.com/workflows/construction-software-integrations/shovels/"&gt;Autodesk integration&lt;/a&gt; and our participation in the &lt;a href="https://www.esri.com/en-us/about/partners/our-partners/startups"&gt;Esri startup program&lt;/a&gt; -- we are moving geo-spatially into construction project management!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And another partnership: &lt;a href="https://deepsync.com/"&gt;Deep Sync&lt;/a&gt; for targeting homeowners with ads based on their permit history. I couldn't fit this one into the previous bullet. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We'll be at the &lt;a href="https://www.esri.com/en-us/about/events/uc/overview"&gt;Esri User Conference&lt;/a&gt; in San Diego next week! Reply or join our Discord (see below) if you can meet up. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How about Austin in March 2025? We need ideas for a SXSW panel. We'll be your data partner. &lt;a href="https://panelpicker.sxsw.com/"&gt;Submissions are due&lt;/a&gt; on July 21.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of reaching out, you can now &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/Nypja3cKDx"&gt;chat us up on Discord&lt;/a&gt;. We launched a public server! &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/Nypja3cKDx"&gt;Hop into our Discord&lt;/a&gt; to chat with us about permits, contractors, data science, or the blink-182 summer concert tour (I went and it was EPIC 🤘)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our customers love our transparency. Here's a big heaping spoonful of it: We released a &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; detailed &lt;a href="https://shovels.metabaseapp.com/public/dashboard/0573503d-88ac-4ba4-a723-346b55de482b"&gt;Shovels Coverage Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;. Now you can see exactly where we have (and don't have) building permit and contractor data! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our nationwide AI-driven permit classifications are available to our database and report customers. These are REALLY GOOD. I know because our most skeptical customers said so. We'll roll them out to the API and web app shortly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Quick reminder&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're getting this email because you reached out to us. We send one big newsletter each month. People seem to like it -- we have over 1,500 subscribers! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels exists to make building permit and contractor data useful. We're hearing from our customers that to be &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; we need to make permit data &lt;em&gt;insightful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where we're headed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We post all of our newsletters on our blog. If you want the full recap on what's been going on at Shovels, you can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/?category=Company"&gt;read them all here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Our thesis as a data insights company&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not the only company selling tons of building permit records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big guys like ATTOM and CoreLogic and smaller ones like BuildZoom and Construction Monitor have been doing this for 10+ years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sets us apart, and the whole reason we built Shovels in the shadow of these incumbents, is to &lt;strong&gt;make it easy&lt;/strong&gt; to get insights from building permit data.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it! We bring data coverage transparency, self-service options, an API with great documentation, a public data dictionary, seamless data lake transfers, and enthusiastic one-on-one support to a huge industry that (clearly) needs it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've learned from our customers that clean, reliable, ready-to-use data about what's getting built and who's doing it is very valuable. They want frequent updates, complete coverage, and lots of ways to filter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've learned from my team that doing all the above is hard. Very hard. Which is why, despite the long head start, the other guys haven't done it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that is our thesis for being here, doing what we do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few highlights of what's coming this year: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jurisdiction profiles.&lt;/strong&gt; We're rolling permits and contractors up by jurisdiction to offer insights like permit approval and construction times by permit type. A clickable dashboard for (almost) every building permit office in the country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address profiles.&lt;/strong&gt; See every permit and contractor who worked on an address. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit portfolios.&lt;/strong&gt; Organize groups of permits that you want to track in one place. This feature is particularly useful for brokers and contractors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit inspection details.&lt;/strong&gt; Get the inspection history on a given permit to see how work is progressing. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit review details.&lt;/strong&gt; Find out why permits get stuck in review and how long each review step usually takes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subcontractor relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; GCs usually work with the same subs. Many jurisdictions document it. We're bringing these valuable relationships to light. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are very excited about all of this! It still feels like we're just getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From the Engineering desk&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the engineering tasks we finished last month. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Permit tagging&lt;/strong&gt;: Our new AI-enhanced tagging process is now active in the data pipeline, processing 120 million permits so far. This upgrade allows us to classify new permits more swiftly and efficiently, utilizing the latest AI methods to deliver industry-leading results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhanced address search&lt;/strong&gt;: We introduced a new &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly/#operation/search_addresses_v1_addresses_search_get"&gt;address search API endpoint&lt;/a&gt;. It is designed to simplify free-form address search for our customers and provide normalized addresses that can be used in other API calls supporting address parameters. This update aims to improve the user experience when using our API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced contractor data handling&lt;/strong&gt;: Our contractor's dataset constantly evolves with new data and advanced data engineering techniques. To enable seamless customer integration, we now provide a full changelog detailing all changes from one month to the next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Things to do with permits: make a coverage heat map&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With mapping on my mind, and a new coverage dashboard, I want to specifically call out our &lt;a href="https://shovels.metabaseapp.com/public/dashboard/0573503d-88ac-4ba4-a723-346b55de482b"&gt;new permit coverage heat map&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have geo-coordinates on most of our permit addresses. We can bin these coordinates in 1 degree blocks to visualize our permit coverage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Explore our permit data using our web app" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/coverage.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may not look like much, but this represents a TON of hard work -- pulling data from thousands of jurisdictions into dozens of data pipelines and finally into a single database of 140M geotagged building permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's what I'm looking forward to talking about next week at the Esri conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to nerd out about it online, now you can &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/Nypja3cKDx"&gt;find us on Discord&lt;/a&gt; 🤓&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="company"></category></entry><entry><title>Shovels partners with Autodesk Construction Cloud</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-partners-with-autodesk-construction-cloud/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-08-09:/blog/shovels-partners-with-autodesk-construction-cloud/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Shovels API provides an intuitive platform for proptech enthusiasts looking to leverage building permit data. Users can access and filter building activities via types or specific date ranges. The API employs 'tags' to categorize 33 distinct types of building activities.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We had an exciting July here at Shovels. We added new customers, expanded our coverage, and found new use cases for our products. As part of our mission to make permit data useful, we constantly explore ways to integrate into the construction industry’s existing tools and systems –- and in July  we took a major step forward with Autodesk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shovels is now an &lt;a href="https://www.autodesk.com/blogs/construction/14-new-integrations-for-autodesk-construction-cloud/"&gt;official partner with Autodesk’s Construction Cloud&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autodesk’s Construction Cloud is a leading tool in the building industry, used by millions of architects, contractors, and subcontractors to design, oversee, and execute complex projects across the world. ACC has a web of integrations enabling its users to access all aspects of a given project in one central hub. On July 30th, Autodesk announced that Shovels would be one of 14 new integrations available in ACC, bringing our data closer to the people who can make the most use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This partnership means Autodesk Construction Cloud users can now integrate with Shovels, enabling them to access permit data from across the country, track timelines within jurisdictions, and identify key projects in development. While our current customers are already leveraging Shovels to find qualified contractors, generate leads, and navigate permitting processes, we are eager to see the new applications that will emerge out of this exciting collaboration with one of the leaders in the construction software space!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the Shovels Autodesk Partner Card &lt;a href="https://construction.autodesk.com/workflows/construction-software-integrations/shovels/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and feel free to &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; to chat more about this exciting new partnership.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="construction software"></category><category term="autodesk construction cloud"></category></entry><entry><title>Shovels partners with WattCarbon</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-partners-with-wattcarbon/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Brown</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-08-22:/blog/shovels-partners-with-wattcarbon/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels supports elecrification efforts through their contractor search platform, as well as through supporting WattCarbon. WattCarbon provides a EAC (Energy Attribute Certificate) Marketplace to individuals and corporations alike. Both WattCarbon and Shovels help make climate-friendly and electrification projects accessible for all.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer ‘24 continues to heat up here at Shovels, with recently announced partnerships with &lt;a href="https://www.esri.com/en-us/about/partners/our-partners/startups"&gt;Esri&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/shovels_shovels-integration-autodesk-construction-activity-7216433428143955968-6c-C"&gt;Autodesk&lt;/a&gt;. Those are important commercial relationships. Today we’re announcing a partnership that’s meaningful for a different reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our two-fold mission — making permit data useful AND supporting climate-friendly tech and initiatives — meant that we have a perfect opportunity to partner with &lt;a href="https://www.wattcarbon.com/"&gt;WattCarbon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.wattcarbon.com/p/shovels-and-wattcarbon-join-forces"&gt;Read the WattCarbon announcement blog post here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WattCarbon is a key player in the nascent EAC (&lt;a href="https://blog.wattcarbon.com/p/what-are-the-benefits-of-eacs"&gt;Energy Attribute Certificate&lt;/a&gt;) Marketplace, aggregating different vendors and clean energy projects into one platform. They make it easy to invest in the kinds of climate-saving industries like solar arrays, wind farms, heat pumps, and many more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we partnered with WattCarbon to set aside and invest a percentage of our quarterly revenue into their OpenEAC Exchange. Our US building permit dataset makes it easy to find contractors ready to work on any kind of climate-friendly or electrification projects, and we want to support this type of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2023 we started &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;a series analyzing EV charger construction&lt;/a&gt; trends, and found that there’s still a lot of room to grow. Adoption of other electrification projects, especially heat pumps, are lagging behind solar and wind energy. However, investing in EACs with WattCarbon will finally allow decarbonization efforts (instead of only carbon-free projects) to be included in the bigger picture, and drive those numbers up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href="https://www.wattcarbon.com/"&gt;WattCarbon&lt;/a&gt; to see how you can get involved with EACs, and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;reach out to us&lt;/a&gt; to talk more about this partnership and how Shovels supports electrification projects all over the country. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Company"></category><category term="EAC"></category><category term="WattCarbon"></category><category term="Decarbonization"></category></entry></feed>