<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels | - Data</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/data.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2024-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The growth of EV chargers in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-07-24:/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Shovels, we provide developers with access to monthly EV charger installation data through our building permit API. This data reveals the tremendous growth and geographic distribution of EV charging infrastructure, with insights into the locations and companies involved. Understanding this data is crucial for businesses, developers, and governments to identify areas for expansion and to make informed decisions. With our API, developers can accurately map existing charger locations, analyze infrastructure, and even predict future demand for electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the world embraces green energy solutions, electric vehicles (EVs) have become increasingly popular. This surge in EV adoption has driven a rapid expansion of the EV charging infrastructure – and now developers can use our &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;building permit API&lt;/a&gt; to access monthly EV charger installation data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our EV charger permit data shows tremendous growth of EV charging infrastructure. We see where it's happening and who's doing the installations. To learn more about how to access this valuable data, check out our API documentation at https://shovels.redoc.ly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of EV charging infrastructure expansion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California's EV charging infrastructure is experiencing unprecedented growth as demand for electric vehicles continues to grow. Government policies, such as subsidies and tax incentives, which have created a favorable environment for the growth of the EV market have driven this surge in EV adoption. In addition, technology advancements have lowered the cost of EV charging systems, allowing consumers to easily charge electric vehicles at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, many cities have introduced curbside chargers that allow users to charge their cars while they are parked on the street or in parking garages. New public chargers are added daily across the country. Businesses and organizations are also making significant investments in EV infrastructure. Private companies are building large-scale networks of high-powered chargers that can charge multiple cars at once. These networks can be found in airports, shopping centers, and other areas with high traffic. Additionally, many municipalities are investing heavily in public charger networks, making it easier than ever before to find a charger when you need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These advancements in technology and policy initiatives have helped create an incredibly robust and rapidly growing EV charging infrastructure that is helping drive consumer adoption of EVs worldwide. Developers are now able to access detailed EV charger installation data through the Shovels API. We share historical trends and the exact places and companies who carried out the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data is essential for businesses, developers, and governments to understand the current state of the EV charging market and identify areas where it needs to be expanded. With the right tools, developers can accurately map out existing EV charger locations and explore geographic distribution of charger networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographic information systems (GIS) are powerful tools that enable developers to map out EV charger locations based on their lat/long coordinates or addresses. GIS can also be used to analyze existing infrastructure to identify areas with high demand for additional charging stations. Companies can use Shovels data to see residential EV charger activity, which could inform the location for commercial charging stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For utilities, this data will be helpful to perform stress test modeling on the electrical grid. For states that have put in place GHG reduction goals, understanding consumer adoption of EV chargers will provide more support for transitioning power sources to solar, wind, and other renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EV Charger chart" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shovels_ev_prediction.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights from our EV charger permit dataset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By examining the EV charger data contained in our building permit API, we can gain a new level of insight into the expansion of EV charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/monthly-ev-charger-permits"&gt;public link to this dataset on Kaggle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Compound Annual Growth Rate (CAGR) for the number of EV charger permits in California from 2012 to 2022 is approximately 38.76%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on monthly EV data going back to 2012, we predict California will see about 11,000 EV permits in 2023, roughly 40% more than 2022, and 13,000 EV permits in 2024, another 20% jump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasonality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It appears that the months of August, October, and September have the highest average number of permits. Here are those monthly averages between 2012 and 2022:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January: 184.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February: 150.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;March: 186.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April: 192.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May: 201.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June: 211.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July: 203.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;August: 239.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;September: 236.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October: 240.55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November: 214.45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December: 229.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's worth noting that the number of permits also seems to be lower in the beginning of the year and tends to increase as the year progresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of permits issued each month varies significantly, indicating the presence of considerable volatility in the data. This could be due to various factors such as changes in governmental policies, market demand, technological advancements, and other external factors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one slice of our permit data. We also offer a comprehensive overview of current and future trends in all energy transition activities, including heat pumps and solar installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to access building permit data with Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessing building permit data is essential for developers, businesses, government, and researchers who want to understand the current state of energy transition infrastructure and identify areas where it needs expansion. To make this process easier, we have a building permit API that enables our customers to query building permits by the type of work involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can query for wall battery permits, heat pump HVAC conversions, solar panel installations, and EV charger networks. The data returned from these queries can be used for construction go-to-market activities, providing highly targeted leads for sales teams. Developers can also use this data to create applications related to energy transition activities, such as mapping out EV charger locations or predicting future demand for electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about how you can use the Shovels building permit API to access monthly energy transition activity data and build applications related to this area, check out our documentation at &lt;a href="https://shovels.redoc.ly"&gt;https://shovels.redoc.ly&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category></entry><entry><title>EV charger permit processing times in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-08-10:/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We conducted an in-depth study on electric vehicle (EV) charger permit approval times in California. Our analysis reveals significant variations in approval times across different jurisdictions in the state. While some jurisdictions in Northern California have remarkably fast approval times, many Southern California jurisdictions experience delays of up to two months. Streamlining the permitting process could be a key factor in improving EV charger installation rates. Interestingly, we found no correlation between the volume of permits processed and approval times, suggesting that bureaucratic overload is not the primary cause of delays. This research provides valuable insights for policymakers, businesses, and homeowners looking to navigate the complex landscape of EV charger installations and contribute to the transition to cleaner, more sustainable transportation options.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Background on EV charging in California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with our thinking about EV chargers, which you can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;read more about here&lt;/a&gt;, we're turning our attention now to how long it takes for jurisdictions to approve EV charger permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let's take a step back. This analysis is important because California has committed to deploying five million zero-emission vehicles (ZEVs) and building out 250,000 charging stations by 2025. This includes building a network of nearly 20,000 Level 2 and DC fast EV charging stations across the state. Additionally, the state plans to invest $2.5 billion over the next five years to expand the EV charging infrastructure and provide incentives for drivers to purchase electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having more residential EV chargers would make it easier for California residents to own and use electric vehicles. This would also relieve the burden on public EV chargers. The more EV chargers we have in homes, the less strain on the public chargers required for people who live in multifamily housing and don't have a dedicated charger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More residential EV chargers also creates more jobs and boost the economy. Installation and maintenance of these chargers increases demand for electricians, supporting many local businesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Potential for building permit reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to get more EV chargers installed is to streamline the permitting process. EV chargers, because they are high-voltage, require a licensed electrician and a building permit to begin the installation, and an inspector must approve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this process can be cumbersome, building permits exist to ensure that construction projects adhere to local safety and building codes. This is important for protecting the public and ensuring that buildings are safe and structurally sound. Building permits also provide a way for local governments to track construction projects and collect fees to help fund public services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people advocate permitting reform because the current permitting process is overly burdensome, time consuming, and costly, leading to delays and inefficiencies. Permitting reform may reduce the time and cost of obtaining permits, and make it easier for businesses and homeowners to quickly obtain the necessary approvals to install appliances like EV chargers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, with that background, let's look at the data in California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shovels analysis of EV charger permit approval times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels collects and analyzes building permit data. Two data points that we consistently see are the file date, or when the permit was submitted to the jurisdiction, and the issue date, or when the jurisdiction approved the permit. At this point, work can begin, and we'll eventually see the final date, or when the work was completed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file date and the issue date show how long it takes for a jurisdiction to process a permit. As anyone who has had work done knows, this can be an agonizing process. The longer the delay, the more likely your contractor will get busy or supply costs will increase. Homeowners and contractors both want faster permit approval times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, we set out to ask a few questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Differences between jurisdictions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurisdiction comparison: Which jurisdictions have the fastest and slowest average EV permit approval times? How do they compare to each other?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there differences in permit approval times between Northern and Southern California?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the jurisdictions with the SLOWEST EV median charger permit approval times. We go with the median because there are outliers in the data that will skew the mean. You can see this in the table below, which shows that the mean is greater than the median in each case. The standard deviation and IQR (interquartile range) also demonstrate the skew. Therefore, the median is our best way to compare jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's interesting that four of the five slowest permitting jurisdictions are in Southern California. The median approval times are at least two months. That's too long! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;402.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;152.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;93.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;227.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Francisco&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;194.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;460.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;203.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;192.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Ana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;117.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;103.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Monica&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;235.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;96.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;121.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pasadena&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111.54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;125.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Worst EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/top5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking now at the FASTEST EV charger timing jurisdictions, we see median times of less than a week. Interstingly, all but one of the jurisdictions is in Northern California. Even the averages here are reasonable, coming in at less than a month in the top four, but jumping to nearly three months average in San Diego. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oakland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;817.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dublin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;108.14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;El Dorado County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;266.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sacramento&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;846.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Diego County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;119.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;118.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Best EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/bottom5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, we see the apparent impact of outliers. San Diego has a media approval time of five days, but an average of three months. A few crazy long wait times down there are pulling the average away from the median.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Histogram of San Diego EV charger permit approval times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/sd-histogram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because it was interesting, to further investigate this distinction between Northern California and Southern California, we made one more chart. It tells the story that emerged just by looking at the top 5 and bottom 5 jurisdictions: Northern California issues EV charger permits faster than Southern California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern CA vs Southern CA" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/norcal-v-socal.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatness of the bottom of the candlestick shows the bottom and top quartile wait times. A smaller candle is better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Trends over time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How has the average EV permit approval time changed over the years for each jurisdiction? Are there any jurisdictions where the approval time is consistently getting faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there certain times of the year when EV permit approval times are generally faster or slower? This could indicate seasonal workload fluctuations in permit offices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, we looked for jurisdictions where permit approval times are getting worse and others where they are getting better. Bucking the NorCal/SoCal trend described above, we found that permit times are getting better in Riverside County and worse in Milpitas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-county.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Milpitas approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/milpitas.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The permit counts by year for each county might give some clues as to what's going on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County and Milpitas EV charger permit counts by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-milpitas-count.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the looks of these three charts, we find that the number of EV charger permits in Riverside County skyrocketed during the pandemic, and the jurisdiction must have put some permit streamlining reforms in place because despite the higher volume, they kept the processing times down. This combination led to a precipitous drop in permit approval times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the COVID question was interesting, so we looked across the board and came up with this chart. The processing times actually improved after COVID. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Impact of COVID on permit approval times in California" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/covid.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The relationship between permit volume and approval times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there a correlation between the number of permits a jurisdiction processes and the speed of approval? In other words, do jurisdictions that process more EV permits tend to approve them faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This result surprised us. We assume that bureaucratic government departments are easily overwhelmed. As the number of permit applications increases, we expect that approval times would get slower. In fact, there's no relationship between the volume of permits and the processing times across the jurisdictions in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scatter of approval times and volumes" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/approval-times-scatter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pearson correlation coefficient here is −0.0730. This value indicates a very weak negative relationship. In other words, there's actually a slight tendency for jurisdictions that process more EV permits to approve them a bit faster, but the relationship is weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phew! That was a lot of information about EV charger approval times. It seems we're still just scratching the surface. If you want to do more analysis, &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;. We have lots of data. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category><category term="permit timeline"></category></entry><entry><title>The growth of EV contractors in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/the-growth-of-ev-contractors-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-01:/blog/the-growth-of-ev-contractors-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this final article of our series on EV charger activity in California, we explore the growth of EV charger contractors. We highlight the flourishing EV charger space and provide examples of companies operating in different parts of the ecosystem. Additionally, we showcase the jurisdictions with the most active EV charger contractors and analyze the increasing trend of new contractor activity. The data underscores the growing demand for EV chargers and the expanding market for contractors in this exciting industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Growth in EV charger contractors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This the final article of our recent series on EV charger activity in California. You can also read about the &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;growth of EV chargers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/"&gt;EV charger permit approval timelines&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen the EV charger space flourish, with companies operating in many different parts of the ecosystem. Check out a few examples::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger hardware companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evocharge.com/"&gt;EvoCharge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evercharge.com/"&gt;EverCharge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evbox.com/en/"&gt;EVBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chargepoint.com/"&gt;ChargePoint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger software companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chargelab.co/"&gt;ChargeLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://driivz.com/"&gt;Driivz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.noodoe.com/"&gt;NooDoe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ampup.io/"&gt;AmpUp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger services companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kopperfield.com/"&gt;Kopperfield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://treehouse.pro/"&gt;Treehouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://elephantenergy.com/"&gt;Elephant Energy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quitcarbon.com/"&gt;QuitCarbon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And charge point operators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.evgo.com/"&gt;EVGo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.electrifyamerica.com/"&gt;Electrify America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tesla.com/commercial-charging"&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also sales and design tools like &lt;a href="https://www.monterra.ai/"&gt;Monterra&lt;/a&gt;, purpose-built to help installers (electrical contractors and EV charging project developers) design, quote, and propose projects faster - streamlining and automating an otherwise manual site design and sales process. It’s a busy space! That’s why we’re spending so much time looking into it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already showed that there’s been a boon in EV charger installs. With all of this activity, it seems that there should be an increase in contractor activity, too. That’s what we set out to prove, and the data says it loud and clear: the number of contractors doing EV charger installations is increasing throughout California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put things into context, nearly 30% of all EV chargers in the US are installed in California today, followed by NY, FL, TX, MA, and WA (making up 25% collectively). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Stay tuned, as we’ll soon dive into the data for FL and TX market in a future post!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the jurisdictions with the most active EV charger contractors since 2022:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sacramento County&lt;/strong&gt;: 429 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berkeley&lt;/strong&gt;: 209 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encinitas&lt;/strong&gt;: 203 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oakland&lt;/strong&gt;: 140 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anaheim&lt;/strong&gt;: 119 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took the top two jurisdictions and looked to see if the number of active EV charger contractors has been increasing over time. Indeed it has! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-sacramento.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-sacramento.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-berkeley.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-berkeley.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend line shows that in Sacramento, another EV charger contractor has become active every quarter. In Berkeley, it’s another 1.5 contractors active each quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berkeley and Sacramento have the most active contractors. In jurisdictions with fewer contractors, is the rate of new activity higher? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-grid.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-grid.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower the base, the higher the slope, with dramatic recent increases in contractor activity in Anaheim, Sacramento, and Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Sacramento (City) and Sacramento County are different permitting jurisdictions, so there’s no overlap here in the charts.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that there should be an increase in &lt;strong&gt;new&lt;/strong&gt; EV charger contractors intrigued us, so we did that analysis, too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="new-ev-contractors.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/new-ev-contractors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart shows the number of new contractors entering each of the jurisdictions each year. A new contractor is one that had no permit history in the years prior. You can see an acceleration happening between 2010 and 2022 as these jurisdictions add more &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; EV charger contractors each year. Anaheim is the outlier. They started high and stayed high. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The EV charger market is growing at an increasing rate.&lt;/strong&gt; Supply of contractors (as well as hardware, software, and services) is responding to an increase in demand, and we can track this response using Shovels building permit data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we figured that another sign of market growth could be EV contractors expanding their own territories. We decided to look at the percentage of EV contractors doing work in multiple jurisdictions each quarter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="multiple-jurisdictions-ev-contractors.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/multiple-jurisdictions-ev-contractors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This geographical expansion is also trending up, with a big surge during COVID that sustained after the pandemic retreated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool stuff, right? This means EV charging is hot. Dare we say &lt;em&gt;electric&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a good market to work and invest in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re excited by all of this data, and we want you to be excited too. Want to do your own epic analysis of the building trades? Get in touch: sales@shovels.ai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daviddkkim/"&gt;David Kim&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.monterra.ai"&gt;Monterra&lt;/a&gt; for contributing to this article!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building contractors"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category></entry><entry><title>Do rebate programs matter to contractors in the SF Bay Area?</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/do-rebate-programs-matter-to-contractors-in-the-sf-bay-area/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-19:/blog/do-rebate-programs-matter-to-contractors-in-the-sf-bay-area/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We look at the impact of BayREN's initiatives on the Bay Area's energy upgrade trends, revealing a significant increase in heat pump installations by BayREN-affiliated contractors compared to a lesser focus on solar panel installations. It suggests that BayREN is strategically filling gaps in the building electrification market.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A key player in the building electrification transformation in the San Francisco Bay Area is the &lt;a href="https://www.bayren.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Bay Area Regional Energy Network&lt;/a&gt; (BayREN). Over the past decade it has become synonymous with fostering environmentally conscious decisions among communities and building contractors alike. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our recent research into building permits has revealed compelling trends that not only underscore BayREN's influence but also signal a shift in the region's approach to energy efficiency. By analyzing building permits, we discovered a stark difference in the uptake of various energy upgrades between contractors affiliated with BayREN and those who are not. This isn't just numerical variance; it's a narrative about where we're heading and what fuels our journey towards a greener Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bayren vs other contractors" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/contractors_comparison_chart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data paints a telling picture: BayREN contractors are installing significantly more heat pumps than their non-affiliated counterparts. Why heat pumps? Heat pumps are a linchpin in the arsenal against energy inefficiency. They serve dual purposes, providing heating and cooling in a single system, and they're remarkably efficient, actually cutting down total energy use compared to traditional HVAC systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This finding aligns perfectly with BayREN's strategic priorities. By streamlining the installation of heat pumps, BayREN is not just pushing for a reduction in greenhouse gas emissions; it's also promoting a technology that can adapt to and leverage the Bay Area's mild climate, proving to be both a cost-effective and environmentally friendly solution for local homeowners and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the same research indicated that BayREN contractors install fewer solar panels than their peers. This could seem counterintuitive at first glance, given the solar industry's growth and the region's ample sunshine. However, this trend could be attributed to several factors. Perhaps the solar market in the Bay Area is already well-developed, necessitating less intervention. Alternatively, it could be that BayREN's current initiatives are designed to fill gaps in the building electrification market where other technologies, such as heat pumps, have yet to mature. It's also possible that the existing financial incentives for solar installations are already optimized, so BayREN focuses its resources on other technologies in need of a push.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to electric vehicle (EV) charger installations, the numbers align closely between BayREN contractors and others. EV technology is an area of robust growth, supported by statewide initiatives and private investments alike. The parallel trends here suggest that the push for EV infrastructure might be equally strong across the board, indicating that BayREN's efforts in this domain are complementing an already thriving market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do these trends mean for the Bay Area's energy landscape? They showcase BayREN's role in helping the region's energy efficiency trajectory. By fostering the adoption of heat pumps, BayREN is helping to redefine the standard for residential and commercial heating and cooling systems. This not only contributes to lowering carbon footprints but also aligns with broader goals of resilience and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data also prompts a re-evaluation of solar energy's place in the Bay Area's proptech scene. With the solar panel market potentially approaching saturation, it may be time to innovate further or redirect focus to complementing technologies that enhance solar efficiency or storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings illuminate the nuanced dynamics of energy upgrades in the Bay Area. As BayREN continues to lead with forward-thinking programs, it remains crucial for us to monitor how these initiatives shape both the demand and the labor market to install these systems. The shifts we see today, influenced by BayREN's strategic decisions, are creating a blueprint for other regions to follow. And as we continue to gather data and analyze trends, we look forward to contributing the conversation around proptech and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="bayren"></category><category term="rebates"></category></entry><entry><title>The list of every building permit jurisdiction in the US</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/list-of-all-building-permit-jurisdictions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-04-06:/blog/list-of-all-building-permit-jurisdictions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels is open-sourcing of a comprehensive list of building permit jurisdictions that we discovered only recently. Our new database includes over ten thousand building permit jurisdictions and associates each jurisdiction with a county and state.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/building-permit-jurisdictions-in-the-united-states" target="_blank"&gt;another Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt; from the Shovels vault. Our &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdiction_mappings.csv"&gt;latest file&lt;/a&gt; is a comprehensive mapping of state, county, and building permit jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is this list of building permit jurisdictions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file includes over 10,000 building permit jurisdictions (AHJs -- authority-having jurisdictions), and relates each jurisdiction to its respective state and county. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found this mapping buried in an &lt;a href="https://socds.huduser.gov/permits/" target="_blank"&gt;obscure government website&lt;/a&gt;. We noticed that when we clicked on a state, a select box appeared with all of the counties in that state. This mapping is widely available from the US Census and many other open data sources. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when we clicked on the county, another select box appeared with every building permit jurisdiction in the county. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; got our attention. Before this discovery, we didn't know of a single source of truth for how many AHJs are out there for building permits. Now we can count at least 10,000 of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who needs a list of every building permit jurisdiction?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When architects, developers, and homeowners start a new project, the first question they might ask is, "Where do I file my building permits?" The answer is far from obvious! Many cities don't have building departments; they delegate building permitting to the county.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list we are open-sourcing today includes every building permit jurisdiction. If a city or town is on this list, then they issue their own building permits. If a city or town is not on this list, then it's safe to conclude that their AHJ is the county. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We figure many folks who work in cities and counties don't know every AHJ within their boundaries. Now they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How many building permit jurisdictions are in each state?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got curious and decided to ask this data a few questions. How many AHJs are in each state? Does that jurisdiction count correlate with population? We had to merge in some public census data to figure this out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average, there are about ten permit jurisdictions per county. If a county has a million residents, that means each permit jurisdiction serves about 100,000 people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pennsylvania stands out with the highest number of permit jurisdictions, totaling 1575. No other state comes close! It's unclear why Pennsylvania needs so many of them. For example, although Pennsylvania has the same population as Ohio, it has almost 3X the number of building permit jurisdictions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart makes the outliers easy to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Population vs Jurisdiction Count" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdictions-vs-population.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's a table of every state, its population, number of jurisdictions, and the ratio of jurisdictions per 100,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="left"&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Population&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Permit Jurisdictions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Jurisdictions per 100,000 Residents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Alaska&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;733406&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.954451&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5108468&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.91507&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Arkansas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3067732&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.58571&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Arizona&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7431344&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.0227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;38965193&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;471&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.20877&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Colorado&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5877610&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;113&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.92255&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Connecticut&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3617176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;137&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.78749&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;District of Columbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;678972&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.147281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Delaware&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1031890&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.93819&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Florida&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;22610726&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;389&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.72042&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11029227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;307&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.78351&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Hawaii&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1435138&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.139359&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Iowa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3207004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;235&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7.32771&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Idaho&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1964726&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.81733&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Illinois&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12549689&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;696&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.54595&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Indiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6862199&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.30798&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Kansas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2940546&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.84925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Kentucky&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4526154&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;135&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.98266&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Louisiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4573749&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;164&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.58568&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7001399&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;317&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.52767&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Maryland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6180253&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.19736&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Maine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1395722&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;131&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9.38582&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Michigan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;10037261&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;659&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.56554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Minnesota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5737915&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;474&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.26084&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6196156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;340&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.48727&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2939690&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.55129&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Montana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1132812&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.85379&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;North Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;10835491&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;226&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.08574&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;North Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;783926&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9.18454&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Nebraska&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1978379&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.80191&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1402054&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.77724&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Jersey&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9290841&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;572&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.1566&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Mexico&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2114371&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.945908&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Nevada&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3194176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.344377&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New York&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;19571216&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;906&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.62925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ohio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11785935&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;586&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.97203&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Oklahoma&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4053824&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.18218&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4233358&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;130&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.07085&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12961683&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1575&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12.1512&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Rhode Island&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1095962&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.55852&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;South Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5373555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;152&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.82867&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;South Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;919318&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.30902&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Tennessee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7126489&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.72224&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Texas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;30503301&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;651&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.1342&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Utah&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3417734&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;141&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.12554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8715698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.31946&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Vermont&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;647464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.17795&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Washington&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7812880&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;201&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.57267&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5910955&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;530&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.9664&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;West Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1770071&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.49691&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Wyoming&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;584057&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.05459&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mission is to make government data meaningful and actionable. Our tools and datasets, like the one we're open-sourcing today, are designed to make government data useful. It's a step in the right direction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the links again: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grab it &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/building-permit-jurisdictions-in-the-united-states" target="_blank"&gt;on Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdiction_mappings.csv"&gt;download the CSV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="AHJ"></category><category term="permit jurisdiction"></category></entry><entry><title>US Solar Construction Trends (2024)</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/us-solar-construction-trends-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Brown</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-09-11:/blog/us-solar-construction-trends-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Shovels dataset and model can highlight key construction trends and patterns. In this blog, we discuss solar construction specifically due to the RE+ clean energy convention. Use Shovels to inform your construction company's business models and strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.re-plus.com/"&gt;RE+&lt;/a&gt; is the largest and most comprehensive clean energy conference in the United States. In honor of it’s 20th Anniversary, we’re publishing some insights we’ve gleaned from our datasets and models here at Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, if you’re reading at the time of publication, we’re at RE+ in Anaheim right now! Come find us on the floor, or reach out directly to coordinate — we want to meet you!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar tech, and clean energy tech generally, is something we’re really passionate about. We’ve recently &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-partners-with-wattcarbon/"&gt;partnered with WattCarbon&lt;/a&gt; to support their decarbonization efforts via their new Energy Attribute Certificate (EAC) Marketplace, and also worked with &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-empowering-carbon-free-homes/"&gt;Carbon Free Homes&lt;/a&gt; to improve their climate-friendly contractor matching platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, we’re shining a light on solar construction trends thus far in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Shovels Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone new here (welcome!), we’ll give a quick refresher on what we do. Shovels is a building insights company, and we aggregate, normalize, and make construction data useful. It started at building permits, but we’re expanding into more robust models by incorporating contractor profiles, tax assessor files, and other publicly accessible data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, we can query, filter, and summarize the data any which way you like: by market, geo-region, or address; by permit type or fields, by contractors, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For today’s analysis, we’re going to be querying our model based on two key filters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Permits filed this year; or &lt;code&gt;file_date = 2024%&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar-inclusive projects (anything that includes solar technology); or &lt;code&gt;solar = true&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[!NOTE]
Fields like these, along with other variables used in our model, can be reviewed in our &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qiIxx37_-6vGfGp2i5pXv4w2FdsLsShjCqSVO5v6OMQ/edit?gid=1818227349#gid=1818227349"&gt;Data Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can dig deeper than those to get into specifics of things like &lt;strong&gt;Contractor Availability&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Average Approval Time&lt;/strong&gt; later on, but for now these two filters will serve as the foundation of this dataset. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are solar projects all over the country, it’s clear that the vast majority of activity is here in California, so let’s take a closer look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spotlight on California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California has led the nation in solar adoption and technology for decades now, and part of that adoption is the widespread governmental support in the forms of &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/home-improvement/solar/california-solar-incentives/"&gt;incentives, tax credits, and rebates&lt;/a&gt;. So it makes sense that The Golden State continues to outpace everyone else in the push towards net-zero emissions and clean energy production. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filtering the dataset above once again — by &lt;code&gt;state = CA&lt;/code&gt; — and sorting by geo-coordinates &lt;code&gt;lat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;long&lt;/code&gt;, we can see a heat map of this year’s construction volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Map of California with heatmap showing volume of solar project permits, by geographical coordinates." src="/images/digging-in-ca-solar-construction-heatmap-watermarked.png"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hubs like Los Angeles, San Diego, San Jose, and others in the Central Valley show the most activity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tax incentives aren’t the entire picture. The state-wide building permit pipeline is a well-oiled machine. Experienced contractors and administrative support makes filing your permit easy, which results in an astounding 6.15 day average approval time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sidenote: to be fair to the other states, some are performaing just as well if not better than California (eg, NY with an average of 2.8 days), yet none come even close to the permit volume. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More impressively, the hotspots above have even better approval times, with San Diego County leading the way with a blistering 1.79 day average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, this is across all projects which include solar installation of any kind, so small panels on your personal home are counted in line with massive commercial construction that cover their roofs with solar arrays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your local jurisdiction wants to up their pace and adoption rates for solar- or other green-energy technologies, California is a good place to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights, In Season&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metrics like &lt;strong&gt;Permit Volume&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Average Approval Time&lt;/strong&gt; can be nice pats-on-the-back, but the real power of the Shovels model is trend and market gap analysis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the model we’ve refined already, let’s tweak it slightly to get a historical view of the past 4 years. If we adjust the original filter to &lt;code&gt;file_date = 202%&lt;/code&gt; (to cover everything built since January 2020), we can see the construction trends and seasonalities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is one such query, visualized and sorted by &lt;code&gt;month&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Area line graph showing California permit volume for solar projects since January 2020, by month." src="/images/digging-in-ca-solar-construction-trend-2020s-watermarked.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are seasonal spikes before and after Summer, with the biggest peak to date in March 2023 with a staggering 33k+ solar-inclusive project permits filed that month alone. This graph illustrates the duality of man, or at least those who installed their solar panels in advance versus those who regret not getting them up earlier that Spring. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trendline here shows that things are slowing down, but only in comparison to the previous years’ highs. Using other construction data to determine solar saturation and wider construction trends in your specific market, Shovels could provide actionable insights into timing and lead-gen opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe other green technologies like &lt;a href="https://techcleanca.com/"&gt;heat pumps&lt;/a&gt; are relatively underrated, and ripe for a strong market push?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[!Tip]
Free Shovels Advice: if you’re a solar supplier or in a solar-adjacent market, now would be &lt;strong&gt;a very good time&lt;/strong&gt; to confirm those outbound pipelines are fired up to prepare for the early Fall installation push. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels has in-depth contractor profiles and data that you could use for that very purpose — &lt;a href="mailto:sales@shovels.ai"&gt;reach out today&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derivative metrics that can inform projections and trends are the name of the game, and a core tenet of the Shovels model and datasets. While solar construction is close-to-heart, we cover all range of project types — if it requires a building permit (and the jurisdiction digitizes their records), then we’ll have it for consumption. If we don't, let us know and we'll get it for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Get Your Own Shovel Today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permit data is the foundation of the Shovels platform, and wrangling it at scale can provide actionable business insights, legislative or administrative effectiveness reports, or anything in between. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that kind of scale is what you’re looking for, then our &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/data-feed"&gt;Enterprise&lt;/a&gt; product will be the best fit. We’ll send you the files and raw data for consumption into, or in tandem with, existing models. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we have a &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/api"&gt;robust API&lt;/a&gt; for direct integration of our data to your own platform(s). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out our &lt;a href="https://beta.shovels.ai"&gt;Free Trial&lt;/a&gt; today to see how our platform works, or get in contact with us for a demo and sample dataset of your preferred market at &lt;a href="mailto:sales@shovels.ai"&gt;sales@shovels.ai&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Digging, and let us know how you enjoyed RE+ in Anaheim this year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="RE Plus"></category><category term="Solar"></category><category term="Insights"></category></entry></feed>