<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels :) - Data</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/data.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The growth of EV chargers in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-07-24:/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Get a comprehensive overview of the current and future trends in energy transition activities, including EV charger infrastructure growth, with Shovels building permit API&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the world embraces green energy solutions, electric vehicles (EVs) have become increasingly popular. This surge in EV adoption has driven a rapid expansion of the EV charging infrastructure – and now developers can use our &lt;a href="https://api.shovels.ai/docs"&gt;building permit API&lt;/a&gt; to access monthly EV charger installation data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our EV charger permit data shows tremendous growth of EV charging infrastructure. We see where it's happening and who's doing the installations. To learn more about how to access this valuable data, check out our API documentation at https://api.shovels.ai/docs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of EV charging infrastructure expansion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California's EV charging infrastructure is experiencing unprecedented growth as demand for electric vehicles continues to grow. Government policies, such as subsidies and tax incentives, which have created a favorable environment for the growth of the EV market have driven this surge in EV adoption. In addition, technology advancements have lowered the cost of EV charging systems, allowing consumers to easily charge electric vehicles at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, many cities have introduced curbside chargers that allow users to charge their cars while they are parked on the street or in parking garages. New public chargers are added daily across the country. Businesses and organizations are also making significant investments in EV infrastructure. Private companies are building large-scale networks of high-powered chargers that can charge multiple cars at once. These networks can be found in airports, shopping centers, and other areas with high traffic. Additionally, many municipalities are investing heavily in public charger networks, making it easier than ever before to find a charger when you need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These advancements in technology and policy initiatives have helped create an incredibly robust and rapidly growing EV charging infrastructure that is helping drive consumer adoption of EVs worldwide. Developers are now able to access detailed EV charger installation data through the Shovels API. We share historical trends and the exact places and companies who carried out the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data is essential for businesses, developers, and governments to understand the current state of the EV charging market and identify areas where it needs to be expanded. With the right tools, developers can accurately map out existing EV charger locations and explore geographic distribution of charger networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographic information systems (GIS) are powerful tools that enable developers to map out EV charger locations based on their lat/long coordinates or addresses. GIS can also be used to analyze existing infrastructure to identify areas with high demand for additional charging stations. Companies can use Shovels data to see residential EV charger activity, which could inform the location for commercial charging stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For utilities, this data will be helpful to perform stress test modeling on the electrical grid. For states that have put in place GHG reduction goals, understanding consumer adoption of EV chargers will provide more support for transitioning power sources to solar, wind, and other renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EV Charger chart" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shovels_ev_prediction.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights from our EV charger permit dataset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By examining the EV charger data contained in our building permit API, we can gain a new level of insight into the expansion of EV charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/monthly-ev-charger-permits"&gt;public link to this dataset on Kaggle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Compound Annual Growth Rate (CAGR) for the number of EV charger permits in California from 2012 to 2022 is approximately 38.76%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on monthly EV data going back to 2012, we predict California will see about 11,000 EV permits in 2023, roughly 40% more than 2022, and 13,000 EV permits in 2024, another 20% jump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasonality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It appears that the months of August, October, and September have the highest average number of permits. Here are those monthly averages between 2012 and 2022:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January: 184.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February: 150.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;March: 186.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April: 192.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May: 201.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June: 211.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July: 203.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;August: 239.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;September: 236.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October: 240.55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November: 214.45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December: 229.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's worth noting that the number of permits also seems to be lower in the beginning of the year and tends to increase as the year progresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of permits issued each month varies significantly, indicating the presence of considerable volatility in the data. This could be due to various factors such as changes in governmental policies, market demand, technological advancements, and other external factors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one slice of our permit data. We also offer a comprehensive overview of current and future trends in all energy transition activities, including heat pumps and solar installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to access building permit data with Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessing building permit data is essential for developers, businesses, government, and researchers who want to understand the current state of energy transition infrastructure and identify areas where it needs expansion. To make this process easier, we have a building permit API that enables our customers to query building permits by the type of work involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can query for wall battery permits, heat pump HVAC conversions, solar panel installations, and EV charger networks. The data returned from these queries can be used for construction go-to-market activities, providing highly targeted leads for sales teams. Developers can also use this data to create applications related to energy transition activities, such as mapping out EV charger locations or predicting future demand for electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about how you can use the Shovels building permit API to access monthly energy transition activity data and build applications related to this area, check out our documentation at &lt;a href="https://api.shovels.ai/docs"&gt;https://api.shovels.ai/docs&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category></entry><entry><title>EV charger permit processing times in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-08-10:/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's a wide disparity in the time it takes for EV charger permits to get approved in California. Some jurisdictions are 10X slower than others, and we'll share which are fastest and slowest to approve EV charger permits in California.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Background on EV charging in California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with our thinking about EV chargers, which you can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;read more about here&lt;/a&gt;, we're turning our attention now to how long it takes for jurisdictions to approve EV charger permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let's take a step back. This analysis is important because California has committed to deploying five million zero-emission vehicles (ZEVs) and building out 250,000 charging stations by 2025. This includes building a network of nearly 20,000 Level 2 and DC fast EV charging stations across the state. Additionally, the state plans to invest $2.5 billion over the next five years to expand the EV charging infrastructure and provide incentives for drivers to purchase electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having more residential EV chargers would make it easier for California residents to own and use electric vehicles. This would also relieve the burden on public EV chargers. The more EV chargers we have in homes, the less strain on the public chargers required for people who live in multifamily housing and don't have a dedicated charger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More residential EV chargers also creates more jobs and boost the economy. Installation and maintenance of these chargers increases demand for electricians, supporting many local businesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Potential for building permit reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to get more EV chargers installed is to streamline the permitting process. EV chargers, because they are high-voltage, require a licensed electrician and a building permit to begin the installation, and an inspector must approve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this process can be cumbersome, building permits exist to ensure that construction projects adhere to local safety and building codes. This is important for protecting the public and ensuring that buildings are safe and structurally sound. Building permits also provide a way for local governments to track construction projects and collect fees to help fund public services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people advocate permitting reform because the current permitting process is overly burdensome, time consuming, and costly, leading to delays and inefficiencies. Permitting reform may reduce the time and cost of obtaining permits, and make it easier for businesses and homeowners to quickly obtain the necessary approvals to install appliances like EV chargers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, with that background, let's look at the data in California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shovels analysis of EV charger permit approval times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels collects and analyzes building permit data. Two data points that we consistently see are the file date, or when the permit was submitted to the jurisdiction, and the issue date, or when the jurisdiction approved the permit. At this point, work can begin, and we'll eventually see the final date, or when the work was completed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file date and the issue date show how long it takes for a jurisdiction to process a permit. As anyone who has had work done knows, this can be an agonizing process. The longer the delay, the more likely your contractor will get busy or supply costs will increase. Homeowners and contractors both want faster permit approval times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, we set out to ask a few questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Differences between jurisdictions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurisdiction comparison: Which jurisdictions have the fastest and slowest average EV permit approval times? How do they compare to each other?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there differences in permit approval times between Northern and Southern California?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the jurisdictions with the SLOWEST EV median charger permit approval times. We go with the median because there are outliers in the data that will skew the mean. You can see this in the table below, which shows that the mean is greater than the median in each case. The standard deviation and IQR (interquartile range) also demonstrate the skew. Therefore, the median is our best way to compare jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's interesting that four of the five slowest permitting jurisdictions are in Southern California. The median approval times are at least two months. That's too long! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;402.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;152.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;93.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;227.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Francisco&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;194.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;460.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;203.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;192.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Ana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;117.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;103.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Monica&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;235.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;96.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;121.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pasadena&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111.54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;125.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Worst EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/top5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking now at the FASTEST EV charger timing jurisdictions, we see median times of less than a week. Interstingly, all but one of the jurisdictions is in Northern California. Even the averages here are reasonable, coming in at less than a month in the top four, but jumping to nearly three months average in San Diego. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oakland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;817.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dublin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;108.14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;El Dorado County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;266.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sacramento&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;846.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Diego County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;119.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;118.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Best EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/bottom5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, we see the apparent impact of outliers. San Diego has a media approval time of five days, but an average of three months. A few crazy long wait times down there are pulling the average away from the median.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Histogram of San Diego EV charger permit approval times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/sd-histogram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because it was interesting, to further investigate this distinction between Northern California and Southern California, we made one more chart. It tells the story that emerged just by looking at the top 5 and bottom 5 jurisdictions: Northern California issues EV charger permits faster than Southern California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern CA vs Southern CA" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/norcal-v-socal.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatness of the bottom of the candlestick shows the bottom and top quartile wait times. A smaller candle is better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Trends over time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How has the average EV permit approval time changed over the years for each jurisdiction? Are there any jurisdictions where the approval time is consistently getting faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there certain times of the year when EV permit approval times are generally faster or slower? This could indicate seasonal workload fluctuations in permit offices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, we looked for jurisdictions where permit approval times are getting worse and others where they are getting better. Bucking the NorCal/SoCal trend described above, we found that permit times are getting better in Riverside County and worse in Milpitas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-county.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Milpitas approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/milpitas.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The permit counts by year for each county might give some clues as to what's going on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County and Milpitas EV charger permit counts by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-milpitas-count.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the looks of these three charts, we find that the number of EV charger permits in Riverside County skyrocketed during the pandemic, and the jurisdiction must have put some permit streamlining reforms in place because despite the higher volume, they kept the processing times down. This combination led to a precipitous drop in permit approval times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the COVID question was interesting, so we looked across the board and came up with this chart. The processing times actually improved after COVID. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Impact of COVID on permit approval times in California" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/covid.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The relationship between permit volume and approval times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there a correlation between the number of permits a jurisdiction processes and the speed of approval? In other words, do jurisdictions that process more EV permits tend to approve them faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This result surprised. We assume that bureaucratic government departments are easily overwhelmed. As the number of permit applications increases, we expect that approval times would get slower. In fact, there's no relationship between the volume of permits and the processing times across the jurisdictions in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scatter of approval times and volumes" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/approval-times-scatter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pearson correlation coefficient here is −0.0730. This value indicates a very weak negative relationship. In other words, there's actually a slight tendency for jurisdictions that process more EV permits to approve them a bit faster, but the relationship is weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phew! That was a lot of information about EV charger approval times. It seems we're still just scratching the surface. If you want to do more analysis, &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;. We have lots of data. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category><category term="permit timeline"></category></entry></feed>