<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels | - Data</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/data.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2025-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The growth of EV chargers in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-07-24:/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Shovels, we provide developers with access to monthly EV charger installation data through our building permit API. This data reveals the tremendous growth and geographic distribution of EV charging infrastructure, with insights into the locations and companies involved. Understanding this data is crucial for businesses, developers, and governments to identify areas for expansion and to make informed decisions. With our API, developers can accurately map existing charger locations, analyze infrastructure, and even predict future demand for electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the world embraces green energy solutions, electric vehicles (EVs) have become increasingly popular. This surge in EV adoption has driven a rapid expansion of the EV charging infrastructure – and now developers can use our &lt;a href="https://docs.shovels.ai/api-reference"&gt;building permit API&lt;/a&gt; to access monthly EV charger installation data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our EV charger permit data shows tremendous growth of EV charging infrastructure. We see where it's happening and who's doing the installations. To learn more about how to access this valuable data, check out our API documentation at https://docs.shovels.ai/api-reference!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of EV charging infrastructure expansion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California's EV charging infrastructure is experiencing unprecedented growth as demand for electric vehicles continues to grow. Government policies, such as subsidies and tax incentives, which have created a favorable environment for the growth of the EV market have driven this surge in EV adoption. In addition, technology advancements have lowered the cost of EV charging systems, allowing consumers to easily charge electric vehicles at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, many cities have introduced curbside chargers that allow users to charge their cars while they are parked on the street or in parking garages. New public chargers are added daily across the country. Businesses and organizations are also making significant investments in EV infrastructure. Private companies are building large-scale networks of high-powered chargers that can charge multiple cars at once. These networks can be found in airports, shopping centers, and other areas with high traffic. Additionally, many municipalities are investing heavily in public charger networks, making it easier than ever before to find a charger when you need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These advancements in technology and policy initiatives have helped create an incredibly robust and rapidly growing EV charging infrastructure that is helping drive consumer adoption of EVs worldwide. Developers are now able to access detailed EV charger installation data through the Shovels API. We share historical trends and the exact places and companies who carried out the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering and analyzing EV charger data is essential for businesses, developers, and governments to understand the current state of the EV charging market and identify areas where it needs to be expanded. With the right tools, developers can accurately map out existing EV charger locations and explore geographic distribution of charger networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographic information systems (GIS) are powerful tools that enable developers to map out EV charger locations based on their lat/long coordinates or addresses. GIS can also be used to analyze existing infrastructure to identify areas with high demand for additional charging stations. Companies can use Shovels data to see residential EV charger activity, which could inform the location for commercial charging stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For utilities, this data will be helpful to perform stress test modeling on the electrical grid. For states that have put in place GHG reduction goals, understanding consumer adoption of EV chargers will provide more support for transitioning power sources to solar, wind, and other renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EV Charger chart" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shovels_ev_prediction.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights from our EV charger permit dataset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By examining the EV charger data contained in our building permit API, we can gain a new level of insight into the expansion of EV charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/monthly-ev-charger-permits"&gt;public link to this dataset on Kaggle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Compound Annual Growth Rate (CAGR) for the number of EV charger permits in California from 2012 to 2022 is approximately 38.76%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on monthly EV data going back to 2012, we predict California will see about 11,000 EV permits in 2023, roughly 40% more than 2022, and 13,000 EV permits in 2024, another 20% jump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasonality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It appears that the months of August, October, and September have the highest average number of permits. Here are those monthly averages between 2012 and 2022:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January: 184.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February: 150.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;March: 186.91&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April: 192.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May: 201.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June: 211.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July: 203.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;August: 239.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;September: 236.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October: 240.55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November: 214.45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December: 229.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's worth noting that the number of permits also seems to be lower in the beginning of the year and tends to increase as the year progresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of permits issued each month varies significantly, indicating the presence of considerable volatility in the data. This could be due to various factors such as changes in governmental policies, market demand, technological advancements, and other external factors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one slice of our permit data. We also offer a comprehensive overview of current and future trends in all energy transition activities, including heat pumps and solar installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to access building permit data with Shovels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessing building permit data is essential for developers, businesses, government, and researchers who want to understand the current state of energy transition infrastructure and identify areas where it needs expansion. To make this process easier, we have a building permit API that enables our customers to query building permits by the type of work involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can query for wall battery permits, heat pump HVAC conversions, solar panel installations, and EV charger networks. The data returned from these queries can be used for construction go-to-market activities, providing highly targeted leads for sales teams. Developers can also use this data to create applications related to energy transition activities, such as mapping out EV charger locations or predicting future demand for electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about how you can use the Shovels building permit API to access monthly energy transition activity data and build applications related to this area, check out our documentation at &lt;a href="https://docs.shovels.ai/api-reference"&gt;https://docs.shovels.ai/api-reference&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category><category term="climate"></category></entry><entry><title>EV charger permit processing times in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-08-10:/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We conducted an in-depth study on electric vehicle (EV) charger permit approval times in California. Our analysis reveals significant variations in approval times across different jurisdictions in the state. While some jurisdictions in Northern California have remarkably fast approval times, many Southern California jurisdictions experience delays of up to two months. Streamlining the permitting process could be a key factor in improving EV charger installation rates. Interestingly, we found no correlation between the volume of permits processed and approval times, suggesting that bureaucratic overload is not the primary cause of delays. This research provides valuable insights for policymakers, businesses, and homeowners looking to navigate the complex landscape of EV charger installations and contribute to the transition to cleaner, more sustainable transportation options.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Background on EV charging in California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with our thinking about EV chargers, which you can &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;read more about here&lt;/a&gt;, we're turning our attention now to how long it takes for jurisdictions to approve EV charger permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let's take a step back. This analysis is important because California has committed to deploying five million zero-emission vehicles (ZEVs) and building out 250,000 charging stations by 2025. This includes building a network of nearly 20,000 Level 2 and DC fast EV charging stations across the state. Additionally, the state plans to invest $2.5 billion over the next five years to expand the EV charging infrastructure and provide incentives for drivers to purchase electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having more residential EV chargers would make it easier for California residents to own and use electric vehicles. This would also relieve the burden on public EV chargers. The more EV chargers we have in homes, the less strain on the public chargers required for people who live in multifamily housing and don't have a dedicated charger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More residential EV chargers also creates more jobs and boost the economy. Installation and maintenance of these chargers increases demand for electricians, supporting many local businesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Potential for building permit reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to get more EV chargers installed is to streamline the permitting process. EV chargers, because they are high-voltage, require a licensed electrician and a building permit to begin the installation, and an inspector must approve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this process can be cumbersome, building permits exist to ensure that construction projects adhere to local safety and building codes. This is important for protecting the public and ensuring that buildings are safe and structurally sound. Building permits also provide a way for local governments to track construction projects and collect fees to help fund public services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people advocate permitting reform because the current permitting process is overly burdensome, time consuming, and costly, leading to delays and inefficiencies. Permitting reform may reduce the time and cost of obtaining permits, and make it easier for businesses and homeowners to quickly obtain the necessary approvals to install appliances like EV chargers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, with that background, let's look at the data in California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shovels analysis of EV charger permit approval times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels collects and analyzes building permit data. Two data points that we consistently see are the file date, or when the permit was submitted to the jurisdiction, and the issue date, or when the jurisdiction approved the permit. At this point, work can begin, and we'll eventually see the final date, or when the work was completed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file date and the issue date show how long it takes for a jurisdiction to process a permit. As anyone who has had work done knows, this can be an agonizing process. The longer the delay, the more likely your contractor will get busy or supply costs will increase. Homeowners and contractors both want faster permit approval times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, we set out to ask a few questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Differences between jurisdictions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jurisdiction comparison: Which jurisdictions have the fastest and slowest average EV permit approval times? How do they compare to each other?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there differences in permit approval times between Northern and Southern California?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the jurisdictions with the SLOWEST EV median charger permit approval times. We go with the median because there are outliers in the data that will skew the mean. You can see this in the table below, which shows that the mean is greater than the median in each case. The standard deviation and IQR (interquartile range) also demonstrate the skew. Therefore, the median is our best way to compare jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's interesting that four of the five slowest permitting jurisdictions are in Southern California. The median approval times are at least two months. That's too long! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;402.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;152.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;93.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;227.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Francisco&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;194.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;460.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;203.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;192.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Ana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;117.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;103.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Santa Monica&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;235.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;96.28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;121.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pasadena&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;111.54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;125.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Worst EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/top5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking now at the FASTEST EV charger timing jurisdictions, we see median times of less than a week. Interstingly, all but one of the jurisdictions is in Northern California. Even the averages here are reasonable, coming in at less than a month in the top four, but jumping to nearly three months average in San Diego. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Jurisdiction&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Standard Deviation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Q3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;IQR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oakland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;817.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40.06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dublin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;94.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;108.14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;El Dorado County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;266.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sacramento&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;846.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Diego County&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;151.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;119.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;118.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Best EV charger permit times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/bottom5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, we see the apparent impact of outliers. San Diego has a media approval time of five days, but an average of three months. A few crazy long wait times down there are pulling the average away from the median.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Histogram of San Diego EV charger permit approval times" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/sd-histogram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because it was interesting, to further investigate this distinction between Northern California and Southern California, we made one more chart. It tells the story that emerged just by looking at the top 5 and bottom 5 jurisdictions: Northern California issues EV charger permits faster than Southern California. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Northern CA vs Southern CA" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/norcal-v-socal.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatness of the bottom of the candlestick shows the bottom and top quartile wait times. A smaller candle is better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Trends over time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How has the average EV permit approval time changed over the years for each jurisdiction? Are there any jurisdictions where the approval time is consistently getting faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are there certain times of the year when EV permit approval times are generally faster or slower? This could indicate seasonal workload fluctuations in permit offices.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, we looked for jurisdictions where permit approval times are getting worse and others where they are getting better. Bucking the NorCal/SoCal trend described above, we found that permit times are getting better in Riverside County and worse in Milpitas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-county.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Milpitas approval times by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/milpitas.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The permit counts by year for each county might give some clues as to what's going on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Riverside County and Milpitas EV charger permit counts by year" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/riverside-milpitas-count.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the looks of these three charts, we find that the number of EV charger permits in Riverside County skyrocketed during the pandemic, and the jurisdiction must have put some permit streamlining reforms in place because despite the higher volume, they kept the processing times down. This combination led to a precipitous drop in permit approval times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the COVID question was interesting, so we looked across the board and came up with this chart. The processing times actually improved after COVID. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Impact of COVID on permit approval times in California" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/covid.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The relationship between permit volume and approval times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there a correlation between the number of permits a jurisdiction processes and the speed of approval? In other words, do jurisdictions that process more EV permits tend to approve them faster or slower?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This result surprised us. We assume that bureaucratic government departments are easily overwhelmed. As the number of permit applications increases, we expect that approval times would get slower. In fact, there's no relationship between the volume of permits and the processing times across the jurisdictions in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scatter of approval times and volumes" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/approval-times-scatter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pearson correlation coefficient here is −0.0730. This value indicates a very weak negative relationship. In other words, there's actually a slight tendency for jurisdictions that process more EV permits to approve them a bit faster, but the relationship is weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phew! That was a lot of information about EV charger approval times. It seems we're still just scratching the surface. If you want to do more analysis, &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;. We have lots of data. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category><category term="permit timeline"></category><category term="climate"></category></entry><entry><title>The growth of EV contractors in California</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/the-growth-of-ev-contractors-in-california/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-01:/blog/the-growth-of-ev-contractors-in-california/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this final article of our series on EV charger activity in California, we explore the growth of EV charger contractors. We highlight the flourishing EV charger space and provide examples of companies operating in different parts of the ecosystem. Additionally, we showcase the jurisdictions with the most active EV charger contractors and analyze the increasing trend of new contractor activity. The data underscores the growing demand for EV chargers and the expanding market for contractors in this exciting industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Growth in EV charger contractors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This the final article of our recent series on EV charger activity in California. You can also read about the &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/growth-of-ev-charging-in-california/"&gt;growth of EV chargers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/ev-charger-permit-processing-times-in-california/"&gt;EV charger permit approval timelines&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen the EV charger space flourish, with companies operating in many different parts of the ecosystem. Check out a few examples::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger hardware companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evocharge.com/"&gt;EvoCharge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evercharge.com/"&gt;EverCharge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://evbox.com/en/"&gt;EVBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chargepoint.com/"&gt;ChargePoint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger software companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chargelab.co/"&gt;ChargeLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://driivz.com/"&gt;Driivz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.noodoe.com/"&gt;NooDoe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ampup.io/"&gt;AmpUp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV charger services companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kopperfield.com/"&gt;Kopperfield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://treehouse.pro/"&gt;Treehouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://elephantenergy.com/"&gt;Elephant Energy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quitcarbon.com/"&gt;QuitCarbon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And charge point operators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.evgo.com/"&gt;EVGo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.electrifyamerica.com/"&gt;Electrify America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tesla.com/commercial-charging"&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also sales and design tools like &lt;a href="https://www.monterra.ai/"&gt;Monterra&lt;/a&gt;, purpose-built to help installers (electrical contractors and EV charging project developers) design, quote, and propose projects faster - streamlining and automating an otherwise manual site design and sales process. It’s a busy space! That’s why we’re spending so much time looking into it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already showed that there’s been a boon in EV charger installs. With all of this activity, it seems that there should be an increase in contractor activity, too. That’s what we set out to prove, and the data says it loud and clear: the number of contractors doing EV charger installations is increasing throughout California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put things into context, nearly 30% of all EV chargers in the US are installed in California today, followed by NY, FL, TX, MA, and WA (making up 25% collectively). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Stay tuned, as we’ll soon dive into the data for FL and TX market in a future post!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the jurisdictions with the most active EV charger contractors since 2022:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sacramento County&lt;/strong&gt;: 429 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berkeley&lt;/strong&gt;: 209 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encinitas&lt;/strong&gt;: 203 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oakland&lt;/strong&gt;: 140 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anaheim&lt;/strong&gt;: 119 contractors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took the top two jurisdictions and looked to see if the number of active EV charger contractors has been increasing over time. Indeed it has! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-sacramento.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-sacramento.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-berkeley.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-berkeley.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend line shows that in Sacramento, another EV charger contractor has become active every quarter. In Berkeley, it’s another 1.5 contractors active each quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berkeley and Sacramento have the most active contractors. In jurisdictions with fewer contractors, is the rate of new activity higher? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ev-contractors-grid.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/ev-contractors-grid.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower the base, the higher the slope, with dramatic recent increases in contractor activity in Anaheim, Sacramento, and Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Sacramento (City) and Sacramento County are different permitting jurisdictions, so there’s no overlap here in the charts.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that there should be an increase in &lt;strong&gt;new&lt;/strong&gt; EV charger contractors intrigued us, so we did that analysis, too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="new-ev-contractors.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/new-ev-contractors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart shows the number of new contractors entering each of the jurisdictions each year. A new contractor is one that had no permit history in the years prior. You can see an acceleration happening between 2010 and 2022 as these jurisdictions add more &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; EV charger contractors each year. Anaheim is the outlier. They started high and stayed high. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The EV charger market is growing at an increasing rate.&lt;/strong&gt; Supply of contractors (as well as hardware, software, and services) is responding to an increase in demand, and we can track this response using Shovels building permit data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we figured that another sign of market growth could be EV contractors expanding their own territories. We decided to look at the percentage of EV contractors doing work in multiple jurisdictions each quarter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="multiple-jurisdictions-ev-contractors.png" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/multiple-jurisdictions-ev-contractors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This geographical expansion is also trending up, with a big surge during COVID that sustained after the pandemic retreated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool stuff, right? This means EV charging is hot. Dare we say &lt;em&gt;electric&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a good market to work and invest in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re excited by all of this data, and we want you to be excited too. Want to do your own epic analysis of the building trades? Get in touch: sales@shovels.ai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daviddkkim/"&gt;David Kim&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.monterra.ai"&gt;Monterra&lt;/a&gt; for contributing to this article!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building contractors"></category><category term="ev chargers"></category><category term="climate"></category></entry><entry><title>Do rebate programs matter to contractors in the SF Bay Area?</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/do-rebate-programs-matter-to-contractors-in-the-sf-bay-area/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-19:/blog/do-rebate-programs-matter-to-contractors-in-the-sf-bay-area/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We look at the impact of BayREN's initiatives on the Bay Area's energy upgrade trends, revealing a significant increase in heat pump installations by BayREN-affiliated contractors compared to a lesser focus on solar panel installations. It suggests that BayREN is strategically filling gaps in the building electrification market.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A key player in the building electrification transformation in the San Francisco Bay Area is the &lt;a href="https://www.bayren.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Bay Area Regional Energy Network&lt;/a&gt; (BayREN). Over the past decade it has become synonymous with fostering environmentally conscious decisions among communities and building contractors alike. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our recent research into building permits has revealed compelling trends that not only underscore BayREN's influence but also signal a shift in the region's approach to energy efficiency. By analyzing building permits, we discovered a stark difference in the uptake of various energy upgrades between contractors affiliated with BayREN and those who are not. This isn't just numerical variance; it's a narrative about where we're heading and what fuels our journey towards a greener Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bayren vs other contractors" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/contractors_comparison_chart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data paints a telling picture: BayREN contractors are installing significantly more heat pumps than their non-affiliated counterparts. Why heat pumps? Heat pumps are a linchpin in the arsenal against energy inefficiency. They serve dual purposes, providing heating and cooling in a single system, and they're remarkably efficient, actually cutting down total energy use compared to traditional HVAC systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This finding aligns perfectly with BayREN's strategic priorities. By streamlining the installation of heat pumps, BayREN is not just pushing for a reduction in greenhouse gas emissions; it's also promoting a technology that can adapt to and leverage the Bay Area's mild climate, proving to be both a cost-effective and environmentally friendly solution for local homeowners and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the same research indicated that BayREN contractors install fewer solar panels than their peers. This could seem counterintuitive at first glance, given the solar industry's growth and the region's ample sunshine. However, this trend could be attributed to several factors. Perhaps the solar market in the Bay Area is already well-developed, necessitating less intervention. Alternatively, it could be that BayREN's current initiatives are designed to fill gaps in the building electrification market where other technologies, such as heat pumps, have yet to mature. It's also possible that the existing financial incentives for solar installations are already optimized, so BayREN focuses its resources on other technologies in need of a push.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to electric vehicle (EV) charger installations, the numbers align closely between BayREN contractors and others. EV technology is an area of robust growth, supported by statewide initiatives and private investments alike. The parallel trends here suggest that the push for EV infrastructure might be equally strong across the board, indicating that BayREN's efforts in this domain are complementing an already thriving market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do these trends mean for the Bay Area's energy landscape? They showcase BayREN's role in helping the region's energy efficiency trajectory. By fostering the adoption of heat pumps, BayREN is helping to redefine the standard for residential and commercial heating and cooling systems. This not only contributes to lowering carbon footprints but also aligns with broader goals of resilience and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data also prompts a re-evaluation of solar energy's place in the Bay Area's proptech scene. With the solar panel market potentially approaching saturation, it may be time to innovate further or redirect focus to complementing technologies that enhance solar efficiency or storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings illuminate the nuanced dynamics of energy upgrades in the Bay Area. As BayREN continues to lead with forward-thinking programs, it remains crucial for us to monitor how these initiatives shape both the demand and the labor market to install these systems. The shifts we see today, influenced by BayREN's strategic decisions, are creating a blueprint for other regions to follow. And as we continue to gather data and analyze trends, we look forward to contributing the conversation around proptech and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="bayren"></category><category term="rebates"></category><category term="climate"></category></entry><entry><title>The list of every building permit jurisdiction in the US</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/list-of-all-building-permit-jurisdictions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-04-06:/blog/list-of-all-building-permit-jurisdictions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels is open-sourcing of a comprehensive list of building permit jurisdictions that we discovered only recently. Our new database includes over ten thousand building permit jurisdictions and associates each jurisdiction with a county and state.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/building-permit-jurisdictions-in-the-united-states" target="_blank"&gt;another Kaggle dataset&lt;/a&gt; from the Shovels vault. Our &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdiction_mappings.csv"&gt;latest file&lt;/a&gt; is a comprehensive mapping of state, county, and building permit jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is this list of building permit jurisdictions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file includes over 10,000 building permit jurisdictions (AHJs -- authority-having jurisdictions), and relates each jurisdiction to its respective state and county. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found this mapping buried in an &lt;a href="https://socds.huduser.gov/permits/" target="_blank"&gt;obscure government website&lt;/a&gt;. We noticed that when we clicked on a state, a select box appeared with all of the counties in that state. This mapping is widely available from the US Census and many other open data sources. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when we clicked on the county, another select box appeared with every building permit jurisdiction in the county. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; got our attention. Before this discovery, we didn't know of a single source of truth for how many AHJs are out there for building permits. Now we can count at least 10,000 of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who needs a list of every building permit jurisdiction?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When architects, developers, and homeowners start a new project, the first question they might ask is, "Where do I file my building permits?" The answer is far from obvious! Many cities don't have building departments; they delegate building permitting to the county.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list we are open-sourcing today includes every building permit jurisdiction. If a city or town is on this list, then they issue their own building permits. If a city or town is not on this list, then it's safe to conclude that their AHJ is the county. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We figure many folks who work in cities and counties don't know every AHJ within their boundaries. Now they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How many building permit jurisdictions are in each state?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got curious and decided to ask this data a few questions. How many AHJs are in each state? Does that jurisdiction count correlate with population? We had to merge in some public census data to figure this out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average, there are about ten permit jurisdictions per county. If a county has a million residents, that means each permit jurisdiction serves about 100,000 people. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pennsylvania stands out with the highest number of permit jurisdictions, totaling 1575. No other state comes close! It's unclear why Pennsylvania needs so many of them. For example, although Pennsylvania has the same population as Ohio, it has almost 3X the number of building permit jurisdictions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart makes the outliers easy to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Population vs Jurisdiction Count" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdictions-vs-population.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's a table of every state, its population, number of jurisdictions, and the ratio of jurisdictions per 100,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="left"&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Population&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Permit Jurisdictions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Jurisdictions per 100,000 Residents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Alaska&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;733406&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.954451&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5108468&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.91507&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Arkansas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3067732&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.58571&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Arizona&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7431344&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.0227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;38965193&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;471&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.20877&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Colorado&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5877610&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;113&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.92255&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Connecticut&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3617176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;137&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.78749&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;District of Columbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;678972&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.147281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Delaware&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1031890&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.93819&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Florida&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;22610726&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;389&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.72042&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11029227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;307&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.78351&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Hawaii&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1435138&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.139359&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Iowa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3207004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;235&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7.32771&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Idaho&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1964726&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.81733&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Illinois&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12549689&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;696&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.54595&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Indiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6862199&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.30798&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Kansas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2940546&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.84925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Kentucky&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4526154&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;135&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.98266&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Louisiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4573749&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;164&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.58568&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7001399&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;317&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.52767&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Maryland&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6180253&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.19736&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Maine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1395722&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;131&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9.38582&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Michigan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;10037261&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;659&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.56554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Minnesota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5737915&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;474&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.26084&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6196156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;340&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.48727&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2939690&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.55129&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Montana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1132812&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.85379&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;North Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;10835491&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;226&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.08574&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;North Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;783926&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9.18454&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Nebraska&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1978379&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.80191&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1402054&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.77724&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Jersey&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9290841&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;572&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.1566&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New Mexico&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2114371&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.945908&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Nevada&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3194176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.344377&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;New York&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;19571216&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;906&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.62925&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ohio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11785935&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;586&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.97203&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Oklahoma&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4053824&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.18218&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4233358&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;130&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.07085&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12961683&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1575&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12.1512&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Rhode Island&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1095962&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.55852&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;South Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5373555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;152&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.82867&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;South Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;919318&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.30902&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Tennessee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7126489&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.72224&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Texas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;30503301&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;651&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.1342&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Utah&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3417734&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;141&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.12554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8715698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.31946&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Vermont&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;647464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.17795&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Washington&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7812880&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;201&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.57267&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5910955&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;530&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.9664&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;West Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1770071&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6.49691&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Wyoming&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;584057&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.05459&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mission is to make government data meaningful and actionable. Our tools and datasets, like the one we're open-sourcing today, are designed to make government data useful. It's a step in the right direction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the links again: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grab it &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/rbucks/building-permit-jurisdictions-in-the-united-states" target="_blank"&gt;on Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/images/jurisdiction_mappings.csv"&gt;download the CSV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="AHJ"></category><category term="permit jurisdiction"></category></entry><entry><title>US Solar Construction Trends (2024)</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/us-solar-construction-trends-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Alex Brown</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-09-11:/blog/us-solar-construction-trends-2024/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Shovels dataset and model can highlight key construction trends and patterns. In this blog, we discuss solar construction specifically due to the RE+ clean energy convention. Use Shovels to inform your construction company's business models and strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.re-plus.com/"&gt;RE+&lt;/a&gt; is the largest and most comprehensive clean energy conference in the United States. In honor of it’s 20th Anniversary, we’re publishing some insights we’ve gleaned from our datasets and models here at Shovels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, if you’re reading at the time of publication, we’re at RE+ in Anaheim right now! Come find us on the floor, or reach out directly to coordinate — we want to meet you!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar tech, and clean energy tech generally, is something we’re really passionate about. We’ve recently &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-partners-with-wattcarbon/"&gt;partnered with WattCarbon&lt;/a&gt; to support their decarbonization efforts via their new Energy Attribute Certificate (EAC) Marketplace, and also worked with &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/case-study-empowering-carbon-free-homes/"&gt;Carbon Free Homes&lt;/a&gt; to improve their climate-friendly contractor matching platform. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, we’re shining a light on solar construction trends thus far in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Shovels Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone new here (welcome!), we’ll give a quick refresher on what we do. Shovels is a building insights company, and we aggregate, normalize, and make construction data useful. It started at building permits, but we’re expanding into more robust models by incorporating contractor profiles, tax assessor files, and other publicly accessible data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, we can query, filter, and summarize the data any which way you like: by market, geo-region, or address; by permit type or fields, by contractors, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For today’s analysis, we’re going to be querying our model based on two key filters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Permits filed this year; or &lt;code&gt;file_date = 2024%&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar-inclusive projects (anything that includes solar technology); or &lt;code&gt;solar = true&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Fields like these, along with other variables used in our model, can be reviewed in our &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qiIxx37_-6vGfGp2i5pXv4w2FdsLsShjCqSVO5v6OMQ/edit?gid=1818227349#gid=1818227349"&gt;Data Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can dig deeper than those to get into specifics of things like &lt;strong&gt;Contractor Availability&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Average Approval Time&lt;/strong&gt; later on, but for now these two filters will serve as the foundation of this dataset. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are solar projects all over the country, it’s clear that the vast majority of activity is here in California, so let’s take a closer look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spotlight on California&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California has led the nation in solar adoption and technology for decades now, and part of that adoption is the widespread governmental support in the forms of &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/home-improvement/solar/california-solar-incentives/"&gt;incentives, tax credits, and rebates&lt;/a&gt;. So it makes sense that The Golden State continues to outpace everyone else in the push towards net-zero emissions and clean energy production. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filtering the dataset above once again — by &lt;code&gt;state = CA&lt;/code&gt; — and sorting by geo-coordinates &lt;code&gt;lat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;long&lt;/code&gt;, we can see a heat map of this year’s construction volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Map of California with heatmap showing volume of solar project permits, by geographical coordinates." src="/images/digging-in-ca-solar-construction-heatmap-watermarked.png"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hubs like Los Angeles, San Diego, San Jose, and others in the Central Valley show the most activity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tax incentives aren’t the entire picture. The state-wide building permit pipeline is a well-oiled machine. Experienced contractors and administrative support makes filing your permit easy, which results in an astounding 6.15 day average approval time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sidenote: to be fair to the other states, some are performaing just as well if not better than California (eg, NY with an average of 2.8 days), yet none come even close to the permit volume. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More impressively, the hotspots above have even better approval times, with San Diego County leading the way with a blistering 1.79 day average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reminder, this is across all projects which include solar installation of any kind, so small panels on your personal home are counted in line with massive commercial construction that cover their roofs with solar arrays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your local jurisdiction wants to up their pace and adoption rates for solar- or other green-energy technologies, California is a good place to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights, In Season&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metrics like &lt;strong&gt;Permit Volume&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Average Approval Time&lt;/strong&gt; can be nice pats-on-the-back, but the real power of the Shovels model is trend and market gap analysis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the model we’ve refined already, let’s tweak it slightly to get a historical view of the past 4 years. If we adjust the original filter to &lt;code&gt;file_date = 202%&lt;/code&gt; (to cover everything built since January 2020), we can see the construction trends and seasonalities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is one such query, visualized and sorted by &lt;code&gt;month&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Area line graph showing California permit volume for solar projects since January 2020, by month." src="/images/digging-in-ca-solar-construction-trend-2020s-watermarked.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are seasonal spikes before and after Summer, with the biggest peak to date in March 2023 with a staggering 33k+ solar-inclusive project permits filed that month alone. This graph illustrates the duality of man, or at least those who installed their solar panels in advance versus those who regret not getting them up earlier that Spring. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trendline here shows that things are slowing down, but only in comparison to the previous years’ highs. Using other construction data to determine solar saturation and wider construction trends in your specific market, Shovels could provide actionable insights into timing and lead-gen opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe other green technologies like &lt;a href="https://techcleanca.com/"&gt;heat pumps&lt;/a&gt; are relatively underrated, and ripe for a strong market push?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free Shovels Advice&lt;/strong&gt;: if you’re a solar supplier or in a solar-adjacent market, now would be &lt;strong&gt;a very good time&lt;/strong&gt; to confirm those outbound pipelines are fired up to prepare for the early Fall installation push. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels has in-depth contractor profiles and data that you could use for that very purpose — &lt;a href="mailto:sales@shovels.ai"&gt;reach out today&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derivative metrics that can inform projections and trends are the name of the game, and a core tenet of the Shovels model and datasets. While solar construction is close-to-heart, we cover all range of project types — if it requires a building permit (and the jurisdiction digitizes their records), then we’ll have it for consumption. If we don't, let us know and we'll get it for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Get Your Own Shovel Today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permit data is the foundation of the Shovels platform, and wrangling it at scale can provide actionable business insights, legislative or administrative effectiveness reports, or anything in between. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that kind of scale is what you’re looking for, then our &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/data-feed"&gt;Enterprise&lt;/a&gt; product will be the best fit. We’ll send you the files and raw data for consumption into, or in tandem with, existing models. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we have a &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/api"&gt;robust API&lt;/a&gt; for direct integration of our data to your own platform(s). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out our &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai"&gt;Free Trial&lt;/a&gt; today to see how our platform works, or get in contact with us for a demo and sample dataset of your preferred market at &lt;a href="mailto:sales@shovels.ai"&gt;sales@shovels.ai&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Digging, and let us know how you enjoyed RE+ in Anaheim this year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="RE Plus"></category><category term="Solar"></category><category term="Insights"></category></entry><entry><title>Analyzing Texas Roofing Permits by Income Bracket</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/analyzing-texas-roofing-permits-by-income-bracket/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Alex Brown</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2025-01-23:/blog/analyzing-texas-roofing-permits-by-income-bracket/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shovels data allows for in-depth analysis of construction trends at any level. Texas roofing permit patterns show higher income areas pull more roofing permits than expected for their household count. This has implications for all homeowners, and should be addressed by policy makers, the market, or both.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Roofs are one of the most important factors in determining (and growing) home value, even if they aren’t as flashy as other remodeling projects. New kitchens or bathrooms can elevate an existing home’s &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;a href="https://www.revive.realestate/post/how-much-does-a-new-roof-add-to-home-value-2024-guide" target="_blank"&gt;roofs increase value across the board&lt;/a&gt;: structural integrity, energy efficiency, and longevity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different neighborhoods and homeowner socio-economics can lead to a wide range of behaviors around maintaining their roofs. Richer areas may see more frequent re-roofing, whereas middle-income areas may prioritize maintenance. And low-income neighborhoods may not have the luxury of such an expensive project. This is commonly understood at an intuitive level, but isn’t the entire picture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shovels provides data about individual property permit history, including roofing and re-roofing, which gives us an opportunity to dig deeper into the relationship between household income and roofing permit activity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We looked at more than 3,200 census tracts across Texas and combined that with roofing permits and owner demographics to see how the real world matches up against general understanding. Let’s see what the data says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, there are some obvious findings, which are supported by both conventional wisdom and academic studies, like &lt;a href="https://www.jchs.harvard.edu/blog/home-repairs-and-updates-pose-considerable-burdens-lower-income-homeowners"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; from the Harvard University Joint Center for Housing Studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the board, we find that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Higher income areas show increased permit activity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data shows clear progressions in roof permit activity as income increases, with a striking jump in areas (census tracts) with a median annual income of $100k or greater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Roofing permit activity in Texas, by income bracket, averaged per household" src="/images/shovels-roofing-permit-density.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Income (&amp;lt;$30k/year): 0.21 RPD, or &lt;em&gt;Roofing Permit Density&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low-Middle Income ($50k-$75k/year): 0.23 RPD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middle Income ($75k-$100k/year): 0.29 RPD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upper-Middle Income ($100k-$150k/year): 0.48 RPD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Income (&amp;gt;$150k/year): 0.51 RPD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;74% of Roofing Permits Come from the Richest 28% of Areas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data is not a surprise, but shows a stark difference in the proportion of roof permits pulled versus the number of households.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Modeled proportions of Texas households, by income bracket" src="/images/shovels-analysis-modeled-households.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some additional stats we found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;72% of areas in Texas fall beneath the Upper-Middle bracket, as described above. That’s roughly 3.5 million households.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A massive 58% of areas in Texas make up the Low-Middle bracket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only 4% of areas make up the High Income bracket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher Income areas (Upper-Middle and High brackets) show the widest variation in permit activity, beyond just roofing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding the Wealth-Permit Correlation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings align with broader research and understandings behind homeowner improvement behaviors, and why large-scale projects like roofs are more frequently done by higher income areas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several key factors contribute to this trend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access to financial resources&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roofing projects represent a smaller proportion of wealthier homeowner’s budget, both generally and for home improvement projects. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better access to project financing, such as mortgage refinancing, home equity loans, or personal loans with favorable terms. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better access to navigate loans and government-backed programs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Property characteristics and maintenance approaches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wealthier areas often feature older homes requiring more regular or controlled maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wealthier homeowners frequently leverage their greater resources to:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get regular roof inspections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Address minor issues promptly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invest in higher-quality and longer-lasting roofing materials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take preventative measures before major problems develop. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Houses-As-Investment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wealthier homeowners view home improvements as strategic investments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wealthier homeowners have better options for temporary housing while major work is done on a given property. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this boils down to what we all intrinsically know: &lt;strong&gt;it’s expensive to be poor, and paying more upfront (in outsourcing labor, better quality materials, and frequent maintenance) is cheaper in the long run. And it’s easier for the wealthy to pay upfront.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integral nature of roofs to both home quality and value, contrasted with the permitting statistics across areas of different socio-economic backgrounds, paints a stark picture. It’s easier for wealthier areas to do roof work, and so they do. Upper-Middle and High Income areas (by median income) make up the majority of statewide permitting, even though they’re the minority of households.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data on its own is nice, but ultimately the value comes from leveraging this data to improve things around us. Shovels is in the business of providing construction insights, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive into some segments that can work with this data to improve home value across the board. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Policy Makers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing equality is a long-standing issue nationwide, but it’s &lt;a href="https://comptroller.texas.gov/economy/fiscal-notes/economics/2024/aff-housing/" target="_blank"&gt;especially present in Texas&lt;/a&gt;. If over a third of homeowners can barely afford their home, how are they expected to front the expenses for a large project like a new roof?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policy makers should investigate longitudinal affordability programs to not only ensure that lower income households can afford housing, but that they can also get the assistance to maintain their home throughout it’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, they should also create cross-industry partnerships to include banks and lending institutions with non-profits and related businesses to help homeowners take care of their roofs, and by extension their homes and investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s cheaper (and greener!) to maintain an existing home than to build and buy a new one, so let’s make that dream a reality for everyone, not just the wealthiest areas. And when the funds are available, the contractors will be happy for the work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Contractors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the invention of the gang-nail plate (sometimes called a truss connector these days) &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3oIeLGkSCMA" target="_blank"&gt;revolutionized the American construction world back in the 50s&lt;/a&gt;, home contractors have switched from building what the homeowners wanted to building what they could, and then selling them the dream of bigger and bigger houses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, as some might put it, Americans gained an appetite for larger and more complex homes, and their incomes didn’t match their dreams. In any case, houses are more expensive and bigger than ever. Combined with rising inflation and stagnating salaries, this is a disaster for the lower and middle classes, and has been for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roofs are just one part of the puzzle. Understanding this roofing problem, and the fact that such a large portion of the available market for roofing projects is in the Lower-Middle income bracket or lower, may unlock substantially more opportunities. Sure there are massive projects funded by the ultra-wealthy that can yield a big paycheck, but sustained work is better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Homeowners&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, homeowners are the ones that benefit the most from increasing the value of their house. In this case, through ensuring that their roof is in excellent condition. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With better information and resources, every homeowner can understand how to best take care of their roof, whether that’s from regular inspections and maintenance plans, or seeking out financing options to measurably improve their home’s value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And ultimately, roof permitting measured against census tracts and income levels is a great litmus test for how well homeowners are faring, both within their communities and nationwide. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between household income and roof permit activity is one facet of a broader reflection on how socioeconomic patterns influence home ownership and property investment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our findings for more than 3,200 census tracts within Texas, wealthier areas showed dramatically disproportionate roof permitting activity compared to less wealthy areas. Beyond the continued alignment with such broader studies, this specifically demonstrates an unbalanced market where Low to Middle Income areas need more assistance with their roofs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these disparities and inequalities, a nuanced approach is necessary. This is what we might do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement policy measures to support necessary roofing repairs in lower-income areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop and educate contractors regarding government-backed programs to help such lower-income areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide more accessible financing options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate with businesses, non-profits, and communities to improve access to home improvement resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drive community education and awareness towards the benefits of maintaining their roofs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more roofing permits we see, the better the home quality and value is, which is &lt;a href="https://insights.som.yale.edu/insights/swings-in-building-permits-can-help-predict-financial-downturns" target="_blank"&gt;a good thing for everyone&lt;/a&gt; from policy makers to contractors to homeowners. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What Next?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This narrow study provided some very interesting results, but we can think of additional research we’d like to do. Some key ideas for future analyses are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deeper dive into how this data affects different industries, like insurance, banking, and real estate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat these analyses for additional states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure real, assessed, or modeled home values against permit activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure contractor-submitted permits versus those done by the homeowner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delineate owner-occupied versus tenant-occupied homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track historical permit data to determine roof lifespans and associated permitted maintenance or re-roofing work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expand our scope beyond roofing to other key signals of home improvement value, like remodels, extensions, or exterior work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there’s anything specific that you’d like to see us cover next, please &lt;a href="mailto:support@shovels.ai"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;! On the other hand, check out our &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai" target="_blank"&gt;Free Trial&lt;/a&gt; and either use &lt;strong&gt;Shovels Online&lt;/strong&gt; or the &lt;strong&gt;Shovels API&lt;/strong&gt; to pull some of this data for yourself. We certainly don’t have time to do it all, and we love to collaborate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Digging!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="texas"></category><category term="roofing permits"></category><category term="analysis"></category></entry><entry><title>Unlocking Urban Electrification in San Diego</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/solar-permit-density-san-diego/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2025-04-09:/blog/solar-permit-density-san-diego/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A deep dive into solar adoption patterns in San Diego County reveals surprising insights about what drives building electrification. Through analysis of census tract data, we discover that two cities - Poway and Chula Vista - lead in solar adoption despite their contrasting demographics and housing characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's hard to understand precisely why homeowners choose to invest in their homes at certain times. By looking at specific installations at the census tract level, we can begin to develop this understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we look specifically at solar adoption in San Diego, California. The understanding of what drives building electrification at the neighborhood level has become essential for policymakers, urban planners, and sustainability advocates. At Shovels, we've been analyzing permit data across the United States to uncover these types of patterns in construction activity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One question has particularly intrigued us: &lt;strong&gt;Why do some communities adopt building electrification faster than others?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our recent analysis of the San Diego-Chula Vista-Carlsbad metropolitan area has revealed some surprising insights about solar adoption patterns that challenge conventional assumptions about urban electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What factors drive electrification adoption? The usual suspects include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax incentives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Keeping up with the Joneses" social influence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Housing stock age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resident wealth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar company marketing efforts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But which of these factors actually matter most? And how can we measure their impact?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our Analytical Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than starting with hypotheses about what might drive adoption, we took a data-first approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on a diverse region&lt;/strong&gt;: We selected the San Diego-Chula Vista-Carlsbad, CA metropolitan area because California has excellent electrification data and this region offers demographic diversity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Census tract analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: We analyzed at the census tract level (smaller than ZIP codes or cities) to capture neighborhood patterns and connect to public datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Electrification (BE) density metric&lt;/strong&gt;: We developed a metric to measure the cumulative adoption of electrification technologies over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Poway and Chula Vista" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/BE_all.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why a Composite Electrification Metric Matters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying building electrification through a single technology (like just solar panels) gives an incomplete picture. True urban sustainability comes from the combined adoption of multiple complementary technologies. Our building electrification (BE) density metric captures this holistic transformation by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accounting for the synergistic relationship between different electrification technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recognizing communities making progress across multiple dimensions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying neighborhoods that might serve as models for comprehensive electrification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helping policymakers understand which areas have balanced adoption versus those with lopsided patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How We Calculate Building Electrification (BE) Density&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shovels BE density score consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Base score (0-100)&lt;/strong&gt;: The average of percentile rankings for solar, heat pump, and EV charger adoption rates across census tracts. This creates a balanced foundation that values all three technologies equally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology leadership bonus&lt;/strong&gt;: +10 points for each technology where the tract ranks in the top 10% (90th percentile) of adoption. This rewards neighborhoods showing exceptional adoption of specific technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive adoption bonus&lt;/strong&gt;: +15 additional points if a tract is in the top 10% for ALL three technologies simultaneously. This significant bonus recognizes truly forward-thinking communities that have embraced electrification holistically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scoring system allows us to identify not just high adoption areas, but specifically those neighborhoods that demonstrate balanced, multi-technology transitions away from fossil fuels—the true leaders in urban electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key Findings: Two Geographic Clusters Stand Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we mapped BE density across the region, we discovered something intriguing: the highest-ranking census tracts were not randomly distributed but clustered primarily in two cities - &lt;strong&gt;Poway&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Poway and Chula Vista" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/pw-and-cv.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background on Poway and Chula Vista&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Poway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poway is a suburban city located in San Diego County, California, often referred to as "The City in the Country" due to its rural feel despite being part of the San Diego metropolitan area. It has a population of approximately 50,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporated in 1980 but most of its housing stock dates to the 1970s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Located inland, about 25 miles northeast of downtown San Diego&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher median household income than the county average ($110,000+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predominantly residential with some light industrial areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Known for excellent school district (Poway Unified School District serves parts of neighboring communities as well)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More spacious lots and properties (typically quarter-acre to acre+ lots)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demographics skew more affluent and less diverse than the county average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contains a mix of older established neighborhoods and newer developments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Poway Solar Density" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/pw.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chula Vista is the second-largest city in the San Diego metropolitan area, with a population of approximately 275,000 residents. Its name means "beautiful view" in Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporated in 1911&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Located just south of San Diego and north of the Mexican border&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has experienced rapid growth since the 1980s and a lot of new construction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Divided geographically between the older western portion (closer to the bay) and newer eastern developments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eastern Chula Vista (where most of the high solar adoption areas are located) consists largely of master-planned communities built since the 1990s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More ethnically diverse than the county average, with a large Hispanic/Latino population (approximately 60%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix of working-class, middle-class, and upper-middle-class neighborhoods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has been proactive in sustainability initiatives, including the Chula Vista Climate Action Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Poway Solar Density" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/cv.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contrast between these two cities makes their similar solar adoption rates particularly interesting - Poway is smaller, more affluent, with older housing stock and more rural character, while Chula Vista is larger, more diverse, with newer housing in its eastern developments and a more suburban/urban character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solar Adoption Growth Patterns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When tracking solar permit density over time, both Poway and Chula Vista show remarkable growth trajectories, but with distinct patterns that reflect their different development timelines and community characteristics. The quarter-by-quarter data reveals not just when adoption began, but how quickly it accelerated and whether growth has been sustained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steep growth curve starting in 2015 in most high-density tracts, coinciding with the city's implementation of its "Solar Ready" ordinance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The highest density tract began growing two years earlier (2013), possibly serving as a catalyst for surrounding neighborhoods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consistent growth of about 4.5 points per year since 2017, showing remarkable stability even through economic fluctuations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All high-adoption tracts show nearly parallel growth trajectories, suggesting coordinated development or similar market forces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar adoption reached 50+ permits per 100 households in top tracts by 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth pattern shows minimal seasonality, indicating year-round installation activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eastern master-planned communities show the highest adoption rates, with newer homes (post-2000) embracing solar technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poway&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally higher solar density compared to Chula Vista throughout the time series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Began adoption 3-5 years earlier than Chula Vista, with meaningful growth beginning around 2010-2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial adoption concentrated in higher-income neighborhoods before spreading throughout the city&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peak early growth of 5.2 points per year (2014-2017), settling to 4.2 points annually in recent years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More varied adoption curves between different census tracts compared to Chula Vista, suggesting less coordinated development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By 2023, top tracts reached 65+ permits per 100 households, approximately 30% higher than Chula Vista's peak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth continued steadily even in older neighborhoods with pre-1980 housing stock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shows evidence of "neighborhood effect" where adoption clusters in adjacent areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest-density tract (607301705) shows distinctly faster growth than others, reaching 65+ permits per 100 households by 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both cities demonstrate strong and sustained solar adoption despite their different demographic profiles, housing stock age, and development patterns, challenging conventional assumptions about which neighborhoods are most likely to embrace renewable energy technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Comparing Housing and Adoption Characteristics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we dove deeper into the housing characteristics and adoption patterns, we discovered some counterintuitive findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Metric&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Poway&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Properties&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8,797 units&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,939 units&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Median Build Year&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1979&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Permit Activity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;83.4%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68.9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Solar Adoption&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55.0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;53.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Heat Pump Adoption&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;EV Charger Adoption&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Combined Electrification&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What stands out immediately is that &lt;strong&gt;Poway has nearly identical solar adoption rates to Chula Vista despite having much older homes&lt;/strong&gt;. This contradicts the conventional wisdom that newer homes are more suitable for solar installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at housing stock more closely reveals that Poway has a more diverse and older housing stock, yet manages to achieve comparable solar adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Permitting Factor: Comparing with San Diego&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this data comparison between Poway, San Diego, and Chula Vista, several key insights emerge about how residential solar permitting varies significantly across these neighboring jurisdictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Metric&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Poway&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;San Diego&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Total Residential Solar Permits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8,393&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;110,618&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21,725&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Median Job Value (Residential)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$18,407&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$23,540&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$15,300&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Average Job Value (Residential)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$26,518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$173,015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$19,231&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Median Approval Duration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;84 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Average Approval Duration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;38 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;136 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Median Permit Fees&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$299&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$457&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Average Permit Fees&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No Data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$359&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$587&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scale and Volume Differences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;San Diego processes by far the largest number of residential solar permits (110,618), which is approximately 5 times more than Chula Vista (21,725) and 13 times more than Poway (8,393). This massive difference in volume likely influences their respective processes and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Permit Value Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most striking anomaly is San Diego's average job value ($173,015), which is roughly 6.5 times higher than Poway's ($26,518) and 9 times higher than Chula Vista's ($19,231). However, the median values are much closer ($23,540 for San Diego vs. $18,407 for Poway and $15,300 for Chula Vista). This suggests San Diego has some extremely high-value residential solar projects skewing its average upward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Processing Efficiency Contrasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval duration data reveals dramatic differences in permitting efficiency:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chula Vista: Remarkably fast with 0 days median approval time (suggesting same-day approvals) and a 12-day average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poway: Moderate processing time with 27 days median and 38 days average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;San Diego: Significantly slower with 84 days median and 136 days average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chula Vista appears to have created an extremely efficient permitting process that somehow processes permits much faster than both Poway and San Diego, despite handling more than double Poway's volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fee Structure Variations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The permit fee data shows an interesting pattern:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;San Diego has lower median fees ($299) compared to Chula Vista ($457)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, Chula Vista's solar adoption rate is higher than San Diego's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests that permit fees alone don't explain adoption differences, and that processing speed may be a more significant factor than cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implications and Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data raises important questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How has Chula Vista achieved such rapid approval times, and could their process be replicated elsewhere?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What accounts for San Diego's dramatically higher average job values? Are they handling fundamentally different types of residential solar installations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does Poway's lack of fee data reflect a different approach to permitting or just a data collection issue?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much does the processing time difference (0 days vs. 84 days median) influence homeowner decisions to install solar?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that Chula Vista combines the fastest approval times with higher adoption rates suggests that streamlined permitting may be more important than lower fees in promoting residential solar adoption. San Diego's significantly longer approval times may be creating a barrier to adoption despite having lower fees than Chula Vista.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Might Explain These Patterns?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research suggests several potential factors that might be driving the higher adoption rates in Poway and Chula Vista:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Policy Initiatives&lt;/strong&gt;: In 2015, Chula Vista added a "Solar Ready" ordinance requiring residential units to be pre-wired for solar photovoltaics, while Poway established an expedited permitting process for small residential rooftop solar systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost Factors&lt;/strong&gt;: Chula Vista's significantly lower permit fees ($458 vs. San Diego's $6,420) likely reduce barriers to installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franchise Fees&lt;/strong&gt;: Chula Vista has a 2% franchise fee on energy, which may impact electricity costs and make solar more attractive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Targeted Marketing&lt;/strong&gt;: Solar companies may have concentrated their door-to-door sales efforts in Poway and Chula Vista.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Network Effects&lt;/strong&gt;: Once adoption begins in a neighborhood, visible solar installations may accelerate the "keeping up with the Joneses" effect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding the "Sweet Spot" for Solar Market Expansion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="30 percent density" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/BE-30.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why Target Areas with Moderate Building Electrification Scores&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map of the San Diego metropolitan area reveals an intriguing pattern of building electrification (BE) adoption. While our analysis has focused on the high-performing areas in Poway and Chula Vista, there's a compelling case for solar companies to direct their attention to census tracts with moderate BE scores of around 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These "middle-tier" adoption areas, highlighted in light pink on the map, represent communities that have begun their electrification journey but haven't yet reached saturation. Several factors make these moderate-adoption tracts particularly attractive targets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Growth Trajectory Advantage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Census tracts with BE scores around 30 are likely in the steep part of their adoption S-curve. Unlike high-adoption areas that may be approaching saturation, or low-adoption areas that haven't yet overcome initial barriers, these middle-adoption communities have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrated receptiveness to solar technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Established proof points with visible installations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overcome initial community skepticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not yet reached market saturation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lower Competition Landscape&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map shows these moderate-adoption tracts scattered throughout the San Diego region, including areas near El Cajon, portions of northern San Diego, and sections of Oceanside. Solar companies may find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less competitive pressure than in high-adoption hotspots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower customer acquisition costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More available qualified properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially faster permitting as these jurisdictions refine their processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Network Effect Potential&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These moderate-adoption areas represent the perfect environment for triggering "solar contagion" – the documented tendency for solar adoption to spread through social networks and neighborhoods. The map shows clusters of moderate adoption where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successful installations provide visible demonstration effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local social proof exists but hasn't saturated the market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Word-of-mouth referrals can accelerate growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neighborhood competition may motivate additional homeowners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Targeting Efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the geographic distribution on the map, these moderate-adoption areas provide an efficient targeting strategy that balances risk and opportunity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diverse geographic spread across multiple jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Varied neighborhood types from coastal to inland communities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix of newer and established neighborhoods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proximity to high-adoption areas that can serve as success models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For solar companies seeking to optimize their marketing and sales efforts, these moderate-adoption census tracts represent the "Goldilocks zone" – not too early, not too late, but just right for accelerated growth. By focusing on communities with BE factors around 30, companies can potentially achieve higher conversion rates while helping these areas advance along their electrification journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions and Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our analysis reveals that building electrification adoption doesn't follow simplistic patterns based on housing age or neighborhood wealth alone. The similar adoption rates between Poway (with older homes) and Chula Vista (with newer homes) suggest that policy interventions, permitting processes, and cost factors may play outsized roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For policymakers seeking to accelerate urban electrification, several lessons emerge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Streamline permitting&lt;/strong&gt;: Fast approvals and lower fees appear to correlate with higher adoption rates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-wiring requirements&lt;/strong&gt;: Chula Vista's "Solar Ready" ordinance may have removed barriers to installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on accessible installations&lt;/strong&gt;: Both Poway and Chula Vista show higher adoption with lower-cost installations ($15,000-$18,600) compared to San Diego's higher-cost projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More research is needed to fully understand these patterns. Future investigations could:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze energy price differences at a more granular level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track door-to-door sales campaign patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate at the Census Block rather than Census Tract level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate the longer-term impact of the 2015 ordinances in both cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As cities worldwide seek to meet climate goals through building electrification, understanding the success stories of communities like Poway and Chula Vista offers valuable insights for creating policies that accelerate adoption while ensuring accessibility across diverse housing stocks and neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="solar"></category><category term="building permits"></category><category term="solar density"></category><category term="policy"></category></entry><entry><title>Shovels Quarterly Permit Index: Q1 2025</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-quarterly-permit-index-q1-2025/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2025-05-22:/blog/shovels-quarterly-permit-index-q1-2025/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Q1 2025 Shovels Permit Index reveals a 6.1% decline in US building permits to 2.02 million, marking the third consecutive quarter of decreases. While the overall trend shows caution, the rate of decline is slowing compared to Q4 2024's 12.5% drop. Regional analysis shows significant growth in counties like Pulaski (AR), Mahoning (OH), and Salt Lake (UT), while major builders like D.R. Horton and Lennar Homes continue to perform strongly. The report highlights the impact of economic factors including inflation, interest rates, and new trade tariffs on construction activity, while noting signs of cautious optimism for the remainder of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction: Navigating a Complex Construction Landscape&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the full report: &lt;a href="https://www.canva.com/design/DAGnoXs3zUU/XDSkHlZlK47Ln77furpYLw/view?utm_content=DAGnoXs3zUU&amp;amp;utm_campaign=designshare&amp;amp;utm_medium=link2&amp;amp;utm_source=uniquelinks&amp;amp;utlId=he08fa464ee"&gt;View online&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/pdfs/Shovels_QPI_Q1_2025.pdf"&gt;download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this inaugural Shovels Quarterly Permit Index, we're going to take a look at how building permits help us understand what's happening in construction. They're like a crystal ball that shows us where the industry is headed and how people are feeling about the economy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this report, we'll explore what's been happening, including how inflation, interest rates, supply chains, and new trade rules are shaping the construction world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Picture: US Permits Are Down, But There's a Silver Lining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels Quarterly Permit Starts Q1 2025" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/spi-permit-starts-q1-2025.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what we found: The US saw about 2.02 million building permits in Q1 2025, which is down 6.1% from Q4 2024's 2.16 million. While this is our third quarter in a row of decreases since things peaked in Q2 2024, there's some good news - the decline is actually slowing down compared to the bigger 12.5% drop we saw between Q3 and Q4 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's behind these numbers? Well, we're dealing with some challenging economic conditions. Construction costs are still feeling the pinch from inflation, even though some areas are starting to improve. We're seeing some ups and downs in material prices - things like steel, lumber, copper, and aluminum - partly because of supply chain hiccups and new trade rules. The new tariffs that came in during early 2025, especially that 25% charge on steel and aluminum imports from February/March, are making homes more expensive to build. And with extra tariffs on goods from China and the UK, getting materials isn't as simple as it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the money side of things, interest rates are still pretty high in early 2025, even though the Federal Reserve made some cuts late last year. This affects both borrowing costs and how affordable homes are for buyers. Mortgage rates have been bouncing around quite a bit, mostly because they're tied to how people think inflation and Fed policies will play out. While we might see rates come down a bit by the end of the year, they'll probably stay on the higher side. Naturally, this makes folks think twice before starting new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels Quarterly New Construction Permit Starts Q1 2025" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/spi-nc-permit-starts-q1-2025.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's some encouraging news: homebuilders are feeling a bit more optimistic in early 2025! While they're still dealing with challenges like material costs, interest rates, and regulations, there's a growing sense that better days are ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at what the numbers tell us about building permits. New construction permits are following the same pattern we see in overall permits, showing us how builders adapt to the changing economy. In Q1 2025, we saw 134,000 new construction permits - that's down 7.2% from Q4 2024's 145,000 permits. While this is our third quarter of decline since we hit a high point of 190,000 permits in Q2 2024, we're starting to see the decrease slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QUARTER&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;PERMIT COUNT&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;PERMIT COUNT % CHANGE&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;NEW CONSTRUCTION PERMIT COUNT&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;NEW CONSTRUCTION COUNT % CHANGE&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,290,810&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;165,467&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-Q1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,450,247&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;186,980&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-Q2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,675,679&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;190,132&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-Q3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,467,533&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-7.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;165,124&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-13.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-Q4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,159,356&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-12.5%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;145,097&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-12.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2025-Q1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,027,611&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-6.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;134,591&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-7.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's causing this slowdown? Well, new construction is especially sensitive to changes in costs and financing. When we see inflation stick around and new tariffs on materials like steel and aluminum, it makes building new homes more expensive. Plus, higher interest rates mean it's harder for both builders to borrow money and for potential buyers to afford homes. This has led builders to take a more careful approach, which we can see in the quarterly permit numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;County-Level Permit Activity: Diverse Regional Responses to Market Conditions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shovels Quarterly Permit Starts Q1 2025" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/spi-county-map-q1-2025.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking closer at individual counties gives us some happy surprises - while some areas are facing challenges, others are showing impressive strength and growth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://felt.com/map/SPI-Q4-to-Q1-Permit-Start-Change-by-County-1k2Zb9AszSUq6M6pN29B4n3B?loc=37.49,-104.18,5.09z&amp;amp;share=1" target="_blank"&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to explore the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Counties with Substantial Growth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some counties with very low Q4 2024 permit counts (e.g., San Mateo, CA; Benton, WA) showed high percentage growth, more indicative growth from a significant base includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pulaski County, AR:&lt;/strong&gt; Increased from 67 to 582 total permits (+769%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahoning County, OH:&lt;/strong&gt; Rose from 378 to 1787 total permits (+373%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Salt Lake County, UT:&lt;/strong&gt; Grew from 212 to 946 total permits (+346%), with new construction permits surging from 4 to 51.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richmond County, GA:&lt;/strong&gt; Jumped from 771 to 2560 total permits (+232%), and new construction permits increased from 29 to 158.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Counties with Largest Absolute Permit Increases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philadelphia County, PA: +6,797 total permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Richmond County, GA: +1,789 total permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pima County, AZ: +1,778 total permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Counties with Notable Declines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Duval County, FL: -12,274 total permits (-77%), with new construction permits falling from 1523 to 466.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hennepin County, MN: -12,677 total permits (-67%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Los Angeles County, CA: -5,203 total permits (-7%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miami-Dade County, FL: -1,965 total permits (-7%), with new construction permits decreasing from 589 to 352.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This diverse performance highlights the importance of local economic factors, ongoing projects, and regional market attractiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Shovels Top 20 Contractors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Top 20 Contractors" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/top-20-contractors.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://shovels.metabaseapp.com/public/question/4301c1bb-dfcf-4784-a7c9-638de85c4f34"&gt;Shovels Top 20 Contractors&lt;/a&gt; have been busy, pulling 19,716 permits in Q1 2025 - that's a 5.9% bump up from the 18,610 permits they had in Q4 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger builders are weathering the storm pretty well - thanks to their size, strong financial backing, and ongoing projects. They've been responsible for 14% of all permits from Q4 2023 to Q1 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Builder Wins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Star Players D.R. Horton (4,237 permits) and Lennar Homes (4,020 permits) led the pack in Q1 2025!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Most Improved (Q1 2025 vs Q4 2024)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perry Homes: An 84% jump (growing from 43 to 156 permits over previous quarters, with 3 straight quarters of growth).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mattamy Homes: An 80% jump in the latest quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highland Homes: Incredible 108% growth in the latest quarter!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Special Mention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legend Homes deserves a shout for their impressive journey from 1 permit (that we can see) to 131! While the percentage looks huge (13,000%), we're keeping it in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Taking a Breather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some others are pulling back - Meritage Homes (-30.8%), M/I Homes (-20.6%), and KB Home (-27.1%) saw some dips this quarter. We'll take note of how this changes in next quarter's Shovels Permit Index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://shovels.metabaseapp.com/public/question/4301c1bb-dfcf-4784-a7c9-638de85c4f34"&gt;View the list details here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking Ahead: Staying Positive in Changing Times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The construction world is going through some changes in Q1 2025. While we're seeing folks being a bit more careful with their permits, it's totally understandable given the current situation with inflation, interest rates, and those tricky supply chain and tariff challenges, especially with steel and aluminum prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here's the silver lining - we're seeing fantastic growth in some counties, and the top 20 builders are still going strong! The experts are feeling good about construction growth in 2025, even though we've got some hurdles to jump (like finding enough workers and dealing with regulations). And as interest rates settle down, we might see more homes being built, plus some exciting stuff happening in commercial construction too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is exactly why having detailed permit data is so valuable. Whether you're spotting local growth opportunities, keeping tabs on what other builders are up to, or figuring out how big-picture changes affect your neighborhood — we're here to help you make smart choices in this exciting 2025 construction landscape!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="spi"></category><category term="permit index"></category><category term="contractor index"></category></entry><entry><title>Virginia’s Data Center Dominance: A Deep Dive into Permit Trends</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/virginia-data-center-permit-trends/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Betty Wan</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2025-08-05:/blog/virginia-data-center-permit-trends/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Explore the latest trends in Virginia’s data center market, uncovering growth areas, infrastructure investment, and hidden market indicators from permit analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All data shared was pulled directly from the Shovels platform. Start a free trial &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai/login"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virginia continues to reinforce its status as the epicenter of data center development in the U.S. Between July 2024 and July 2025, the state issued an impressive 1,239 permits explicitly linked to data centers—an astonishing &lt;strong&gt;80.4% of all such permits nationwide&lt;/strong&gt;. The uncontrolled expansion of data centers in Northern Virginia is creating significant conflict, as evidenced by new housing developments now encircled by these facilities. Bloomberg reports this situation is &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2025-07-29/loudon-county-data-center-growth-strains-residents-seeking-ai-regulation"&gt;intensifying calls for stricter regulation&lt;/a&gt;. This robust activity not only underscores Virginia’s central role in supporting the digital economy but also generated significant local revenue, totaling over $1.6 million in permit fees associated with 57 unique contractors working across 140 different locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll summarize our findings, explore proxy search terms to uncover data center permits, and share raw data pulled directly from the Shovels platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loudoun County&lt;/strong&gt; accounts for 89.67% of Virginia's data center permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; leads all cities with 442 permits (35.67%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1,599,186.68&lt;/strong&gt; in total permit fees collected  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;890 permits&lt;/strong&gt; (71.8%) currently in review or active status  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;57 unique contractors&lt;/strong&gt; involved in data center projects  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;140 unique addresses&lt;/strong&gt; with data center development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Loudoun County: The Heart of Data Center Alley&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt="Loudoun County Data Center Map" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/Loudon-map.png"&gt;
&lt;span style="font-size: 0.9em;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data centers in Loudon County, VA. Source: Google Maps&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data reveals Loudoun County as the undisputed leader, accounting for nearly 90% of all permits issued in Virginia. Sterling emerged as the leading city, with 442 permits (35.67%), emphasizing its critical role in the sector. Leesburg and Aldie followed closely, reflecting growing corridors of activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;County&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Permits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;% of Total&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cities&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Locations&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Contractors&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loudoun&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;981&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fairfax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.39%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manassas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.74%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prince William&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Others&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.74%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dominance of Loudoun County is driven by its established infrastructure, proximity to major internet exchange points, robust power availability, and supportive local policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Anatomy of Virginia’s Data Center Boom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1,239 permits mentioned above specifically mention "data center" while there are other permits that we can confidently deduce are infrastructure upgrades related to data centers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case in point, permits for infrastructure upgrades accounted for nearly 50% of all permits, reflecting the industry's maturity and increasing demand for electrical and cooling capacities. Specifically, permits for electrical infrastructure alone comprised over 27% of all permits, underscoring critical power needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top permit categories included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical (commercial alterations): 132 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New electrical infrastructure: 116 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanical upgrades: 76 permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Contractors and Mega-Projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several major contractors lead the development, including &lt;a href="https://dynalectric-dc.com/"&gt;Dynalectric Co&lt;/a&gt;., &lt;a href="https://ses-company.com/"&gt;SES Mid Atlantic LLC&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.hitt.com/"&gt;HITT Contracting Inc.&lt;/a&gt;, showcasing a specialized ecosystem geared towards high-capacity electrical and mechanical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notable mega-project sites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celtic Park Drive, Leesburg&lt;/strong&gt;: 286 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Light Speed Plaza, Sterling&lt;/strong&gt;: 246 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reeds Farm Lane, Aldie&lt;/strong&gt;: 96 permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monitoring the Market’s Pulse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the market remains strong, recent data indicates a sharp decline in permit activity from June to July 2025, a trend warranting close observation for potential market saturation or seasonal factors. Still, with over 890 permits currently under review, the future pipeline remains robust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Implications for Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virginia’s data center landscape continues to flourish, driven by concentrated expertise, infrastructure investments, and a favorable regulatory environment. As the market matures, understanding hidden trends and diversifying strategically will be essential for sustained leadership in this critical industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Developers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on infrastructure efficiency in existing facilities  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider secondary markets within Virginia  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan for phased development approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Contractors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specialize in critical infrastructure (electrical, mechanical)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build relationships with major developers  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare for continued high activity through 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Policymakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor infrastructure capacity constraints  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider incentives for geographic distribution  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure power grid can support continued growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Investors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong pipeline supports continued investment  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on companies with electrical/mechanical expertise  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor emerging locations (Aldie, Prince William County)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City-Level Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top data center cities in Virginia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; (442 permits, 35.67%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;41 unique locations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 contractors active&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Major hub for data center development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Leesburg&lt;/strong&gt; (348 permits, 28.09%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 unique locations (indicating larger projects)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12 contractors  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home to several mega-projects  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Aldie&lt;/strong&gt; (114 permits, 9.20%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 locations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 contractors  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emerging data center corridor  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Ashburn&lt;/strong&gt; (77 permits, 6.21%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23 locations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12 contractors  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historic center of Data Center Alley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Temporal Trends and Market Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monthly Permit Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data reveals interesting patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peak Activity Period (Oct 2024 - May 2025):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;October 2024: 188 permits (highest single month)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December 2024: 208 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 2025: 184 permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 2025: 167 permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notable Decline (June-July 2025):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 2025: 15 permits (91% decrease from May)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July 2025: 1 permit (partial month data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sharp decline warrants monitoring as it could indicate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasonal patterns in construction planning  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market saturation in certain areas  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economic or regulatory changes  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data collection lag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit Status Distribution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current status shows active development pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Review&lt;/strong&gt;: 890 permits (71.8%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active&lt;/strong&gt;: 135 permits (10.9%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final&lt;/strong&gt;: 41 permits (3.3%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unknown/Other&lt;/strong&gt;: 173 permits (14.0%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high percentage of permits in review suggests continued strong demand and future construction activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Project Types and Infrastructure Focus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work Category Breakdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of permit types reveals the nature of data center development:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Other Infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; (49.96%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical, mechanical, plumbing systems  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical for data center operations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. New Construction&lt;/strong&gt; (22.52%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;279 permits for ground-up builds  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significant capacity expansion  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.Alterations/Modifications&lt;/strong&gt; (22.44%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrades to existing facilities  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modernization efforts  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Tenant Fit-Outs&lt;/strong&gt; (5.08%)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customization for specific clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Permit Types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common permit types reflect infrastructure priorities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical (commercial) - alteration: 132 permits (10.65%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical (commercial): 116 permits (9.36%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical (commercial) - new construction: 91 permits (7.34%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanical (commercial): 76 permits (6.13%)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building commercial - new construction: 74 permits (5.97%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dominance of electrical permits (339 total, 27.36%) underscores the critical power infrastructure needs of data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Major Development Sites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mega-Projects by Location&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several addresses show concentrated development activity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Celtic Park Dr, Leesburg&lt;/strong&gt; - 286 permits  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11 different work types  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active from July 2024 to March 2025  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Likely a major campus development  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Light Speed Plz, Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; - 246 permits  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 work types  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single contractor (indicating unified project)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous activity through May 2025  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Reeds Farm Ln, Aldie&lt;/strong&gt; - 96 permits  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-phase development (18+ phases mentioned)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 different contractors  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three-story data center complex  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Broderick Dr, Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; - 91 permits  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IAD 291 data center project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple tenant fit-out phases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active through June 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Contractor Ecosystem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leading Contractors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top contractors demonstrate specialization in data center construction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. &lt;a href="https://dynalectric-dc.com"&gt;Dynalectric Co.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (86 permits)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical specialty contractor  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active in 4 cities  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. &lt;a href="https://ses-company.com"&gt;SES Mid Atlantic LLC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (58 permits)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 unique addresses  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 cities served  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. &lt;a href="https://www.hitt.com"&gt;HITT Contracting Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (44 permits)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General contractor  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. &lt;a href="https://theseverngroup.com"&gt;The Severn Group Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (35 permits)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focused on single location (specialized project)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notable patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electrical contractors dominate (Dynalectric, Rosendin)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix of local and national firms  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High concentration on few major projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Financial Impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permit Fee Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total Fees Collected&lt;/strong&gt;: $1,599,186.68  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Fee&lt;/strong&gt; (where recorded): $3,988.00  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permits with Fee Data&lt;/strong&gt;: 247 (19.9%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The limited fee data suggests many jurisdictions don't consistently record fees or have varying fee structures. The average fee of nearly $4,000 indicates significant revenue generation for local governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Industry Insights and Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Infrastructure Over New Builds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 50% of permits are for infrastructure improvements rather than new construction, indicating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maturation of existing facilities  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology refresh cycles  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing power and cooling demands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Geographic Concentration Benefits and Risks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loudoun County's 89.67% concentration presents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: Established ecosystem, skilled workforce, infrastructure  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risks&lt;/strong&gt;: Over-concentration, resource constraints, single point of failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Phased Development Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major projects showing 10+ phases indicate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk mitigation strategies  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demand-driven expansion  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capital efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Contractor Specialization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dominance of electrical contractors reflects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical nature of power infrastructure  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing power densities  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need for specialized expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Market Outlook and Recommendations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short-Term Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitor June-July Decline&lt;/strong&gt;: The 91% drop in permits requires investigation  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pipeline Strength&lt;/strong&gt;: 890 permits in review suggest 6-12 months of activity  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure Focus&lt;/strong&gt;: Continued emphasis on electrical/mechanical upgrades&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long-Term Strategic Implications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geographic Diversification&lt;/strong&gt;: Consider opportunities outside Loudoun County  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor Relationships&lt;/strong&gt;: Limited contractor pool creates both opportunities and risks  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology Evolution&lt;/strong&gt;: Infrastructure modifications suggest adapting to new technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Center Proxy Indicators: Identifying Hidden Data Center Permits in Virginia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, explicit data center permits represent only part of the story. Analysis of permit descriptions revealed hidden indicators—like high-amperage electrical systems and specialized cooling references—that point to additional, uncounted data center activity. At Beaumeade Circle in Ashburn, only 8 permits explicitly mention "data center," but 75 additional permits show clear data center indicators - that's &lt;strong&gt;90% hidden activity&lt;/strong&gt;. Similar patterns appear at other locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests the true scale of data center construction in Virginia might be 15-20% higher than official counts. Many data center permits don't explicitly mention "data center" in their descriptions. Through analysis of permit patterns in known data center locations, we've identified key indicators that strongly suggest data center construction or operations. These "proxy indicators" could reveal hundreds or thousands of additional data center-related permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Primary Proxy Indicators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. High-Amperage Electrical Infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"4000A service" (4000 amp) - Standard for data center power  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"3000A service" or "3000A switchgear"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"2500kw" or "2750kw generator"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple electrical "lineups" (e.g., "lineup a1", "lineup b1")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Permits Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency Dr, Sterling: Multiple "4000a service and gen" permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beaumeade Cir, Ashburn: 7+ permits for "Phase 4 lineup [X] 4000a service"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Data Hall References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"data hall" or "data halls"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"data hall fit-out"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"data hall fan wall units"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It Matters:&lt;/strong&gt; "Data hall" is industry-specific terminology almost exclusively used in data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Permits Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple "Low voltage for hvac controls for interior alteration - data halls" at Beaumeade Cir  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Level 1 data hall fit-out" at Relocation Dr, Sterling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Critical Power Infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"UPS" (Uninterruptible Power Supply)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"1000kw ups" or similar  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Medium voltage" or "34.5kv"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"switchgear" with high amperage  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"backup power" or "emergency power" at commercial scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Phase 4 lineup r1 (1) cod switchboards 3000a-480v (2) mod panels 400a-480v (2) 1000kw ups"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Specialized Cooling Systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"CRAH" (Computer Room Air Handler)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"chiller" in commercial contexts with high power  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"cooling tower" with electrical infrastructure  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"fan wall units" in data halls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why It Matters:&lt;/strong&gt; These are specialized HVAC systems designed for high-density computing environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Fire Suppression Systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"VESDA" (Very Early Smoke Detection Apparatus)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"double interlock pre-action valves"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"pre-action sprinkler" systems  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire systems specifically for "data halls"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Expansion of the existing vesda (assd) network" at Relocation Dr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Phased Development Patterns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Phase [number]" with high-power electrical  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple permits for same address with sequential phases  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"lineup" designations (a1, b1, c1, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pattern Example:&lt;/strong&gt; Beaumeade Cir shows Phase 4 with lineups a1 through r1, indicating systematic buildout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Project Naming Conventions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicator Terms:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"IAD" prefix (Internet Ashburn Data center designation)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"POD" references (Point of Delivery)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"PC" or "PowerCenter" designations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alphanumeric building codes (e.g., "usb 2.4b", "ara3a-fr1")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples Found:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Iad 055 pod 13 wmw electrical upgrades"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Pc4 3000a service: powercenter 4-1d 2233"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Geographic Patterns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;High-Probability Streets for Hidden Data Centers:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the analysis, these streets show significant "hidden" data center activity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficiency Dr, Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; - 17 implicit indicators vs 4 explicit  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beaumeade Cir, Ashburn&lt;/strong&gt; - 75 implicit vs 8 explicit  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relocation Dr, Sterling&lt;/strong&gt; - 16 implicit vs 1 explicit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommended Search Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are high and medium-confidence proxy search indicators we identified in analyzing the data. To uncover potential hidden data center projects, we recommend searching for permits containing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4000a  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3000a  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data hall  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CRAH  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vesda  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2500kw  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switchgear  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ups  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medium voltage  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lineup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these additional search terms, consider location + infrastructure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commercial permits in Loudoun County with fees &amp;gt; $5,000  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple electrical permits at same address  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Permits mentioning "phase" with electrical work  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streets with known data center presence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Validation Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To confirm these are data center projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-reference addresses&lt;/strong&gt; with known data center locations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look for permit clusters&lt;/strong&gt; - multiple high-power permits at same address  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check contractor patterns&lt;/strong&gt; - same contractors working on confirmed data centers  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze permit sequences&lt;/strong&gt; - phased development over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Estimated Hidden Volume&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the sample analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explicit mentions&lt;/strong&gt;: 681 permits at these 7 addresses  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implicit indicators&lt;/strong&gt;: 120 additional permits  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hidden ratio&lt;/strong&gt;: ~15% of data center activity may be "hidden"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extrapolating to all of Virginia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If 1,239 permits explicitly mention "data center"  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An additional 185-250 permits may be data center-related but hidden  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total real data center permit activity: ~1,425-1,490 permits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business Intelligence Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis enables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More accurate market sizing&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding true scale of data center development  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early identification&lt;/strong&gt; of new data center projects before public announcement  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; - Tracking competitor expansion through proxy indicators  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site selection&lt;/strong&gt; - Identifying areas with data center-ready infrastructure  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contractor analysis&lt;/strong&gt; - Finding specialized contractors through permit patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expand search queries&lt;/strong&gt; to include these proxy indicators  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create alert systems&lt;/strong&gt; for high-confidence indicator combinations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map infrastructure patterns&lt;/strong&gt; to predict future data center corridors  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track permit sequences&lt;/strong&gt; at addresses showing these indicators  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitor contractor activity&lt;/strong&gt; on permits with these characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true scale of data center development in Virginia is significantly larger than what appears in explicit "data center" permit searches. By using these proxy indicators, analysts can uncover 15-20% more data center activity and gain earlier insights into market developments. The concentration of these hidden permits in known data center areas validates these indicators as reliable proxies for data center construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start digging our data with a &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai/"&gt;free online Shovels account&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact"&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; today to get started. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="data-centers"></category><category term="virginia"></category><category term="permits"></category><category term="construction"></category><category term="infrastructure"></category><category term="loudoun-county"></category><category term="electrical"></category><category term="market-analysis"></category><category term="commercial-real-estate"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="sterling-va"></category><category term="leesburg-va"></category><category term="contractors"></category><category term="power-infrastructure"></category><category term="market-trends"></category></entry><entry><title>Shovels Quarterly Permit Index: Q2 2025</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/shovels-quarterly-permit-index-q2-2025/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Morgan Friberg</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2025-09-08:/blog/shovels-quarterly-permit-index-q2-2025/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Q2 2025 Shovels Quarterly Permit Index analyzes U.S. construction trends, showing high electrical, plumbing, and HVAC activity. Florida, Texas, and California dominate permit volume, with surprising growth in West Virginia. The report analyzes processing times across project types and regional ADU development patterns, providing key insights for industry professionals, investors, and policymakers in the construction sector.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;📊 &lt;em&gt;All data in this index was pulled from Shovels proprietary platform for 2025-Q2 (April 1 - June 30). While we strive for 100% permit coverage, we just aren't there yet for a myriad of reasons. We currently have 85% population coverage and add hundreds of new jurisdictions each month. Dig into our data with a &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai/signup/"&gt;free account&lt;/a&gt; and keep an eye on our &lt;a href="https://shovels.metabaseapp.com/public/dashboard/0573503d-88ac-4ba4-a723-346b55de482b?adu=&amp;amp;battery=&amp;amp;cbsa=&amp;amp;city=&amp;amp;county_or_jurisdiction=&amp;amp;date_filter=&amp;amp;electrical=&amp;amp;generator=&amp;amp;hvac=&amp;amp;new_construction=&amp;amp;plumbing=&amp;amp;property_type=&amp;amp;property_type_detail=&amp;amp;remodel=&amp;amp;roofing=&amp;amp;solar=&amp;amp;state=&amp;amp;status=&amp;amp;tab=36-summary&amp;amp;window_%252F_door=&amp;amp;zip_code="&gt;coverage dashboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Shovels Quarterly Permit Index for Q2 2025, your go-to guide for all the latest construction and renovation trends happening across America. We've crunched the numbers and uncovered some pretty cool patterns in building activity, how fast permits get processed, and what's different from region to region. You'll see everything from a surprising boom in electrical permits to some unexpected states leading the pack in new construction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you're a contractor, supplier, researcher, investor, or policy maker trying to navigate today's ever-changing construction scene, we've got insights you can actually use. Let's dive into the data that's shaping the future of our buildings and homes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2025-Q2: The Big Picture&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our latest permit data reveals a comprehensive picture of construction and home improvement activity across diverse sectors during this dynamic quarter. While Reuters reports an &lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/us-single-family-homebuilding-hits-11-month-low-building-permits-slump-2025-07-18/"&gt;11-month decline in single-family starts&lt;/a&gt;—likely due to labor shortages stemming from the administration's immigration crackdown, increased materials costs, and high interest rates—the raw numbers tell a more nuanced story. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Q2 2025, Shovels recorded 712,060 permits with: &lt;code&gt;ISSUE_DATE BETWEEN '2025-04-01' AND '2025-06-30' AND APPROVAL_DURATION IS NOT NULL&lt;/code&gt;. The defined issue date range ensures we only look at permits in Q2, and the approval duration only looks at permits with a file date AND issue date. We want to report on clean data, so these parameters help weed out permits with variable quality of record keeping. Of the 712,060 permits issued in Q2, here is the breakdown of permit statuses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Permit Statuses" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-permit-statuses.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Percent&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detail&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Active&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;414288&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;58.18%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Most common: represents ongoing or in-progress permits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Final&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;266124&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37.37%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indicates permits that have been fully processed and closed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In Review&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16155&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.27%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Permits currently being evaluated&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Null Status&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13898&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.95%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No status assigned&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Inactive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1595&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.22%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Likely stagnant, cancelled or abandoned permits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper into the Q2 2025 data reveals some fascinating trends across permit types. When looking at permits issued in Q2, electrical permits are lighting up the charts with a whopping 106,784 filings - clear evidence that America is rewiring for the future. Plumbing systems aren't far behind at 72,957 permits, while HVAC work, nearly tied with plumbing, continues to flow steadily with 72,874 permits. This trifecta of essential building systems represents major investments in creating smarter, more efficient living spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Total Permits by Permit Type" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-total-permits-by-permit-type.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at permit types as a percentage of the total. Electrical systems emerge as the unequivocal cornerstone of infrastructure development, commanding an impressive 21.21% of total permits. This electrical revolution is complemented by robust mechanical and plumbing upgrades – plumbing at 14.49% and HVAC at 14.48% – highlighting a comprehensive picture of systematic infrastructure renewal. New construction (12.45%) and roofing (11.02%) round out the top five categories, revealing a nuanced approach to building and renovation that balances critical system upgrades with expansive development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Permit Type Percentage of Total" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-permit-type-percentage-of-total.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🔌 Permit Type Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical Systems Dominance&lt;/strong&gt;: Electrical, plumbing, and HVAC permits collectively represent 50.18% of all permit activities, underscoring a strategic focus on core infrastructure resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emerging Technologies&lt;/strong&gt;: Solar permits at 4.69% and heat pump installations at 1.09% signal a gradual but meaningful transition towards sustainable energy solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptive Spaces&lt;/strong&gt;: Additions (3.54%), bathroom remodels (2.32%), and ADUs (2.61%) demonstrate a dynamic approach to space utilization and home transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunbelt Surge: Regional Distribution of Permits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Florida dominates the permit landscape with 138,742 permits issued in Q2 2025, accounting for 19.48% of the national total. Texas follows closely with 120,127 permits (16.87%), while California rounds out the top three with 91,897 permits (12.91%). These three states alone represent nearly half (49.26%) of all permits issued nationwide, showcasing the concentrated construction and infrastructure activity in sunbelt states. While Louisiana (8.66%) and North Carolina (7.01%) complete the top five, the data reveals significant construction momentum across diverse geographic areas, with emerging activity in states like Virginia, Washington, and South Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📍Interactive map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Total Permits by State" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-cbK8J" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/cbK8J/3/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="756" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE_NAME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PERCENT_OF_TOTAL_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE_RANK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Florida&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;138742&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.48%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Texas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;120127&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.87%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;91897&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.91%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Louisiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;61642&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.66%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;North Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49922&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.01%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27092&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Washington&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26343&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;South Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18630&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.62%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12847&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arizona&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12397&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.74%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we graph the states by permit count, the dominance of the top states is very clear. In a striking correlation between permit activity and insurance landscape, five states – Florida, California, Texas, Louisiana, and North Carolina – not only dominate the Q2 2025 construction permit scene but also represent critical hotspots in the national insurance risk matrix. These states account for nearly 65% of total permits and are simultaneously the most complex property insurance markets in the United States, characterized by heightened climate-related risks and evolving infrastructure challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Top 25 States by Permit Count" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-top-25-states-by-permit-count.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These states represent the epicenter of catastrophe-related insurance claims. Coined an “&lt;a href="https://www.insurancebusinessmag.com/us/news/property/insurance-crisis-deepens-in-gulf-states-537234.aspx"&gt;insurance crisis in Gulf states&lt;/a&gt;,”  insurers are increasingly denying or closing claims without payment, with a significant rise in claim denial rates. Florida consistently ranks as the state with the &lt;a href="https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2025/06/property-insurance.html"&gt;highest property insurance cost&lt;/a&gt; due to hurricane risks. California stands as the second-largest insurance market in the U.S. because of high wildfire and earthquake risk exposure. Texas' large insurance market is driven by frequent wind and hail damage claims while Louisiana and North Carolina both face similar challenges with hurricane and flood risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Construction Surges in Unlikely States&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many customers want to know what percentage of permits fall under the new construction permit category. Across the 62,660 nationwide new construction permits that Shovels tracked this quarter, we've analyzed the data state-by-state to reveal where the real building action is happening. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="New Construction as Percent of Total Permits" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-HYwy6" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/HYwy6/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="734" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data reveals unexpected regional leaders in new construction activity. West Virginia stands as the surprising frontrunner with 34.67% of its permits dedicated to new builds—significantly above the national average (9.39%). This ranking is followed by a diverse group of states including Delaware (25.32%), Mississippi (20.47%), and Idaho (17.98%), which form the top tier of states transforming their built environments. The data suggests a complex narrative of economic renewal, demographic shifts, and strategic development extending well beyond previous growth centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This state-level analysis provides a more nuanced picture of construction activity across America. Rather than concentrating solely on established construction hubs, we're witnessing significant activity in previously overlooked regions. Below are the top ten states with the highest percentage of new construction permits relative to their total permit count for Q2-2025:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW_CONSTRUCTION_PERCENTAGE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;West Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34.67%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Delaware&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25.32%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.47%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Idaho&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.98%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tennessee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.77%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.68%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Michigan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.42%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;North Carolina&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15.87%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oklahoma&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15.61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indiana&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15.12%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏗️ Key Insights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;West Virginia Leads the Way&lt;/strong&gt;: With 34.67% of permits dedicated to new construction, West Virginia significantly outpaces the national average, followed by Delaware (25.32%) and Mississippi (20.47%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regional Diversity&lt;/strong&gt;: The top ten states span multiple regions including Appalachia (West Virginia), Mid-Atlantic (Delaware, Pennsylvania), the South (Mississippi, Tennessee, North Carolina, Oklahoma), and the Midwest (Michigan, Indiana).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emerging Growth Centers&lt;/strong&gt;: The data reveals significant construction activity in previously overlooked states, possibly driven by lower living costs, manufacturing growth, and strategic economic development initiatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Permit Processing: The Rhythm of Bureaucratic Efficiency&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April 2025, the White House issued a transformative &lt;a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/04/updating-permitting-technology-for-the-21st-century/"&gt;Presidential Memorandum on Permitting Technology&lt;/a&gt; that is already reshaping how building permits are processed nationwide. This comprehensive directive tackles longstanding inefficiencies in the environmental review and permitting process by mandating technological modernization across all federal agencies. By eliminating paper-based systems, reducing redundant submissions, and enhancing interagency coordination, this initiative aims to dramatically accelerate project timelines while maintaining thorough review standards. The following analysis of permit processing times reveals the early impact of these reforms and highlights significant variations across permit types and jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our initial analysis of average permit processing times revealed significant data skewing due to outliers with extended APPROVAL_DURATION (file date to issue date). For instance, ADU permits averaged 177 days, solar permits 103 days, fire sprinkler 70 days, and new construction permits an extraordinary 238 days! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand the distribution of permit approval times, we analyzed each permit type across 9 duration bins. Here’s a sample of a few permit types:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Permit Approval Distribution" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-approval-distribution.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown, processing times vary dramatically across permit types, causing average values to skew significantly higher for certain categories. To present a more accurate picture of typical approval times, we've chosen to report median processing days instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For context, the median represents the middle value when all processing times are arranged from shortest to longest, ensuring the data isn't influenced by extreme values. This means 50% of permits are processed faster and 50% slower than the median processing day reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Median Processing Days by Permit Type" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-median-processing-days-by-permit-type.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at permit processing times by permit type uncovers clear patterns. Basic permits get processed quickly - plumbing, HVAC, and heat pump permits all take just 1 day (median). Roofing and gas permits need 2 days, while electrical permits require 4 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More involved projects take longer: bathroom remodels (5 days), solar installations (7 days), and kitchen renovations (7 days). Not surprisingly, the most complex projects require the most review time, with new construction taking 18 days and ADUs needing 19 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data shows a permit system that effectively balances safety requirements with construction needs, processing simple permits quickly while giving necessary attention to complex projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PERMIT_TYPE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MEDIAN_PROCESSING_DAYS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PLUMBING&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72957&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HVAC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72874&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HEAT_PUMP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5504&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ROOFING&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55459&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16463&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ELECTRICAL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;106784&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;BATHROOM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11683&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SOLAR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23631&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DEMOLITION&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9758&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;KITCHEN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2212&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FIRE_SPRINKLER&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11604&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;POOL_AND_HOT_TUB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9810&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ADDITION&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17831&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WINDOW_DOOR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GENERATOR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3326&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NEW_CONSTRUCTION&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;62660&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ADU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13140&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's deep dive into four key permit types that provide valuable insights into current construction and development trends across the country. Our analysis of ADUs, Solar installations, Fire Sprinkler systems, and New Construction reveals fascinating patterns in processing efficiency, regional variations, and potential economic indicators that matter to builders, investors, and policymakers alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessory Dwelling Units (ADUs): The Micro-Housing Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no denying the explosion of ADU popularity in recent years. ADUs, including basement apartments and garage flats, are a proven way to increase affordable housing supply. Also known as “granny flats” and “in-law units”, they offer numerous benefits, such as reducing housing costs, supporting aging in place, and creating wealth-building opportunities. Most cities have successfully &lt;a href="https://www.illinoispolicy.org/reports/chicagos-hidden-housing-solution-how-additional-dwelling-unit-expansion-can-make-city-more-affordable/"&gt;implemented ADU programs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a total of 13,140 ADU permits issued in Q2 of 2025. Our analysis reveals significant variations in processing times across counties, with Henderson County, NC ranking first in efficiency. The data shows a strong presence of North Carolina counties (4 of the top 10) in ADU permit processing speed, while California's Orange County also ranks among the leaders at #4. In April of 2025, The House Committee on Regulatory Reform in North Carolina gave &lt;a href="https://www.wral.com/story/backyard-homes-couldn-t-be-blocked-by-north-carolina-cities-if-lawmakers-get-their-way/21982323/"&gt;preliminary approval to a bill&lt;/a&gt; that would allow many North Carolinians to build at least one ADU on their property, which might explain the high concentration in that state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This regional efficiency suggests strategic prioritization of ADUs as housing solutions, particularly in areas facing affordability challenges. The quick turnaround times reflect how local governments are streamlining approval processes to support housing density and affordability initiatives through accessory dwelling units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Top 10 Counties: ADU Permit Processing Time" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-nbQyM" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nbQyM/3/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="416" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data note: If counties tied for processing speed, the county with the higher total permits issued was ranked higher.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROCESSING_SPEED_RANK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HENDERSON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;STEUBEN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DESOTO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ORANGE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ROWAN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAYNE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LA CROSSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DARLINGTON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LEON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HARNETT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, we also report the total number of ADU permits issued per top ten counties in Q2. The data shows Los Angeles County significantly outpaced all other counties, with nearly 10 times more ADU permits than the second-ranking county. Florida appears multiple times in the top 10 (Escambia, Lee, Santa Rosa, and Indian River counties), suggesting strong ADU growth in that state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_ADU_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LOS ANGELES&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2243&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HARFORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;259&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ESCAMBIA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;257&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TRAVIS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;221&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CATAWBA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;203&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HENDERSON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;193&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LEE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SANTA ROSA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;170&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SPOKANE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;162&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;INDIAN RIVER&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;131&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solar Surge: The Green Permit Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renewable energy industry watched anxiously as the current administration took office. They anticipated a period of uncertainty, which was confirmed when the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_Big_Beautiful_Bill_Act"&gt;One Big Beautiful Bill Act&lt;/a&gt; passed in May 2025, significantly hampering renewable energy production and research across the United States. While this policy &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/16/interior-requires-burgum-sign-off-for-solar-wind-projects-00458999"&gt;began taking effect in Q2&lt;/a&gt;, its full impact won't be evident for several quarters. We'll continue monitoring solar permit trends closely in the coming months and years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q2 2025 saw 23,631 solar permits issued across the country. The data reveals California's dominance in solar permit processing efficiency, with Los Angeles County leading the rankings followed by other California counties occupying seven of the top eight positions. Florida's Hillsborough County ranks ninth, while Hawaii's Honolulu County rounds out the top ten. These rankings reflect both the growing investment in renewable energy infrastructure and the streamlined permitting processes developed in these solar-friendly and sun-drenched regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Top 10 Counties: Solar Permit Processing Time" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-JvFLs" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/JvFLs/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="415" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROCESSING_SPEED_RANK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LOS ANGELES&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PIMA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SOLANO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ORANGE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SAN DIEGO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MARIN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;VENTURA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SONOMA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HILLSBOROUGH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HONOLULU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California dominates the solar permit landscape, with Los Angeles County leading with 1,932 permits, followed by other California counties claiming six of the top ten spots. Arizona, Florida, and Texas also show strong solar adoption, suggesting broader regional momentum for renewable energy despite recent policy challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_SOLAR_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LOS ANGELES&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1932&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RIVERSIDE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;952&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SAN BERNARDINO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;630&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ESCAMBIA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;629&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PIMA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;482&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SOLANO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;428&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MARICOPA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;414&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SANTA CLARA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;BELL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ORANGE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;359&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fire Sprinkler Frontier: The Digital Infrastructure Safety Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🔥 Fire sprinklers are hot! In Q2 2025, 11,604 fire sprinkler permits illuminate a critical infrastructure trend. These permits aren't just about safety—they serve as early warning systems for commercial development, new construction, tenant improvements, industrial facility upgrades, and expansions in healthcare or education facilities. The data also indicates rapid growth in high-risk facilities such as data centers, multi-family housing, and critical infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policy makers, researchers, and insurance providers should take note: emerging indicators highlight evolving fire safety standards, particularly in wildfire-prone regions like California, where regulatory changes continue to reshape construction and risk management landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Top 10 Counties: Fire Sprinkler Permit Processing Time" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-zAxtk" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/zAxtk/3/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="415" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis reveals a diverse mix of counties with fast fire safety permit processing, with Richmond, VA leading the rankings at #1. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New York's Albany County shows impressive efficiency at #2, while Texas appears twice in the top 10 with Webb County at #4 and McLennan County at #10. The geographic distribution suggests prioritization of critical safety infrastructure across various regions, particularly in areas housing commercial and technological facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROCESSING_SPEED_RANK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;VA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RICHMOND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ALBANY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAYNE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WEBB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HENNEPIN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SEMINOLE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WELD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SANTA CRUZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LA CROSSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MCLENNAN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When turning our attention to the top ten counties based on total fire sprinkler permits issued, we see California leads with Los Angeles County issuing the most permits (1,310), demonstrating significant investment in fire safety infrastructure. Texas (Collin County and Denton County) and Florida (Escambia and Miami-Dade) both appear twice in the top ten, prominently highlighting regional focus on fire safety. Virginia's Loudoun County's presence (222 permits) correlates with the region's &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/virginia-data-center-permit-trends/"&gt;expanding data center corridor&lt;/a&gt;, which requires robust fire protection systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geographic distribution reflects areas with commercial development, technological infrastructure, and possibly regions with stringent fire safety requirements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_FIRE_SPRINKLER_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LOS ANGELES&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1310&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;COLLIN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;383&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RIVERSIDE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;285&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MARICOPA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;284&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ESCAMBIA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;256&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MIAMI-DADE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;234&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAKE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;222&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;VA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LOUDOUN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;222&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ORANGE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;214&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DENTON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Construction: Building Momentum at Record Speeds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the recent instability in the solar industry, new construction falls into uncharted territory as &lt;a href="https://www.realestatenews.com/2025/03/18/new-construction-momentum-stalls-as-costs-expected-to-rise"&gt;tariffs are estimated to add $9,200 to the cost of a new home&lt;/a&gt;. Increased existing-home listings also creates competition for new homes, which could make it a challenging future for home builders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q2 2025 saw 62,660 new construction permits issued nationwide. In regards to median processing times, the data reveals Texas's Hidalgo County leading the rankings at #1, with Nevada's Clark County following at #2. Similar to the ADU permit processing times, North Carolina appears prominently with four counties (Pitt, Wayne, Columbus, and Rowan) in the top 10, demonstrating the state's efficient permitting processes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Top 10 Counties: New Construction Permit Processing Time" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-piyBP" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/piyBP/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="415" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROCESSING_SPEED_RANK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HIDALGO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NV&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CLARK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PITT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;BURLEIGH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAYNE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;COLUMBUS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;VA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RICHMOND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MOBILE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LINN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ROWAN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the top counties for total new construction permits, Southeastern states dominate, with Florida's Escambia County leading (2,554 permits). Louisiana's St. Tammany Parish (2,100) and Texas's Travis County (2,127) follow closely. The data suggests significant construction in hurricane-prone regions, with North Carolina (Catawba: 983, Wake: 832), Florida (Santa Rosa: 683), and South Carolina (Spartanburg: 712) all showing substantial activity, likely representing both recovery efforts and population growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_NEW_CONSTRUCTION_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ESCAMBIA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2554&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TRAVIS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2127&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ST. TAMMANY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CATAWBA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;983&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FORT BEND&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;836&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAKE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;832&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CLAY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;758&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SPARTANBURG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;712&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SANTA ROSA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;683&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ID&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CANYON&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;655&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Roofing Resilience: A State-by-State Infrastructure Narrative&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at roofing permits in Q2 2025, we see one clear story: Florida is booming. The Sunshine State was issued a whopping 42.88% of all roofing permits nationwide (24,818 permits). California came in second with 17.06% (9,874 permits), and Texas rounded out the top three with 16.08% (9,308 permits). When you add in Louisiana and Washington, these five states account for over 83% of all roofing permits issued. This concentration tells us where infrastructure investments are happening - primarily in states facing climate challenges or experiencing rapid growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Total Roofing Permits by State" aria-label="Choropleth map" id="datawrapper-chart-paEAw" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/paEAw/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="734" data-external="1"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}})}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL_ROOFING_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PERCENT_OF_ROOFING_PERMITS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24818&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42.88%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9874&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.06%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9308&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2604&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.50%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1747&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.02%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1192&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.06%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;950&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;705&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.22%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;488&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.84%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Construction Kingpins: Q2 Permit Performers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏅 Our analysis of 50 top contractors provides a comprehensive overview of builder permit activity. The data showcases total permits, new construction projects, and quarter-to-quarter changes between Q1 and Q2 of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The construction industry's Q2 2025 performance reveals that these 50 contractors generated 10,483 permits, highlighting the dynamic nature of residential development. Lennar Homes emerged as the clear leader, pulling 2,390 permits and solidifying their market dominance, followed by D.R. Horton with 844 permits and NVR with 678 permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View the full dataset, including all 50 contractors, &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1vFKUQ2cuzDEzExV_Yqf5AlgFioYmKgUfqmK9EpjegBU/edit?gid=1874195951#gid=1874195951"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2025 Q2 Shovels Top Contractors" src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/blog_images/2025-Q2-top-contractors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏗️ Key Insights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Leaders&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="https://www.lennar.com/"&gt;Lennar Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://drhorton.com"&gt;D.R. Horton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://nvrinc.com"&gt;NVR&lt;/a&gt; set the pace for residential construction based on Q2 total permits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standout Performers&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://drbgroup.com"&gt;DRB Group&lt;/a&gt; leads with a remarkable 131.6% increase from Q1 to Q2, followed closely by &lt;a href="http://sheahomes.com"&gt;Shea Homes&lt;/a&gt; at 129.7%. &lt;a href="http://lgihomes.com"&gt;LGI Homes&lt;/a&gt; also demonstrated significant growth at 55.8%, while &lt;a href="http://tripointehomes.com"&gt;Tri Pointe Homes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://fischerhomes.com"&gt;Fischer Homes&lt;/a&gt; showed positive trends with 46.6% and 27.3% growth, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Losing Ground&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://dsldhomes.com"&gt;DSLD Homes&lt;/a&gt; saw the most significant decline in total permits from Q1 to Q2 with a -93.0% change. &lt;a href="http://cbhhomes.com"&gt;CBH Homes&lt;/a&gt; followed with a substantial decrease of -92.2%. &lt;a href="http://legendhomes.com"&gt;Legend Homes&lt;/a&gt; also experienced a notable drop of -90.2%. &lt;a href="http://pulte.com"&gt;PulteGroup&lt;/a&gt; recorded a decrease of -84.3%, and &lt;a href="http://landseahomes.com"&gt;Landsea Homes&lt;/a&gt;' permits declined by -83.7%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Construction Champs&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="https://www.amh.com/"&gt;AMH Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://rauschcolemanhomes.com"&gt;Rausch Coleman Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.brookfieldresidential.com/"&gt;Brookfield Homes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://smithdouglas.com"&gt;Smith Douglas Homes&lt;/a&gt; (new), and &lt;a href="http://landseahomes.com"&gt;Landsea Homes&lt;/a&gt; all achieved a 100% new construction permit rate in Q2. This indicates that all of their permits in the second quarter were for new construction projects, highlighting their focus and success in this area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A Pivotal Moment in Construction: Resilience Amid Complexity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the Q2 2025 data, we see clear construction trends that matter for builders, developers, and investors. Despite challenges from new tariffs, labor shortages, and economic uncertainty, the numbers show remarkable resilience across the industry. The electrical permit surge in the Northeast, surprising new construction growth in Southeastern states, and concentrated roofing activity in climate-vulnerable regions all point to an industry that's adapting quickly to changing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren't just statistics—they're signals of where the market is heading. As permitting processes become more efficient in places like North Carolina, and as contractors like DRB Group and Shea Homes show triple-digit quarterly growth, we're seeing the industry's remarkable ability to evolve. From ADUs in Wayne County to climate-adapted roofing in Florida, each permit represents concrete market intelligence you can use to make smarter business decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; align-items: flex-start; gap: 2rem; flex-wrap: wrap;"&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex: 1 1 320px; min-width: 260px;"&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
      ❓ Have ideas for future reports? Let us know what permit data you think we should report on.
    &lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;
      Shovels tracks over 170M permits in 2,000+ jurisdictions. Dig into the data yourself with a &lt;a href="https://app.shovels.ai/signup/" target="_blank"&gt;free Shovels account&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/contact" target="_blank"&gt;contact sales&lt;/a&gt; today.
    &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex: 0 0 220px; min-width: 180px; text-align: right;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://www.shovels.ai/images/shovelsGuy-pose10@2x.png" alt="Chuck the Shovels Guy" style="max-width: 150px; width: 100%; height: auto;"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Data"></category><category term="permit index"></category><category term="contractor index"></category></entry></feed>