<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels :) - GTM</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/gtm.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2023-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Go-to-market strategies for proptech companies</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-06-22:/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn how to create an effective go-to-market plan for proptech companies that will help them reach their target audiences and maximize success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you a proptech company looking to reach your target audience? It can be a challenge to penetrate the tech landscape and get your message out there. However, with the right strategies in place, you can create an effective go-to-market plan that will make sure your message is heard loud and clear. In this blog post, we'll outline the necessary steps to take for proptech companies to effectively reach their target audiences. We'll cover understanding the proptech landscape, developing target audience personas, creating a go-to-market plan using building permits, choosing the right technologies for your proptech company, and measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read on to learn more about how you can maximize your success with these strategies and tools! And don't forget to read our &lt;a href="https://api.shovels.ai/redoc"&gt;API docs&lt;/a&gt; and check out our article on &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-contech-companies/"&gt;contech GTM strategies&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Understanding the proptech landscape&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proptech, or property technology, is revolutionizing the real estate industry. By leveraging cutting-edge technologies such as big data, cloud computing, the Internet of Things (IoT), and artificial intelligence (AI), proptech companies are creating innovative products and services that are transforming how people live and work with an emphasis on property data. In this section, we will discuss what proptech is and its different categories, the impact of proptech on the real estate industry, highlight some of the most successful proptech companies and their strategies, and share examples of how proptech is transforming how people live and work with an emphasis on property data including building permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, proptech consists of software solutions developed to improve efficiency in real estate transactions. It can be divided into three categories; product/service innovation – aimed at improving customer experiences; process automation – aimed at streamlining internal processes; and data-driven analytics – focused on gaining insights from a large amount of data to improve operations. These categories are helping to drive efficiency in both residential and commercial markets across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of proptech has been far-reaching in the real estate industry. From streamlining processes for tenants to providing more detailed insights into market trends for buyers - these technological solutions have enabled businesses to make better decisions faster than ever before. Additionally, they have allowed them to provide their customers with a better experience by utilizing tools such as virtual reality tours or digital payment options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most successful proptech companies include &lt;a href="https://www.zillow.com/"&gt;Zillow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.wework.com/"&gt;WeWork&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.compass.com/"&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.redfin.com/"&gt;Redfin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.opendoor.com/"&gt;OpenDoor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.divvyhomes.com/"&gt;Divvy&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.reonomy.com/"&gt;Reonomy&lt;/a&gt; to name a few. Each company has its own unique strategy for success but all have leveraged technology to create products that make it easier for consumers to access information about properties or facilitate transactions quickly and conveniently online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to providing convenience for consumers searching for properties or looking to close a transaction quickly, proptech solutions like building permits also benefit businesses by giving them access to up-to-date information about local regulations quickly so they can avoid compliance issues or costly delays during development projects. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.accela.com/"&gt;Accela's&lt;/a&gt; govtech permit module enables users to easily search for permits within their city or county in order to view detailed information about each permit including who applied for it when it was filed and when it was granted or denied. This not only saves time but also helps developers stay informed about local rules while planning new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, proptech offers tremendous potential both for consumers who are looking for more convenient ways of accessing information about properties or closing a transaction quickly, as well as businesses who need access up -to -date information quickly in order stay compliant with local regulations while planning projects. By leveraging these technologies, proptech companies can create effective go-to-market strategies that will help them reach their target audiences effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Developing target audience personas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing target audience personas is an important step for proptech companies to reach their customers. Personas define the characteristics of a customer segment, allowing businesses to create marketing strategies that are tailored to the specific needs and desires of that group. By understanding their target audience, proptech companies can craft effective messaging that resonates with them and helps them achieve their goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing target audience personas should be done during the planning phase of any go-to-market strategy as it will inform all subsequent decisions about how best to reach those customers. It’s also important for a proptech company to analyze customer behavior in order to determine what types of messaging they respond most positively towards. For example, understanding which channels they use most frequently and what types of content they consume can help inform which methods would be most effective for reaching them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permits are another key tool for understanding when a persona is in the market for a proptech purchase. Building permits offer insight into when people are ready or likely to invest in property technology products or services such as automated home energy monitors, smart security systems, or heat pump HVAC systems. By leveraging this data, businesses can customize their go-to-market plan accordingly and ensure that their message reaches potential customers at the right time with maximum impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, proptech companies can create effective marketing strategies tailored towards their desired audiences that will help them maximize success and reach their goals. Developing comprehensive target audience personas is key for any business looking to make an impact with its go-to-market strategy, and especially so for those operating within the ever-evolving proptech landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating a go-to-market plan using building permits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a go-to-market plan using building permits is an important step for just about every proptech company. Building permits are documents that allow businesses to carry out construction or renovation projects, and they provide valuable information on who the target market is for a particular proptech product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main types of building permits: residential and commercial. Residential building permits refer to those issued for homes, such as single-family residences or duplexes, while commercial building permits refer to those issued for large-scale projects, such as multi-family dwellings or retail stores. Understanding these permit types can help proptech companies determine which types of customers will benefit most from their products or services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if a proptech company is offering a smart home energy management system, they might look for recently approved residential building permits in order to identify potential buyers who would be interested in the product. On the other hand, if the proptech company offers a cloud-based property management system suitable for large buildings with multiple tenants, then they may look at recently approved commercial building permits in order to find potential customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there's a tool available that makes it easier to quickly find homeowners and contractors who have recently submitted or completed a building permit: Shovels. With Shovels, proptech companies can use advanced search tools and filters to narrow down potential customers based on criteria such as location and type of project (residential vs. commercial). This allows them to create targeted marketing strategies tailored specifically towards their target audiences more efficiently than traditional methods like cold calling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the right technologies like Shovels and understanding how building permits work as part of their go-to-market strategy, proptech companies can reach their target customers more effectively and maximize their success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing the right technologies for your proptech company&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right technologies for your proptech company is essential for reaching out to your target audiences and maximizing success. The technologies you choose should be tailored to the needs of your business, so it’s important to take the time to research what’s available and understand how they can work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most effective ways to reach out to potential customers is through direct mail. &lt;a href="https://www.lob.com/"&gt;Lob&lt;/a&gt; is a valuable tool for proptech companies, as it allows them to send out direct mail pieces with a home address on them. This helps build trust between potential customers and your brand, as it shows that you’re willing to put in the extra effort when communicating with them, especially when using building permits to reach out at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way of reaching out via phone or email is by using a homeowner phone and email database. These databases allow you to access contact information for potential customers, allowing you to connect directly with personalized messages that speak to their specific projects. You can also use these databases to track customer behavior over time, giving you a better understanding of who your target audience is and how best to reach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, hiring a software consultant or using your engineering team can help stitch APIs together and automate processes such as data collection and analysis. This means that all the data collected from different sources will be automatically compiled into one place, allowing you to make more informed decisions about which technologies are best suited for your business goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By selecting the right technologies for your proptech company, you can create an effective go-to-market strategy that will help you reach your target audiences and maximize success in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success is essential for proptech companies that want to maximize their return on investment. Proptech companies can use a variety of strategies to measure and optimize their success, such as regularly analyzing data, conducting A/B tests, and taking customer feedback into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analyzing data regularly is one of the most important strategies for measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. By looking at data trends over time, proptech companies can better understand how their marketing efforts are performing in terms of website visits, conversions, customer satisfaction scores, etc., as well as identify any potential issues or anomalies. This allows them to make informed decisions about how to tweak campaigns or products in order to maximize performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A/B testing is another powerful tool that proptech companies can use to measure the effectiveness of changes they have made to their marketing efforts. A/B testing involves creating two versions of a piece of content (e.g., an email) and then testing both versions on different audiences in order to determine which one performs better. This technique enables proptech companies to experiment with different approaches without having to guess what will work best for their target customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, taking customer feedback into account is essential when it comes to measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success. By asking customers questions about their experience with your product or service after they’ve used it, you can gain valuable insights into what works and what doesn’t work from a user’s perspective – information which you can then use to improve campaigns or products accordingly. In addition, using surveys or focus groups provides another way for proptech companies to gain insights into what would improve the customer experience and increase engagement rates with their offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the right technologies and following these strategies for measuring and optimizing your go-to-market success, proptech companies can ensure that they reach the right audiences with the right message at the right time - helping them maximize their return on investment in this rapidly growing industry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="GTM"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category></entry><entry><title>Go-to-market strategies for contech companies</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-contech-companies/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-07-10:/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-contech-companies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Grow your contech startup with this comprehensive guide to go-to-market strategies, covering topics such as identifying target markets, developing an effective plan, and leveraging building permits to identify potential customers.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article provides a comprehensive overview of go-to-market strategies specifically tailored to contech companies. We'll cover key topics such as identifying target markets, developing an effective plan, and leveraging building permits to identify potential customers. With these strategies in hand, you can create a successful go-to-market plan that will help you reach your goals and grow your business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out our article on &lt;a href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/go-to-market-strategies-for-proptech-companies/"&gt;proptech GTM strategies&lt;/a&gt;. And don't forget to check out our API docs at https://api.shovels.ai/redoc for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of contech and go-to-market strategies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go-to-market strategies are essential for construction technology (contech) companies to succeed in the competitive market. To reach their goals and grow their business, contech companies must have an effective go-to-market strategy that is tailored to the needs of their target customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing and executing an effective go-to-market strategy can be challenging. It requires careful planning, market research, and dedication. To ensure success, contech companies need to identify target markets, develop a plan of action with specific goals and objectives, leverage building permits to identify potential customers, create a marketing plan for reaching those customers, track performance metrics, and finally measure customer sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful go-to-market plan for contech companies should include several key components. First, it should clearly define the target audience and outline the customer journey from awareness through purchase. Additionally, it should include an analysis of competitive offerings in the same space as well as strategies for achieving a competitive advantage in the market. Finally, it should demonstrate how the company will monitor its progress towards its goals and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say you are a contech startup with a few million dollars in VC funding. The rest of this blog post is about how you can create your go-to-market strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Identifying your target market&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying your target market is an integral part of any successful go-to-market plan. Knowing who you are targeting, and understanding their needs, preferences, and behaviors allows you to craft a marketing message that will resonate with them and drive conversions. Here are some key steps that you should take when identifying your target market:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Define and segment the target market: Start by defining the primary demographic characteristics for your ideal customer base – age, gender, income level, education level, etc. Then segment this broader group into distinct subgroups based on psychographic characteristics such as lifestyle and interests as well as geographic criteria like location or climate. This is basic Marketing 101 stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research the needs of the target market: Once you have identified your target market segments, it's time to conduct research to understand what drives them. This could include surveying customers about their preferences or using data from online search behavior to identify what topics they are interested in learning more about. This research will help you define your message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map out the customer journey: By understanding how customers interact with products or services throughout their journey (awareness stage through purchase), you can identify areas where they may be experiencing pain points that need solutions. Analyzing competitor activity can also provide insights into potential customer behavior so you can better customize your go-to-market strategies accordingly. Knowing if your target customers already use a competing product and what they think about that product can yield powerful insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use primary and secondary research methods: Primary research involves gathering information directly from customers through surveys or interviews while secondary research involves collecting existing data from sources such as industry reports or government statistics databases. Both types of research are important when it comes to developing an accurate picture of the target market so you can effectively tailor your go-to-market approach for maximum success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking these steps to identify and understand their target market, you can create a successful go-to-market plan tailored to meet your unique goals and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Developing an effective go-to-market plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some key steps to help you create a successful go-to-market plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Align the strategy with your company's mission and objectives: Your strategy should clearly define what you are trying to achieve and how you will accomplish your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a timeline for implementation: A timeline helps make sure that tasks are completed on time, resources are allocated efficiently, and goals are met on schedule. Timelines also keep you organized in case something unexpected arises or needs adjustment along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outline necessary resources: Developing an effective go-to-market plan requires having access to the right resources. These may include personnel, marketing materials, customer service support teams, technical assistance, and budget for data acquisition, depending upon your plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Track progress &amp;amp; adjust as necessary: As you implement your go-to-market strategy, it's important to track progress against set objectives throughout the process so that you can make any needed adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leveraging building permits to identify players in your target market&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leveraging building permits to identify players in your target market can be a very powerful tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building permit data is an invaluable resource for understanding the competitive landscape and identifying potential customers that may need contech services or products. By using this data, you can gain valuable insights into your target market and use that information to better inform your go-to-market strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different types of building permits that can provide you with useful insight into your target market. Residential building permits give you a better understanding of the homeowners who might need your services, while commercial building permits provide information about businesses in the area that may benefit from your products. Additionally, local and state ordinances can give you insight into zoning regulations and other rules that could affect the success of your business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To leverage building permits for market research purposes, first look up what types of permits are available in your area, then search for those specific permit types in Shovels to get additional details about any applicable property or project. Shovels will produce lists of addresses and the contractors working on those projects. Both the building owner and the contractor can be prospective customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also track changes in permit activity over time to see if there has been any recent growth or decline in your target geographical markets. By tracking these changes, you can adjust your strategies accordingly and take advantage of new opportunities as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging building permit data to identify players in your target market, you can gain valuable insight into the competitive landscape and develop an effective go-to-market strategy tailored specifically to your own unique circumstances. Building permits are the ultimate buyer signal for contech go-to-market planning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="GTM"></category><category term="gtm"></category><category term="building permits"></category></entry></feed>