<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shovels | - Podcast</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/feeds/podcast.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.shovels.ai/</id><updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Episode 1: Using no-code solutions in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-1-using-no-code-solutions-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-09-22:/blog/episode-1-using-no-code-solutions-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Proptech startups are like other startups: resource-constrained, we try to move as fast as we can with minimal burn. We take a look at two no-code solutions, Bubble and FlutterFlow, which we used to develop our minimal viable products for Aikito and Shovels.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-Tea-on-Bubble-e29s4k0/a-aadirrd" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web development has witnessed a remarkable transformation, thanks in large part to the advent of no-code platforms. These platforms have eased the process of app development, making it accessible to a broader range of founders and startups, with all levels of coding expertise. In this, our first episode of the &lt;a href="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/"&gt;What We Learned This Week In Proptech&lt;/a&gt; we explore this shift, leveraging insights from a recent discussion which sheds light on the practical applications of no-code solutions in various business scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Inevitable Pivot to No-Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, many tech professionals, including myself, viewed no-code platforms with a certain level of skepticism. It's not uncommon for seasoned engineers to dismiss these solutions as inferior or limited​​. However, this perception is rapidly changing as the benefits and potentials of no-code solutions become more apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No-code platforms offer a way to build applications without writing a single line of code. This is 
particularly valuable for small teams or solo entrepreneurs who need to deploy functional apps quickly without the resources to hire a full-time developer​​. For instance, when faced with the daunting task of creating a web application for loan origination, underwriting, and servicing, especially under the pressure of limited resources and a tight deadline, no-code solutions like Bubble become not just an option but a necessity​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Mechanics of No-Code Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle behind no-code platforms is fairly straightforward: they provide an interface with drag-and-drop components that can be connected to various data stores. This approach simplifies the development process to the point where hosting is also taken care of by the platform itself​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a setup was instrumental when my co-host, Fernando, needed to pivot his business model due to significant changes in the commercial lending environment. With most resources laid off and a pressing need to adapt quickly, no-code platforms enabled rapid development and deployment​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing the Right No-Code Platform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I dove into Reddit forums and other communities to gauge the most popular no-code platforms, &lt;a href="https://bubble.io/"&gt;Bubble&lt;/a&gt; repeatedly came up as a frontrunner due to its strong footprint and search engine optimization (SEO) presence​​. Its capabilities extend to creating a blend of a marketplace and a project management tool, exemplified by a modified Upwork and Asana template​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, each no-code platform has its limitations and unique features. For example, Bubble uses its proprietary framework, which means you cannot export your code out of the platform. In contrast, platforms like &lt;a href="https://flutterflow.io/"&gt;Flutterflow&lt;/a&gt; offer the flexibility to export the code written in the Flutter language framework and continue development outside the confines of the original no-code environment​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No-Code Cost Efficiency and Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of employing no-code solutions is significantly less than hiring a developer, though it comes with a trade-off in customization. The analogy that resonates here is the difference between buying a prefabricated home and building a custom one from scratch​​. For startups and small businesses, especially in the property technology sector, the ability to quickly test and iterate on an idea without a large upfront investment is invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Reality of Tech Debt and No-Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A critical aspect of using no-code platforms is the understanding of technical debt. While no-code solutions allow for rapid deployment, they are not immune to the buildup of tech debt. Eventually, there's a need to review and refactor the functionalities built within the no-code environment to ensure scalability and efficiency​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, even with no-code solutions, a certain level of technical acumen is necessary. While platforms like Bubble and Flutterflow are user-friendly, they are still complex web applications that require some understanding of technology and design principles to use effectively​​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Verdict on No-Code Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No-code platforms are changing the landscape of app development and business operations. They empower non-technical founders and teams to bring their ideas to life, providing an avenue for innovation and entrepreneurship that was previously gated by technical barriers. The key to leveraging no-code solutions lies in understanding their strengths and limitations and using them as a stepping stone towards more sophisticated and customized solutions as the business grows and evolves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to witness the rise of these platforms, it's clear that they are not just a temporary workaround but a fundamental shift in how we approach problem-solving and development in the digital age. No-code is not just about building applications; it's about building opportunities and possibilities for a future where technology is inclusive and accessible to all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tune in to our next episode when we'll discuss fundraising in proptech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="no-code"></category><category term="coding"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 2: Fundraising in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-2-fundraising-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-01:/blog/episode-2-fundraising-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the second episode, Fernando Pizarro and I explore the complexities of fundraising in the proptech sector. We discuss the convergence of proptech and climate tech, highlighting how their ventures integrate sustainable practices into real estate technology. The episode concludes with insights into the evolving Proptech landscape, stressing the significance of strategic partnerships and a strong commitment to business goals.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Fundraising-Fun-e2a6vr6/a-aaekent" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our latest episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech," my co-host Fernando Pizarro and I, Ryan Buckley, delved into the intricate world of fundraising in Proptech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Art of Fundraising&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our conversation began with a reflection on fundraising trends. As Fernando pointed out, the financial markets for Proptech are in a state of flux, echoing my observations at Blueprint Las Vegas, where venture capitalists (VCs) exhibited a growing enthusiasm for the sector. This surge in interest is a positive indicator for startups seeking funding, even as the broader VC landscape faces challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando shared his experiences working at companies like Disney, National Geographic, and Yahoo, and his transition to startups in the Bay Area. His journey in gamification and Go-To-Market strategies, particularly in PropTech, offered a rich perspective on how funding dynamics have evolved over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discussed my own journey with Shovels, the company I co-founded. Our fundraising approach was shaped by lessons from my previous ventures and a determination to avoid the pitfalls I encountered earlier. I emphasized the importance of finding investors who share your vision and passion, echoing advice I received: seek investors who are "irrationally excited" about your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Climate Tech Connection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A significant aspect of our discussion revolved around the intersection of proptech and climate tech. We explored how technology in real estate inevitably ties into broader environmental concerns. Fernando’s work in facilitating business owners with sustainable space development showcases this intersection too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Shovels, the connection to climate tech is direct. We leveraged building permits to identify competent contractors, particularly those skilled in installing eco-friendly systems like heat pumps. This approach didn't just align with our business goals but also resonated with many investors' commitment to environmental sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diverse Approaches to Fundraising&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fundraising strategies, while guided by similar principles, took different paths. Fernando’s approach was deeply influenced by his rich network and personal connections. My journey with Shovels was a mix of leveraging networks and targeting investors aligned with our mission and vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of us agreed that while the process is challenging, the right investor relationship can be a game-changer. It’s not just about securing funds but about finding partners who contribute more than just capital to your venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Future of Proptech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we wrapped up our discussion, we reflected on the future of Proptech and its inevitable intertwining with climate tech. This sector is not just about innovative technology; it's also about driving meaningful change in one of the world's most fundamental industries – real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode closed with an optimistic outlook for Proptech startups. Despite the varying challenges, the opportunities in this space are immense. The key lies in understanding market dynamics, aligning with the right partners, and staying committed to the vision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="proptech"></category><category term="fundraising"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 3: Positioning in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-3-positioning-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-13:/blog/episode-3-positioning-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The third episode, Fernando and Ryan Buckley dives deep into the concept of positioning in the PropTech industry. Drawing inspiration from April Dunford's book, Obviously Awesome, they explore how positioning can significantly impact the success and perception of a product. The episode uses a compelling analogy of a bakery specializing in chocolate cake to demonstrate how different positioning (cake, muffin, lollipop) can create entirely different market segments and customer perceptions, even with the same product.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/A-Peek-at-Positioning-e2ap6fp/a-aage57p" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ever-evolving world of property technology (proptech), understanding and mastering the art of positioning can be the difference between success and obscurity. In our latest episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech," Fernando and I delve into this critical business strategy, drawing parallels between a simple bakery product and complex proptech solutions. This comparison, inspired by insights from April Dunford's "Obviously Awesome," sheds light on how strategic positioning can make a significant impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Bakery Analogy: A Lesson in Positioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine walking into a bakery that sells the most delicious chocolate cake. This cake is their flagship product, the crown jewel of their culinary expertise. Now, picture this cake being sold not just as a cake but also as a muffin or even a lollipop. This is where the concept of positioning comes into play. It's about how you frame and market your product to target different segments and create diverse customer perceptions, even if the core product remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of proptech, this analogy translates into how companies position their products or services in the market. It's not just about what you offer; it's about how you present it to your audience and how they perceive its value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shovels: An Evolution in Positioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shovels journey serves as a prime example of effective positioning. Initially positioned as an API provider, the company recognized the need to pivot towards a more market-driven offering. By rebranding themselves as a go-to-market solution for lead generation, Shovels was able to tap into a more lucrative and relevant market segment. This shift wasn't just a change in our marketing strategy; it was a strategic move that aligned our product with the evolving needs of our customers and the market at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This evolution in positioning demonstrates the importance of being agile and responsive to market trends. Shovels listened to customer feedback, understood the changing landscape of proptech, and adapted their positioning accordingly. It's a testament to the fact that in the fast-paced world of technology, flexibility and adaptability are key to survival and success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aikito: Adapting to Market Needs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aikito's story is another compelling case of strategic positioning. Initially offering financing solutions, the company pivoted to providing project management and contractor connections. This change was driven by a deep understanding of their customers' evolving needs and the market dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aikito's shift highlights a critical aspect of positioning: it's an ongoing process. As markets change and customer needs evolve, so must the positioning of products and services. Aikito's ability to adapt and reposition itself allowed the company to stay relevant and competitive in the dynamic proptech landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Aligning with Customer Needs and Market Trends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key takeaway from our episode is the importance of aligning your product's positioning with customer needs and market trends. In proptech, where technology and customer preferences are constantly evolving, staying attuned to these changes is crucial. Whether it's through customer feedback, market research, or industry trends, understanding the ecosystem in which your product exists is vital for effective positioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positioning is not just a one-time marketing exercise; it's a strategic decision that influences every aspect of your business. It affects how you develop your product, engage with your customers, and ultimately, how your business is perceived in the market. In the fast-paced world of proptech, getting your positioning right can mean the difference between leading the market or lagging behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the art of positioning in proptech, as illustrated through our bakery analogy, is about more than just marketing. It's about strategically aligning your product with the market and customer needs. It's about being adaptable, responsive, and always willing to evolve. As proptech continues to grow and change, those who master the art of positioning will be the ones who thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore the fascinating world of proptech, Fernando and I are excited to share more insights and learnings with you. Stay tuned for more episodes of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech," where we delve into the trends, challenges, and opportunities shaping this dynamic industry!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="proptech"></category><category term="positioning"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 4: Unlocking hiring secrets in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-4-unlocking-hiring-secrets-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-20:/blog/episode-4-unlocking-hiring-secrets-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the latest episode of our podcast, we explored the nuances of hiring in the proptech industry. We emphasized the importance of attitude, potential, communication skills, and cultural fit over traditional qualifications. Our discussion highlighted how diverse backgrounds, passion, and adaptability are key to building a successful team in the dynamic world of proptech.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Is-it-possible-to-hire-well-reliably-e2b26me/a-aaha9b0" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fourth episode of our podcast, "What I Learned This Week In Proptech," we delved into a vital aspect of any business, especially in the fast-paced world of proptech: hiring the right talent. Fernando and I discussed our experiences and insights, offering a fresh perspective on this challenging yet crucial process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Understanding the Importance of Attitude over Pedigree&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first lessons we've learned is the paramount importance of attitude over academic pedigree. In proptech, where innovation and adaptability are key, a candidate's mindset can often be a greater asset than their educational background. This approach is particularly pertinent in startups, where a flexible and positive attitude is crucial for navigating the uncertain waters of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Art of Identifying Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying potential in candidates can be challenging, and we often find that traditional markers like academic achievements or previous job titles don't always paint the full picture. We've learned to look deeper, seeking signs of creativity, problem-solving abilities, and a genuine passion for proptech. These qualities often indicate a candidate's ability to grow and adapt within a dynamic field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Role of 'Homework' in the Hiring Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assigning 'homework' or practical tasks during the hiring process can be a valuable tool. This approach allows us to assess a candidate's real-world skills and how they approach problem-solving. It's an effective way to gauge not only their technical abilities but also their commitment and enthusiasm for the role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Writing Skills Matter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the remote working environment that dominates proptech, clear and effective communication is essential. We place a high value on writing skills, as they are often indicative of a candidate's ability to think clearly and communicate effectively, both of which are critical in a fast-moving and often complex industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Value of Diverse Backgrounds and Perspectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proptech, innovation is key, and diverse backgrounds can be a significant asset. We've learned to value candidates who bring different perspectives and experiences to the table. This diversity fosters a culture of creativity and can lead to innovative solutions and approaches in the proptech space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Balancing Technical Skills with Cultural Fit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technical skills are undoubtedly important, we've learned that a candidate's fit within the team and the company culture is equally vital. We look for individuals who not only have the necessary skills but who also share our passion for proptech and our vision for the future of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Passion and Curiosity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passion and curiosity are qualities we highly value in candidates. Individuals who are genuinely excited about proptech and continually seek to learn and grow within the field are likely to be valuable assets to our team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Embracing Flexibility and Adaptability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proptech industry is ever-evolving, and we need team members who can adapt to changes and embrace new challenges. Flexibility and adaptability are crucial traits that we look for in candidates, as they are essential for success in a dynamic and rapidly changing sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion: Crafting a Successful Team in Proptech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building a successful team in proptech requires a nuanced approach to hiring. By focusing on attitude, potential, communication skills, and cultural fit, and by valuing diversity, passion, and adaptability, we can assemble a team capable of driving innovation and success in the proptech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore and learn in the world of proptech, these hiring strategies will remain central to our efforts in cultivating a dynamic and effective team, ready to meet the challenges and seize the opportunities that lie ahead in this exciting field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="no-code"></category><category term="coding"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 5: Navigating the sales and CRM landscape in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-5-navigating-the-sales-and-crm-landscape-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-10-27:/blog/episode-5-navigating-the-sales-and-crm-landscape-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the fifth episode of our podcast, we explore the unique challenges of sales and CRM strategies in the proptech industry. We discuss the importance of aligning sales approaches with diverse customer needs and behaviors, and the impact of CRM choices on a company's workflow and culture. The conversation highlights the significance of structured customer relationship management in driving the success of proptech ventures.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Moving-Down-the-Funnel---Sales-Motion-and-CRM-e2baf5f/a-aai3thu" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to our exploration of the dynamic world of proptech. In this fifth podcast episode, Fernando and I dive deep into the sales cycle unique to proptech and the critical role of Customer Relationship Management (CRM) systems in this niche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proptech industry, with its distinct sales cycle and customer profiles, requires a nuanced approach to sales and CRM utilization. As a proptech / climate tech founder, I grapple with questions surrounding the uniqueness of selling in proptech. What sets it apart? How do the competitive environment, pricing constraints, and urgency affect sales strategies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando, my co-host and seasoned author and expert in sales, helps unpack these complexities. We discuss the importance of understanding different customer segments in proptech – from small businesses to large enterprises – and how their varying needs impact the sales process. For instance, an enterprise client might have different contract values and buying behaviors than a smaller business, dramatically influencing the sales approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key takeaway from our discussion is the significance of aligning sales strategies with customer needs and behaviors. This alignment is crucial for effective go-to-market strategies. As we transitioned the conversation to CRM systems, it was clear that the choice of CRM can profoundly influence a company's culture and workflow. This choice can make or break the efficiency of sales processes, especially in a nuanced field like proptech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fascinating part of our conversation revolved around the use of different CRMs. While I shared my experience with Pipedrive, emphasizing its ease of integration with Google Workspace and its cost-effectiveness, Fernando provided insights into the use of HubSpot, highlighting its robust marketing and sales hubs. This difference in choice underscores the varied needs of proptech businesses and the necessity to tailor CRM solutions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion also touched upon the importance of considering territorial aspects in sales and the potential cost implications of hiring proptech sales professionals. Understanding the local nature of proptech sales is vital, as the industry often revolves around specific geographic locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our conversation underscored a fundamental truth: in proptech, as in any industry, a deep understanding of your customer segments, coupled with the right technological tools, is key to successful sales and marketing strategies. For any proptech entrepreneurs out there, our advice is clear – invest in a CRM system that aligns with your business needs and embrace the nuances of selling in this unique industry early in your journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Every conversation should in your CRM, one way or the other," Fernando aptly notes. This simple yet powerful statement is a reminder of the critical role that structured, efficient customer relationship management plays in the success of any proptech venture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="sales"></category><category term="crm"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 6: Revitalizing urban landscapes in the age of proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-6-revitalizing-urban-landscapes-in-the-age-of-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-02:/blog/episode-6-revitalizing-urban-landscapes-in-the-age-of-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Episode 6 we explored the transformative trends in urban real estate, particularly in downtown areas like San Francisco. The discussion covered the rising vacancy rates, innovative repurposing of commercial spaces, and the evolving concept of coworking. We highlighted the significance of community in these transformations and contemplated the role of local government in shaping the future of urban landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/A-Changing-Real-Estate-Landscape-e2bik2p/a-aaissjg" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the latest episode of our podcast, "What I Learned This Week In Proptech," Fernando and I delved into the rapidly evolving landscape of urban real estate, focusing on the transformation of downtown areas. We discussed how changes in work patterns and the economic climate reshaped urban centers, especially in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Future of Downtown Areas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We operated in a space that was changing really quickly," Fernando said, highlighting the dynamic nature of real estate in today's world. The episode kicked off with a discussion about the future of downtown areas, particularly in the context of changing work patterns. Fernando shared his observations on how these shifts visibly impacted San Francisco, our home base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Real Estate Downturn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One striking point I raised was the alarming vacancy rates in San Francisco - surpassing 30%. This trend was not just a local phenomenon but a broader reflection of the global shifts in the real estate market. "It's kind of like one of those Y2K level thresholds that you just don't want to be passed," I noted, drawing parallels between the current real estate situation and past significant events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Repurposing Commercial Spaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key part of our discussion revolved around the innovative repurposing of traditional commercial spaces. Fernando mentioned Aikito's involvement in such projects, emphasizing the importance of community in reimagining these spaces. "Community was the thing that was missing since the pandemic and it's what was missing when you work from home," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;San Francisco's Resilience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the challenges, there were signs of resilience and adaptation in San Francisco. Fernando shared his recent experiences in the city, noting a surprising uptick in activity and cleanliness in areas traditionally perceived as less desirable. This observation sparked a conversation about the city's potential for recovery and transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Rise of Themed Commercial Spaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shared an interesting encounter with an entrepreneur who planned to convert a major building downtown into a climate-themed skyscraper. This concept of themed commercial spaces as a means to attract specific communities and businesses represented a novel approach in commercial real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The WeWork Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our conversation also touched upon the recent news of WeWork's bankruptcy, leading to a broader discussion on the future of coworking spaces. We agreed that while WeWork's model faced challenges, the concept of coworking remained relevant and was likely to evolve with more sustainable business practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Role of Local Government&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the episode, we explored the role of local government in responding to these changes. I emphasized the potential of local policies to create opportunities or pose challenges in the evolving landscape of urban real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode wrapped up with us contemplating future discussions, particularly around the intricacies of commercial permitting and its impact on urban development. This conversation set the stage for more in-depth exploration of the intersection between proptech, urban development, and community building.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="downtown"></category><category term="economic development"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 7: Exploring commercial building permits</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-7-exploring-commercial-building-permits/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-08:/blog/episode-7-exploring-commercial-building-permits/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Episode 7, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro explored the complexities of commercial building permits. They discussed the variations in permits across states, the insights gained from analyzing permit data, and the practical implications for businesses and property technology. The episode highlighted the importance of understanding permit trends and regulations in commercial construction and renovation projects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Everything-You-Didnt-Know-About-Building-Permits-e2bnefv/a-aajc8k4" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to our latest installment of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech." In this episode, Fernando Pizarro and I, Ryan Buckley, delve into a topic that's both fascinating and crucial in the realm of property technology: commercial building permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of a building permit might seem straightforward at first glance, but as we explored, it's anything but. We started by defining what a building permit is. Essentially, it's a document issued by local government authorities to regulate and track construction activities. This aspect of local regulation is vital because building standards and requirements can vary significantly from one jurisdiction to another. As I often say, the devil is in the details, and in the case of building permits, those details are critical for ensuring public safety and compliance with local laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando brought up an interesting point about the variety of permits available. Indeed, a building permit can refer to many different things, and this diversity is a crucial aspect of understanding the landscape of commercial building permits. What we find fascinating is how these permits serve as a gateway to a wealth of data and insights into construction activities, contractor histories, and market trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During our discussion, we uncovered some intriguing insights, particularly about commercial permits. For instance, the proportion of commercial permits varies significantly across states. Surprisingly, states like Alaska have a higher percentage of commercial permits relative to residential ones, likely due to the lower overall number of residential permits. This finding led us to consider the implications of such data for businesses and contractors operating in different states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation then shifted to the practical applications of this data. For instance, by analyzing permits, we can identify trends in commercial construction, such as the prevalence of electrical work or the surprisingly low incidence of HVAC-related projects. These insights are invaluable for businesses and contractors looking to capitalize on market demands or for those in the property technology industry seeking to understand where their services might be most needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more striking revelations from our analysis was the significant variation in the time taken to approve commercial permits across different states. New York, for example, stood out with an average approval time of over 500 days for commercial permits, a stark contrast to states like California and Texas, where the process is considerably quicker. This kind of information is crucial for businesses planning construction or renovation projects, as it directly impacts project timelines and budgets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando, drawing on his experience with Aikito, provided valuable insights into how this data applies to real-world scenarios. He noted the importance of understanding these permit trends, especially in the context of renovations and conversions of existing spaces, which is a significant part of Aikito's focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our deep dive into commercial building permits revealed a complex and nuanced landscape. These permits are more than just bureaucratic necessities; they are a lens through which we can view and understand market trends, regulatory environments, and the ever-evolving world of property technology. As always, we aim to demystify these topics, providing our listeners with valuable insights and practical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="building permit"></category><category term="building contractor"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 8: Navigating commercial buildouts</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-8-navigating-commercial-buildouts/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-15:/blog/episode-8-navigating-commercial-buildouts/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Episode 8 Fernando Pizarro and I explored the intricate process of commercial buildouts, discussing the importance of choosing the right space, the role of brokers, architects, and contractors, and the complexities of permitting. We also highlighted the transformative impact of technology in streamlining these processes, reflecting on the potential efficiencies it brings to the proptech industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Opening-a-Restaurant-for-Dummies-e2c1bke/a-aakbtbq" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week on "What We Learned This Week In Proptech," Fernando and I delved into the intricate world of commercial buildouts. This topic, particularly close to Fernando's heart, unraveled the journey of a chef with a unique restaurant concept, ready to transform vision into reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our discussion began with the initial stages of a commercial buildout, where the focus lies heavily on finding and outfitting a suitable space. "It's all about turning that concept into a tangible reality," said Fernando, highlighting the importance of selecting the right location and designing the space to fit the unique needs of a business, like our chef's innovative chicken finger restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation then shifted to my experiences at Chubbles, where the week had been a mix of successes and challenges. The excitement of new subscriptions contrasted with the delays in releasing our national contractor API. "The main headache has been around infrastructure and release cycles," I said, emphasizing the complexities in technology deployment in proptech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando shared his insights on the role of commercial brokers, crucial in navigating the complex landscape of commercial real estate. "Brokers are essential in linking clients with architects, contractors, and negotiating lease terms," Fernando explained. However, he also cautioned about the delicate balance of brokers' incentives, particularly when negotiating work letters that define the condition of the leased space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also discussed the role of architects and general contractors in the buildout process. "Their expertise becomes pivotal once a space is chosen," I noted, underlining the importance of these professionals in the preliminary planning and execution stages. Fernando added, "It's a highly collaborative process involving numerous stakeholders."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key takeaways from our discussion was the significance of permits in the buildout process. "Permitting can be a complex and time-consuming stage," Fernando said, stressing the need for early engagement with architects and contractors to ensure compliance and avoid delays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the conversation wound down, we touched upon the impact of technology in streamlining the buildout process. Fernando pointed out, "Tech platforms can significantly reduce time and complexity, bringing efficiency to a traditionally manual process." This insight aligns with the emerging trends in proptech, where technology integration is revolutionizing traditional practices.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="commercial permit"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 9: Exploring AI in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-9-exploring-ai-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-21:/blog/episode-9-exploring-ai-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our latest podcast episode we discuss the evolving role of artificial intelligence in the proptech industry. We explore AI's applications in content strategy and real estate marketing, highlighting innovations like GPTs for content creation. The episode concludes with insights on the future of AI in proptech, emphasizing its potential to transform real estate and other industries.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/AI-for-Real-Estate-and-Proptech-Startups-e2c9h4q/a-aal605k" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this exciting episode of our podcast, Fernando Pizarro and I, Ryan Buckley, delve into the intriguing world of artificial intelligence (AI) and its application in the proptech industry. Our discussion comes at a critical time, following recent changes at OpenAI and the broader implications for the tech world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our conversation began with a reflection on the significant shift at OpenAI, marked by Sam Altman's departure. This event conveniently intersected with our topic of discussion - AI, offering a timely and relevant backdrop. We explored how these changes could potentially influence AI's role in various industries, especially proptech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the podcast, I shared my experiences using Google's BARD and ChatGPT. I noted the limitations I encountered with BARD, particularly in comparison to the more effective ChatGPT. This segued into a broader discussion on the practical uses of AI in proptech, including content creation and strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI's role in content marketing and SEO strategy was a key focus. Drawing from my decade-long experience as an entrepreneur, I emphasized the importance of consistent effort in SEO and content marketing. We discussed how AI can be a powerful tool in these areas, significantly aiding businesses in building and maintaining an online presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major highlight was the introduction of GPTs - custom instances of ChatGPT that remember specific prompts. This advancement in AI technology has streamlined content creation processes, allowing for more personalized and efficient use of AI tools. I shared an example of how I created a custom GPT for summarizing podcast transcripts, which significantly eased the content creation for our podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we delved into the potential of AI in real estate listings. Using AI to write compelling, keyword-dense property descriptions based on images alone showcased the technology's capacity to understand and interpret visual data effectively. This capability can revolutionize how real estate listings are created, offering both efficiency and creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode concluded with a discussion on the future of AI in proptech and other industries. We pondered the technology's evolving nature and its potential to simplify complex tasks, foreseeing a future where AI's integration becomes more seamless and indispensable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, this week's podcast offered an insightful exploration of AI in proptech. We discussed the changing landscape of AI, its practical applications in content strategy, and its burgeoning role in real estate marketing. As AI continues to evolve, its impact on proptech and beyond is bound to be profound and transformative.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="commercial permit"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 10: Navigating email marketing challenges</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-10-navigating-email-marketing-challenges/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-11-29:/blog/episode-10-navigating-email-marketing-challenges/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This episode of our podcast delves into the complexities of email marketing, highlighting the challenges of declining effectiveness despite advancements in tools and personalization. We discuss diagnostic approaches to improving campaigns, the significance of SEO in organic marketing strategies, and the importance of selecting the right keywords for successful engagement. The conversation underscores the necessity of adapting marketing strategies to effectively reach and resonate with target audiences in the proptech industry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/SEO-for-Proptech-e2cqe2k/a-aamqgs7" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 10th episode of our insightful podcast, Fernando Pizarro and I, Ryan Buckley, tackle a vital topic in today's digital marketing landscape: the effectiveness of email marketing campaigns, particularly in the proptech sector. This discussion is timely and significant, considering the evolving challenges and opportunities in digital marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We kicked off the episode with a deep dive into the declining effectiveness of email marketing. Despite advancements in tools and personalization techniques, response rates continue to fall. Fernando shared his extensive experience in email marketing since 2010, noting this trend and its impact on marketing strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drew on my experience to shed light on the intricacies of diagnosing and resolving issues in email marketing campaigns. We discussed various metrics like open rates, click-through rates, and the importance of list building. I emphasized the need for a diagnostic approach, akin to a doctor assessing a patient, to pinpoint specific areas of improvement in email marketing strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A significant portion of our conversation revolved around the relevance of content in email campaigns. We explored how subject lines might attract attention but fail to convert, highlighting the crucial balance between capturing interest and driving action. Fernando pointed out the common pitfall of focusing too much on features rather than benefits, which can hinder effective communication with the target audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transitioning from the challenges of email marketing, we shifted our focus to organic marketing strategies, particularly the power of SEO. I shared insights from my experience with Scripted.com, stressing the importance of consistent content creation as a long-term strategy. We discussed the nuances of static and dynamic content optimization, highlighting the necessity of a sustainable approach to content creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation then led to the practical aspects of keyword selection for SEO, underscoring the importance of choosing high-volume, low-competition keywords. I shared personal anecdotes about my journey with Shovels, particularly the deliberate focus on niche keywords like "building permit API," demonstrating the targeted approach needed for successful SEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our episode concluded with an exploration of the intersections between different marketing strategies, including social media and field sales. We touched on the unique challenges of reaching specific target audiences, like restaurant and bakery owners, through conventional digital marketing channels.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="email marketing"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 11: Exploring the intersection of proptech and climate tech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-11-exploring-the-intersection-of-proptech-and-climate-tech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-12-07:/blog/episode-11-exploring-the-intersection-of-proptech-and-climate-tech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this week's episode, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro delve into the promising intersection of proptech and climate tech. They discuss the impact of the Inflation Reduction Act, the role of virtual power plants, and the implications of Local Law 97 in New York, highlighting the significant opportunities emerging at this crossroads.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-Intersection-of-Climate-and-Real-Estate-e2d4i3c/a-aanqf01" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 11th episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech," I had an enlightening discussion with Fernando Pizarro about the convergence of proptech and climate tech. This intersection is creating unique opportunities and driving innovation in both sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We delved into how climate tech startups, particularly those at the intersection with proptech, are gaining momentum. I shared insights from my experiences and meetings, emphasizing the perfect timing for such ventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The timing of climate tech startups, particularly the intersection of climate tech and property tech, is just really good right now," I noted, highlighting the market readiness for these innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode also touched on the Inflation Reduction Act of 2022, which I believe plays a crucial role in this sector. "It's pumping a lot of money, tens of billions of dollars, specifically into the intersection of climate tech and property tech," I said, underscoring the significant financial backing fueling these industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then explored the emerging trend of virtual power plants and the role of software in managing and distributing energy across the grid. This highlights the increasing need for technology in efficiently utilizing renewable energy sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando shared insights on New York's Local Law 97, which mandates buildings to reduce carbon emissions. This law has sparked a surge in interest for solutions that proptech startups can provide, demonstrating the regulatory push towards sustainable practices in real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our conversation circled back to the significance of being mission-driven in the tech industry, especially in the realms of proptech and climate tech. "It's really nice to be mission driven," I reflected, emphasizing the satisfaction derived from working towards a greater good.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="climatetech"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 12: Navigating culture in proptech</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-12-navigating-culture-in-proptech/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2023-12-13:/blog/episode-12-navigating-culture-in-proptech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Episode 12 delves into the intricacies of company culture in proptech. They discuss its impact on decision-making, diversity, and sustainability, underscoring its essential role in shaping company dynamics and future growth.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the 12th episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech," Fernando Pizarro and I delved into the nuanced and pivotal role of culture in the proptech industry. We explored how culture underpins decision-making and influences company dynamics, particularly in tech startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We are talking about culture, a subject that is near and dear to my heart," Fernando began, emphasizing culture's omnipresence in every facet of a company. I echoed this sentiment, noting that culture occurs whether intentionally cultivated or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A significant part of our discussion revolved around how culture guides hard decisions. Fernando believed that culture comes to the forefront when making trade-offs. "Culture is what you fall back on when there's a tough call to make," he said, highlighting its foundational role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shared insights from the EconTalk podcast, which resonated with our topic. Andrew McAfee's thoughts on culture simplified it to 'how decisions are made.' This idea of constrained optimization, choosing paths when you can't do everything, resonated with both of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our conversation then shifted to how culture shapes companies' approach to diversity and inclusion. I shared my  view on this, favoring equality of opportunity over outcome. "I am a big believer of recruiting from non-traditional sources," I mentioned, discussing how varying perspectives enrich company culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando and I also touched on sustainability in proptech. Although sustainability isn't the only focus for my current business, its significance in the industry and its future role in our company culture were acknowledged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode concluded with reflections on the evolution of company culture. As Fernando and I shared our experiences and learnings, it was evident that culture, whether meticulously crafted or naturally evolved, is a cornerstone in the success and identity of proptech companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="hr"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 13: The Sitzer/Burnett decision</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-13-the-sitzerburnett-decision/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-01-11:/blog/episode-13-the-sitzerburnett-decision/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Episode 13 delves into the Sitzer Burnett case which challenges the traditional commission-based system in real estate transactions. This lawsuit could potentially lead to a transformative change in the industry, paving the way for more efficient and consumer-friendly proptech innovations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-SitzerBurnett-Decision-e2elt8f/a-aas6e4k" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ever-evolving landscape of property technology (proptech), 2024 has already marked itself as a year of significant developments. As we dive into the intricacies of these changes, particularly the Sitzer/Burnett case, it's clear that the traditional real estate industry is on the cusp of transformation. I explored these shifts in our latest episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech" with Fernando Pizarro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year kicked off with an insightful discussion around a pivotal lawsuit, Sitzer Burnett, that's currently in the appeal process in Missouri. The crux of this case lies in challenging the commission-based system prevalent in real estate transactions. As consumers, we've been bound to this model, particularly in scenarios where sellers are compelled to pay the buyer agent's commission. This system, deeply ingrained in the industry, is facilitated by key players like the National Association of Realtors (NAR) and the multiple listing service (MLS). The NAR's substantial membership and the exclusivity of MLS access to its members create a unique dynamic in the industry, one that's now under legal scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando and I discussed the monopolistic and cartel-like nature of this setup, where the NAR and MLS seemingly manipulate prices, inflating home costs and consequently harming consumers. A striking aspect of this lawsuit is the alleged 6% 'non-negotiable and anti-competitive' tax that costs consumers billions annually. This system essentially forces buyer agents into transactions, often inflating costs by significant percentages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on our personal experiences with real estate transactions, the sentiment towards this commission-based structure has long been one of skepticism. The prevalence of startups promoting 'For Sale By Owner' (FSBO) models highlights an ongoing resistance to traditional methods. These startups, along with platforms like Redfin or Zillow, challenge the necessity of buyer agents in an era where much of the preliminary house-hunting and negotiation can be conducted independently by buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the implications of the Sitzer Burnett case extend beyond just buyer-seller dynamics. Each MLS could potentially face its own lawsuit, as seen with subsequent cases in California. This legal pushback signifies a monumental shift that could dismantle the long-standing practices of the NAR and MLS. As Fernando noted, "it's going to be a ton of lawsuits that are going to be coming down the pike," driving significant behavioral change in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repercussions of this case could remake the industry, opening avenues for proptech companies to innovate and reshape real estate transactions. We see a future where AI could play a transformative role, potentially making traditional broker systems obsolete. AI, with its capability to analyze real estate data, legal requirements, and consumer preferences, could streamline transactions, reducing costs and enhancing efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the changes aren't just confined to residential real estate. The commercial sector, including leasing, might also see increased transparency and disclosure of commission arrangements. This could directly impact my field at Shovels.ai, which deals with construction permits. The potential alignment of our services with evolving industry norms offers exciting possibilities for innovation and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we navigate these changes, we must be nimble, keeping an eye on how our companies can leverage this upheaval. For proptech companies, this period is not just a challenge but an opportunity to redefine the industry, offering more transparent, efficient, and consumer-friendly solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the legal developments in the real estate industry signal a turning point for proptech. The dismantling of long-standing practices presents a unique opportunity for innovation and growth in the sector. As we at Shovels and other proptech companies observe these changes, we are looking to capitalize on an environment that promotes transparency, data access, and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="supreme court"></category><category term="proptech"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 14: Davos and the DOE</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-14-davos-and-the-doe/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-01-18:/blog/episode-14-davos-and-the-doe/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this compelling episode, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro shared their unique experiences at Davos and a White House roundtable. Fernando highlighted the networking and insights gained at Davos, focusing on sustainability and AI, while Ryan discussed the complexities of green infrastructure and permits in a White House session. The episode underscored the growing importance of proptech in addressing global challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/A-week-of-cool-events---Dept--of-Energy-and-WEF-e2er8e8/a-aasmc7f" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest episode of "What We Learned This Week in Proptech" with Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro offered an intriguing juxtaposition of two distinct yet influential events: the World Economic Forum at Davos and a significant roundtable discussion hosted by the White House Office of Science, Transportation, and Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando's experience at Davos was nothing short of fascinating. The event, known for its congregation of government, business, and non-governmental leaders, aimed at solving global issues, provided a platform for unprecedented networking and insights. Fernando’s interactions ranged from meeting the new president of the Club of Rome, a sustainability-focused organization, to engaging discussions on topics like AI and geopolitical happenings. The event's exclusivity, combined with its high-profile attendees, made for an environment rich in opportunities and spontaneous connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the globe, I had the privilege of virtually engaging with key figures from the White House and the Department of Energy. This engagement revolved around a pressing contemporary issue: building electrification and the challenges in obtaining permits for green infrastructure projects. The discussion highlighted the complexities of zoning changes, permit approvals, and the necessity for streamlined processes. This event underscored the critical role of proptech in facilitating green initiatives, a topic close to the heart of my work at Shovels.ai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events, though contrasting in their settings, offered a shared theme: the need for innovation and collaboration in tackling global challenges. Fernando's insights from Davos emphasized the growing significance of sustainability and the urgent need for actionable solutions. My discussion with White House representatives echoed this sentiment, focusing on the bureaucratic challenges hindering progress in green infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast episode culminated in a rich exchange of ideas and experiences, illustrating the vast potential for proptech to contribute meaningfully to these global conversations. From Davos’s high-altitude discussions on global sustainability to the White House’s focus on green infrastructure and permitting, the episode painted a picture of a world increasingly reliant on technological solutions to drive progress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="davos"></category><category term="energy"></category><category term="permit data"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 15: The sexiest topic we've done so far: Zoning</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-15-the-sexiest-topic-weve-done-so-far-zoning/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-01-29:/blog/episode-15-the-sexiest-topic-weve-done-so-far-zoning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro embarked on an insightful journey through the complexities of zoning and its pivotal role in proptech. They discussed zoning's historical roots, its impact on urban planning and development, and the innovative ways technology is being used to navigate and reshape zoning regulations for a more sustainable and efficient future in real estate.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-sexiest-topic-weve-done-so-far-Zoning-e2f3k57/a-aateuqt" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro did a deep dive into the world of zoning in their latest podcast episode. They explored the historical roots of zoning, initiated in New York City in 1916, to manage urban growth and separate industrial, residential, and commercial spaces. The discussion then shifted to the implications of zoning on socio-economic dynamics, highlighting the balance between development and environmental preservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buckley shared insights into the complexities of modern zoning and its impact on property technology (proptech). He discussed the case of Houston, the largest U.S. city without conventional zoning laws, presenting a unique landscape for urban planning and development. The conversation also touched on innovative proptech startups like DeepBlocks, leveraging AI to navigate zoning compliance and enhance urban planning processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the episode, Buckley and Pizarro illuminated zoning's pervasive influence on daily life, development, and the proptech sector. They underscored the critical role of zoning in setting development guardrails and its evolving nature amidst technological advancements and urban challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="zoning"></category><category term="proptech"></category><category term="real estate law"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 16: The proptech macro investing environment</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-16-the-proptech-macro-investing-environment/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-02-05:/blog/episode-16-the-proptech-macro-investing-environment/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro offer an in-depth look at PropTech fundraising, from understanding different funding stages to analyzing current investment trends. Their discussion, enriched by Buckley's experience with Shovels and insights into investor expectations, provides valuable perspectives for startups navigating the fundraising process amidst a changing economic environment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-Proptech-Macro-Investing-Environment-e2fdeda/a-aaubg2b" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an engaging discussion on the latest trends in PropTech investment, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro dissected a recent article by Brad Hargreaves, offering a timely examination of the state of PropTech investing. The conversation, rich with personal insights and industry analysis, ventured into the nuances of fundraising, from the early stages of securing capital to the strategic moves shaping companies' futures in the PropTech landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buckley shared his journey with Shovels, detailing their fundraising progress and strategic decision-making to manage dilution and value for early and potential investors. He elaborated on the distinctions between pre-seed, seed, and Series A funding rounds, shedding light on the evolving definitions and expectations at each stage. This provided a practical framework for understanding how startups navigate the complex terrain of investment, balancing growth, valuation, and investor relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando and Ryan also explored the broader investment climate, discussing the impact of macroeconomic factors on fundraising and the sectors within PropTech drawing investor interest. They touched on the significance of AI and data management in attracting investment, highlighting the symbiotic relationship between data and AI in creating a competitive edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dialogue further delved into construction tech's rising appeal, emphasizing the industry's delayed but accelerating adoption of technology and the potential for significant efficiency gains. Buckley and Pizarro conversed about the strategic pivot from point solutions to broader platform visions, illustrating the journey from niche offerings to comprehensive solutions addressing wider market needs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="fundraising"></category><category term="seed"></category><category term="series a"></category><category term="pre-seed"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 17: The Super Bowl pre-game show</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-17-the-super-bowl-pre-game-show/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-02-13:/blog/episode-17-the-super-bowl-pre-game-show/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro discuss the significance of having a figurehead in proptech, akin to Taylor Swift in music, to elevate the industry's visibility. They explore the potential for proptech companies to feature in Super Bowl ads, reflecting on the impact of marketing in technology's success. The conversation highlights the importance of storytelling and effective marketing strategies in distinguishing proptech ventures in a crowded market, emphasizing the need for compelling narratives to connect with and captivate audiences.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Super-Bowl-Pregame-Whos-the-Taylor-Swift-of-Proptech-e2fo8rg/a-aav9701" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode, Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro discuss the Super Bowl and its impact on marketing and brand exposure. They explore the idea of a PropTech Super Bowl commercial and speculate on potential spokespersons for the industry. The conversation shifts to the importance of go-to-market strategies and the role of marketing in the success of software companies. They also discuss the value of data and marketing referrals, as well as the challenges of product launch and hiring for marketing roles. The episode concludes with their Super Bowl plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Super Bowl is a significant event for brand exposure and marketing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go-to-market strategies and marketing are crucial for the success of software companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data and marketing referrals are becoming increasingly valuable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The narrative and storytelling in marketing play a vital role in capturing audience attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;00:00 Introduction and Super Bowl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;01:09 The Taylor Swift of PropTech&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;02:42 Success Factors for Software Companies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;03:40 Super Bowl and the Importance of Influencers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;06:29 PropTech Super Bowl Commercial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;07:54 Potential PropTech Super Bowl Ads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;09:31 Importance of Go-To-Market Strategy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:20 Fundraising Update&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11:14 The Role of Marketing in Fundraising&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13:07 Challenges in Fundraising&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14:14 The Importance of Storytelling and Marketing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15:45 The Value of Marketing Referrals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17:13 The Increasing Value of Data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18:45 The Role of Narrative in Marketing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20:20 The Role of Scripted in Storytelling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21:16 Choosing Between Data and Marketing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22:35 The Challenges of Product Launch and Marketing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24:18 Hiring and Challenges in Marketing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;26:56 Conclusion and Super Bowl Plans&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="super bowl"></category><category term="advertising"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 18: Outbound sales masterclass</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-18-outbound-sales-masterclass/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-02-20:/blog/episode-18-outbound-sales-masterclass/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro explore outbound sales tactics in the proptech space, highlighting the evolution of sales tools and strategies over the years. They discuss the transition from manual to automated sales processes, emphasizing the role of technology in enhancing sales efficiency and personalization. Buckley shares his journey in sales and the impact of tech advancements on sales practices, while Pizarro provides insights into the blend of technology and human touch in outbound sales. The discussion includes practical tips on using tools like Clay and Lemlist to streamline outbound sales and the significance of personalized communication in engaging potential clients.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/Outbound-Sales-Masterclass-e2g20vq/a-ab01rbf" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode, Ryan Buckley shares his insights and experiences with outbound sales tactics in the PropTech space. He discusses the importance of preparation and positioning before starting an outbound campaign. Ryan explains how he builds a targeted list of potential clients using tools like Clay and Lemlist. He also highlights the use of N8N as a workflow tool to automate and manage replies. Ryan emphasizes the significance of automation and the availability of advanced tools in today's market. Overall, this episode provides valuable information on leveraging technology for successful outbound sales in PropTech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation and positioning are crucial before starting an outbound sales campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools like Clay and Lemlist can help build targeted lists and automate email sequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;N8N is a powerful workflow tool that can integrate with various apps and automate processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyzing results and iterating on the outbound strategy is essential for continuous improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation and advanced tools have revolutionized outbound sales in the PropTech space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;00:00 Introduction and Background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;06:18 Preparation and Positioning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;07:30 When to Start Outbounding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;09:20 Building the List&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:16 Using Clay for Email Addresses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13:31 Sequencing Software: Lemlist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15:24 Iterating and Scaling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19:39 Using N8N as a Workflow Tool&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25:26 Analyzing Results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;28:42 Using N8N for Reply Management&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;30:05 N8N and OpenAI Integration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;35:19 Automation and Tools in Today's Market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;36:15 Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="outbound sales"></category><category term="cold emails"></category></entry><entry><title>Episode 19: The books that saved us</title><link href="https://www.shovels.ai/blog/episode-19-the-books-that-saved-us/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Buckley</name></author><id>tag:www.shovels.ai,2024-02-27:/blog/episode-19-the-books-that-saved-us/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan Buckley and Fernando Pizarro explore the influence of reading on their professional journey in proptech, discussing key takeaways from books like The Hard Thing About Hard Things and Atomic Habits. They highlight how these books have shaped their understanding of leadership, decision-making, and personal growth, emphasizing the role of reading in acquiring knowledge and insights that are integral to success in the proptech sector.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;iframe src="https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/thisweekinproptech/embed/episodes/The-Books-that-Saved-Us-e2gc5gd/a-ab0ru02" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode, Fernando and Ryan discuss their favorite business books and the lessons they learned from them. They cover a range of topics, from leadership and decision-making to habits and building successful startups. The books they discuss include 'The Hard Thing About Hard Things' by Ben Horowitz, 'Atomic Habits' by James Clear, 'Zero to One' by Peter Thiel, and 'Predictable Revenue' by Aaron Ross. They highlight the importance of embracing challenges, focusing on process over outcomes, and creating original work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embrace the difficulties and challenges in business, as they can lead to personal and professional growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on building effective habits and processes, as they can have a big cumulative impact over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the difference between zero-to-one and one-to-end businesses, and the value of creating something original.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specialize and optimize different parts of your sales process to improve conversion rates and drive predictable revenue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;00:00 Introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;00:30 Discussing Favorite Business Books&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;05:39 Choosing Business Books&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;08:38 The Hard Thing About Hard Things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14:55 Atomic Habits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;19:41 Zero to One&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25:43 Predictable Revenue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31:36 Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="book club"></category><category term="sales books"></category><category term="marketing books"></category><category term="business books"></category></entry></feed>